<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A relation of the coasts of Africk called Guinee with a description of the countreys, manners and customs of the inhabitants, of the productions of the earth, and the merchandise and commodities it affords : with some historical observations upon the coasts : being collected in a voyage made by the Sieur Villault ... in the years 1666, and 1667 / written in French, and faithfully Englished.</title>
            <title>Relation des costes d'Afrique appellées Guinée. English</title>
            <author>Villault, Nicolas, sieur de Bellefond, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1670</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 248 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 145 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64941</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V388</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3207</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12083588</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12083588</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53662</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64941)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53662)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 587:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A relation of the coasts of Africk called Guinee with a description of the countreys, manners and customs of the inhabitants, of the productions of the earth, and the merchandise and commodities it affords : with some historical observations upon the coasts : being collected in a voyage made by the Sieur Villault ... in the years 1666, and 1667 / written in French, and faithfully Englished.</title>
                  <title>Relation des costes d'Afrique appellées Guinée. English</title>
                  <author>Villault, Nicolas, sieur de Bellefond, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[8], 280 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Starkey ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1670.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title: A voyage to Guinee.</note>
                  <note>First edition in English of the author's Relation des costes d'Afrique, appellées Guinée.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Africa --  Description and travel.</term>
               <term>Guinea --  Description and travel.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:53662:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53662:1"/>
            <p>A RELATION OF THE COASTS OF <hi>AFRICK</hi> CALLED GUINEE; WITH A Deſcription of the Countreys, Manners and Cuſtoms of the Inhabitants; of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions of the Earth, and the Merchandiſe and Commodities it affords; with ſome Hiſtorical Obſervations upon the Coaſts.</p>
            <p>Being Collected in a VOYAGE By the <hi>Sieur Villault,</hi> Eſcuyer, <hi>Sieur de Bellefond,</hi> in the years 1666, and 1667.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written in French, and faithfully Engliſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Second Edition.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>John Starkey</hi> at the <hi>Mitre</hi> in <hi>Fleet-street</hi> near <hi>Temple-Barr,</hi> 1670.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:53662:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53662:2"/>
            <head>THE TABLE OF CHAPTERS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>A</hi> Relation of their Voyage from <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam. page 1</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Deſcription of <hi>Cap-Verd. p. 16</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Coaſt of <hi>Malegeta,</hi> with the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Sierra-Leone. p. 29</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Deſcription of <hi>Sierra-Leone,</hi> or the Mountain of Lyons. <hi>p. 37</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cap de Monte,</hi> and its Deſcription. <hi>p. 54</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cap Miſerado. p. 66</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:53662:3"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Rio de Junco. p. 73</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Petit Dieppe. p. 76</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Rio-Sextos. p. 77</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Coaſt of <hi>Graives</hi> called <hi>Malaguette. p. 87</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Coaſt of Elephants Teeth. <hi>p. 98</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Coſte d' Or,</hi> or the Gold Coaſt, with a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of our Occurrences there. <hi>p. 114</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Deſcription of the Golden Coaſt. <hi>p. 131</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the Stature and Proportion of the People of this Countrey, of their Wit, Inclination, Induſtry, and Habits. <hi>p. 133</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of their Women, their Genius, Humour, and Habits. <hi>p. 140</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of their Mariages, and the Education of their Children. <hi>p. 145</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of their Houſes, Heuſholdstuff, Drink,
<pb facs="tcp:53662:3"/> Meat, Palme wine, and how it is made. <hi>p. 154</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of their Markets, their manner of Buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Selling, with a Deſcription of their Meaſures and Weights. <hi>p. 162</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Their Religion. Of their Sundayes, Feaſts, Devotions, Gods or <hi>Fetiches,</hi> of their Sacrifices, Prieſts, and Habits. <hi>p. 166</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of their Superſtition, their Swearing upon their <hi>Fetiches,</hi> their manner of pacify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, when they think they are angry, and the Burial of the Dead. <hi>p. 182</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of their Old Men, their Slaves, their Lame, their Servants, the Diſeaſes they are uſually ſubject to, with their Cures, and the way to prevent them. <hi>p. 195</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of their Dances, and Feaſts, both pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate and ſolemn. <hi>p. 207</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of their Exerciſes, their workmen, their Trades, their Merchandiſes, their Fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and the Duty they pay to the King. <hi>p. 214</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:53662:4"/>
               <item>Of the Kings of thoſe Countreys, their Courts, Authority, and manner of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving with their Courtiers, of their Wives and Children, of the Succeſſion of their Kingdoms, their Revenues, Feaſts, Deaths, Burials, and Elections of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther King. <hi>p. 223</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of their Nobles, the manner of their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Warr, the grounds upon which they do uſually make it, their Arms, of their Ceſſations and Peace. <hi>p. 238</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of their Civil and their Criminal Juſtice, and of the ſucceſſions of particular men. <hi>p. 249</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of their Beaſts, their Birds, and their Fiſh. <hi>p. 255</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Their Fruits, Hearbs, Bread, Millet<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Mays, their manner of ſowing and making of Salt. <hi>p. 260</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of their Gold, where it is found, and how, with the variety of works they make of it. <hi>p. 264</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:53662:4"/>
               <item>Of the Return of our Veſſel for <hi>Europe. p. 272</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Deſcription of the Iſle of <hi>Saint Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> which lyes under the Line. <hi>p. 274</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:53662:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:53662:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A VOYAGE TO The Coaſts of</hi> Africk <hi>called GUINEE.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>With a Deſcription of the ſeveral Countries, Faſhions, and Manners of the People, the Fruit and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities of thoſe parts, with the Trade and Commerce they afford.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Coaſts of <hi>Africk,</hi> commonly called <hi>Guinee,</hi> comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Tract of ground of ſeven hundred Leagues, from <hi>Cap-verd</hi> in the fourteenth degree of Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:53662:6"/> latitude, and nintieth degree of longitude Eaſt: to <hi>Cape Gonſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vo</hi> in the firſt degree of Southern la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude and 29 and a half of Eaſtern longitude, are at preſent ſo little fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented by the French (and all from an opinion they have taken up of the Malignity of the air) that it cannot (without great ſence and reluctancy) be conſider'd how long, and how unhappily they have been deſerted by them, and left as a prey to all other Nations, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving ſo much as the leaſt ſhare in the moſt advantagious Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce they afford.</p>
               <p>I muſt confeſs (having the heart and paſſions of a Frenchman) I could not obſerve without great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gret, the cunning, and artifice, wherewith the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> the <hi>Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> and the <hi>Dane</hi> had poſſeſt us of the pernitiouſneſs of the air, and the unwholſomneſs of the place,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:53662:6"/> and that with ſo much ſubtilty, they had almoſt perſwaded us out of the whole country, and to have given up thoſe few places which are ſtill in our power: a practice of that Moment, and importance to them all, that from their traffique upon theſe coaſts alone (would they be ingenious and confeſs) they muſt acknowledg they derive their moſt conſiderable profit and advantage.</p>
               <p>And indeed what Frenchman is their in the world ſo ſtupid and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitrable, that can behold ſeveral Bays along theſe coaſts, (by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants called <hi>Bays de France</hi>) and ſeveral Towns (as <hi>Petit Diep</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) declaring at this day the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nealogy of their founders, ſo intire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly abandon'd by his countrymen, that there is nothing remaining there now but their name, and an indeliable deſire in the natives, that they would conquer them again;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:53662:7"/> what Frenchman I ſay can conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this without remorſe, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member it without being affected.</p>
               <p>True it is, in the time of the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil wars wherewith it pleas'd God to afflict the Kingdome of <hi>France</hi> in the reign of <hi>Henry le grand,</hi> our expulſion in thoſe parts was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleated, for having no leiſure to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inforce ſuch garriſons as we had there from the time of <hi>Lewis</hi> the Eleventh, we were forc'd out of them all and conſtrain'd to yeild poſſeſſion to the <hi>Portugais,</hi> who at that time like an inundation over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelm'd all we had formerly gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the <hi>Golden Coaſt,</hi> and for better ſecurity of their conqueſts, built a Caſtle called <hi>St. George de la Mine,</hi> of which I ſhall give a more ample diſcription hereafter.</p>
               <p>Yet, as an argument that our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt was conſiderable there once, and that our magnificence was ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:53662:7"/> to our intereſt: it is worthy obſervation, that at this very day the <hi>Dutch</hi> make uſe of a fair Church built formerly by the <hi>French,</hi> ſtill adorned with our Monuments and Arms, and the principal Battery they have towards the ſea, is ſtill by the Natives themſelves called <hi>la batterie de France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon theſe Coaſts we had once the poſſeſſion of <hi>Akara, Carmentin, Cape-corſe</hi> and <hi>Takorai,</hi> at which laſt the <hi>Sweeds</hi> rais'd a new Fort ſince that, and upon the ruines of ours, but their late wars in <hi>Germany,</hi> (like our wars in <hi>France</hi>) having caus'd it to be neglected, and been an occaſion of interrupting its ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies, it is demolliſh'd as well as ours, and hath nothing left now but rubbiſh, to ſhew that ever it was there.</p>
               <p>Beſides this, we have ſuffered the Hollander to incroach upon us in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:53662:8"/> our days, and to poſſeſs themſelves of our Plantation at <hi>Commendo,</hi> a Town ſome two leagues diſtance from the <hi>Chaſteau de la Mine,</hi> but they were glad to attend the death of two Frenchmen who had lived there along time, built a fair houſe (of which there is nothing now ſtanding but the walls) and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported themſelves with that candor and integrity to the Natives, that they gain'd the affections of them all, and have left ſuch a perfume and reputation of the French be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind them, the <hi>Moores</hi> do glory in being call'd by that name, and will ſtill beat their drums after the mode of <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Three Months in the year, the aire of this Country is dangerous, and no more, yet ſo little then, that with the leaſt providence and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration one may preſerve himſelf as well as in <hi>France,</hi> and perhaps
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:53662:8"/> better, becauſe we have ſeveral di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes which are familiar in <hi>Europe,</hi> that are utterly unknown in this Country.</p>
               <p>But the truth is, this is but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, and the colluſion of the <hi>Dutch</hi> to put that into our heads, that ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our commerce declining in thoſe parts, they might not onely eradicate all our thoughts of reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering it again, but all our regret and concernment for the loſs of it, and they themſelves go quietly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with the commerce of ſo many Kingdoms, which is ſo prodigiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rich, I ſhall only touch upon it <hi>in tranſitu,</hi> and not tell what I ſaw my ſelf leaſt it ſhould ſeem to be incredible.</p>
               <p>Only this I ſhall be bold to offer to the conſideration of the world, whether it is probable the <hi>Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> (who are a people ſo ardently devoted to their intereſt and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:53662:9"/> that there is ſcarce any body but knows it) would upon occaſion of ſurpriſing the <hi>Fort</hi> at <hi>Cormentin</hi> upon the Golden Coaſt which was formerly theirs, have ventured upon the laſt war with <hi>England,</hi> had not their profits upon thoſe coaſts been more then ordinarily conſiderable.</p>
               <p>And indeed ſo ſweet was their trade there, and of that conſequence and importance they would never have endured either <hi>Engliſh</hi> or <hi>Dane</hi> amongſt them, had not the Natives compelled them.</p>
               <p>The inſtance I ſhall give in the ill uſage we receiv'd from <hi>the Heer Walkenbourg</hi> their General at the <hi>Mine,</hi> at a time too when we were in ſo ſtrict alliance with them, that we had eſpous'd their quarrel, and made their Enemies our own, will I doubt not be ſufficient to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, that there is nothing ſo Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous, or inhoſpitable, they will
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:53662:9"/> not act for their profit, and to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the world from the notion of a Trade that would alone maintain the Grandeur of their State, were they abſolute Maſters of theſe coaſts without any competitors.</p>
               <p>That the Genius and Humour of the <hi>Mores</hi> is more ſuſceptible of the <hi>French,</hi> then any other Nation, is manifeſt by the deſigns all Forreign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers have lay'd to keep us from thence: they know very well ſhould our commerce be readmitted, theirs would be loſt irrecoverably, and we ſhould ingroſs the vaſt quantities of Ivory and Gold-ſand, which comes yearly from thence: beſides the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the Nigroes which are tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſported for Slaves into <hi>America;</hi> and contribute exceedingly to the profit of thoſe plantations.</p>
               <p>Nor ought any difficulty in the Voyage, be able to diſcourage us, ſeeing when once arrived at the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries,</hi>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:53662:10"/> the wind ſerves always ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well, no tempeſts, no ſtorms, and ankorage is every where ſo good, that an ankor of nine or ten inches, will hold a Veſſel of 400 Tun.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Monſieur Daliez Seigneur Martel</hi> being imployed into theſe parts by the <hi>Weſt-Indy</hi> Company at <hi>Paris,</hi> and ſetting out from <hi>Amſterdam</hi> in a new Ship of four hundred Tun, (called the <hi>Europe</hi>) took me along with him in the quality of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouler for that Voyage.</p>
               <p>On St. <hi>Mathews</hi> Eve, in the year one thouſand ſix hundred ſixty ſix, I departed from <hi>Paris</hi> in order to my imployment, and arrived at <hi>Bruſſels</hi> the Saturday after, the next night paſſing to <hi>Antwerp,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Roterdam,</hi> I came ſafely to <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam</hi> on the 13th of <hi>September</hi> where having ſpent ſome weeks with the reſt of our Officers in frait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Ship, I departed with the <pb n="11" facs="tcp:53662:10"/> 
                  <hi>Heer Vanteſck,</hi> the <hi>Heer Willembourg</hi> (our Captain,) the <hi>Heer Vander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg,</hi> and <hi>Mounſieur Mathews</hi> (our Secretary) for the <hi>Texel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The next morning we went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board, and on the 13 of <hi>November</hi> with a fair wind we ſet ſail, ſteer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our courſe ſouth ſouth weſt; we gave the <hi>Fort</hi> of the <hi>Texel</hi> three guns, and then put out the colours of <hi>Ostend</hi> to prevent being ſtopt, there having been an expreſs prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition for any <hi>Hollander</hi> to ſerve any forreigner in thoſe parts upon pain of death, let the pretence be what it would.</p>
               <p>Having diſmiſt our Pilot which conducted us to ſea; by degrees, and the opportunity of a miſt we paſt thorough the Channel, and (eſcap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of whom we had great apprehenſion) we came up at length to certain Iſlands about ſome 20 leagues diſtance from the River of <hi>Lisbon.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:53662:11"/>
               <p>In this place it ſeems it is a cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome amongſt the <hi>Hollanders</hi> (and punctually obſerved) to baptize ſuch of their ſeamen and paſſengers as have never paſt the Tropique or Line before, and if the Veſſel have never made that Voyage before (as ours had never done) by the ſame cuſtome the Captain is to obliged to give the Seamen ſome certain bottles of Brandy to be merry, and drink his health with all, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe he forfeits.</p>
               <p>The weather being fair, and we very much beholding to the benig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the ſun, all things were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, the Bell rung, and the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men immediately upon the Deck, and having ſlackned our Sails, they began the ceremony of Baptiſm as follows.</p>
               <p>Thoſe of the Seamen who had made this Voyage before, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the other, and tying their hands
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:53662:11"/> behind them, they took them one by one, and having faſtned a Rope under their armpits, they puld them up to the yard of the main maſt, from thence ſoucing them into the water, and then drawing them out again three or four times, ſomtimes they ducked them for the King of <hi>France,</hi> and ſomtimes for the States General, and at laſt for the Officers of the Ship, and their wives if they had any, after which they gave them a glaſs of Sack, or a diſh of Brandy, and all were good friends.</p>
               <p>The boys in the Ship were ſtript to their ſhirts, and put under a bas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, and had ſeven or eight buckets of water poured over their heads.</p>
               <p>Nor were the Officers exempt, for after their preſents of drink to the Seamen, they were contented to ſtand ſtill till they threw ſome little water upon their heads out of a glaſs or pot, which concluded the ceremony.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:53662:12"/>
               <p>This Chriſtning being over, we ſet ſail again, and by the error of our Pilots, we paſt by the <hi>Maderas,</hi> where we intended to have put in.</p>
               <p>At length we diſcovered a high foreland, and advanced within 4 leagues of it to diſcover what it was, after five hours coaſting we found by our ſounding (the water being forty fathom) and the redneſs of the ſand, that it was not the Iſle of <hi>Palma</hi> (as we imagined) but that we were got as far as the Gulf <hi>de ſainte Croix</hi> neer the Cape <hi>Geer</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the coaſts of <hi>Moroque.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Having paſt the <hi>Canaries</hi> and the Cape <hi>de Bajador,</hi> we paſt the Tropick of <hi>Cancer</hi> on the 10 of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember,</hi> and on the 12 having paſt the Cape <hi>Blanc,</hi> we came into 18 degrees of latitude, and by the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of a ſouth eaſt wind we run a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long by the ſhore till we came to the 16 degrees, at which time we
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:53662:12"/> began to deſcry the coaſts of <hi>Africk</hi> and to obſerve them ſandy and low.</p>
               <p>The 14 at ſun-riſing we found our ſelves at the mouth of the river of <hi>Senegal,</hi> about 15 degrees, where the wind falling, we endured a calm, ſo as that day nor the night following, we made no progreſs at all.</p>
               <p>On the 15th we diſcover'd <hi>Cap-Verd,</hi> which at a diſtance reſembled two Breſts, but in reſpect it was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vironed with Rocks, and not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachable without danger, we ſteer'd to the North-Weſt, and on the 16, we doubled the <hi>Cap</hi> in our paſſage to <hi>Rio-Freſco,</hi> a Town upon the coaſts of <hi>Africk,</hi> about 6 leagues from the <hi>Cap;</hi> a place where they uſually take in freſh water, and ſomtimes trade, but with little ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, the <hi>Fort</hi> and Iſland of <hi>Goure</hi> (which belongs to the <hi>Hollander</hi>) being too near.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:53662:13"/>
               <head>CAP-VERD.</head>
               <p>SO called from a perpetual ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure which embelliſhes it, is one of the pleaſanteſt and moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable places in the world. It is a Promontory which throws it ſelf a long way from Eaſt to Weſt into the Sea; the North part of it is Mountanous, and covered always with green Trees, its point to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Eaſt, is about a Mile over: it is a Rock very ſteep and ſharp towards the Sea, which with great gentleneſs bathes and waſhes the feet of it, after it has been bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and diſcuſt by ſeveral ſmaller, and conceal'd rocks that incompaſs it, and ſeem to be plac'd there by nature, on no other purpoſe but to oppoſe themſelves (in the behalf of ſo delicate a place) againſt the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:53662:13"/> fury of ſo impetuous an Element. The 2 points advancing like moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, and making as it were a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant terras or rampart walk betwixt them, yeilds a moſt incomparable perſpective thorough the trees on the Eaſt-ſide, and is no leſs beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful on the South, though the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try lies low, by reaſon of the Trees which one would think were plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by a line, if he conſiders with what exactneſs and regularity they grow.</p>
               <p>But the ſame wind which (being gentle) had indulg'd our curioſity, and given us a grateful and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat proſpect of this Cape, remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved us almoſt inſenſibly, and brought us to <hi>Goure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Goure</hi> is a little Iſland about a League in circumference, and three Leagues diſtant from <hi>Cap-Verd,</hi> 'tis ſeparated from the <hi>Terraſirma</hi> by a little arm of the Sea, about half a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:53662:14"/> League over. At preſent it belongs to the <hi>Hollander,</hi> who on a mountain on the weſt-ſide has built a Fort, on the Eaſt it is low, has a good Port on the South, and good Ankorage.</p>
               <p>We ſaluted the Fort with five pieces of Canon, and received as many from them; we gave them 3. more by way of thanks, and that they might not ſeem to be behind us in civility, they return'd us one more, and ſet up the <hi>Dutch</hi> Standard.</p>
               <p>A while after the Governor ſent out his Boat to inquire what we were, and what news; he that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded it ſpake very good <hi>French,</hi> and it fell to my ſhare to entertain him a good while. Our diſcourſe was about <hi>Cap-Verd,</hi> and <hi>Le-Segnal,</hi> which he cry'd up to me as the moſt pleaſant part of the world, and the beſt for trade, and told me, that at long run the French would carry it from every body.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:53662:14"/>
               <p>For <hi>Cap-Verd,</hi> that they whch loved hunting, might abundantly divert themſelves there, that there was plenty of game, as Partridge, Hares, Harts, Roe-Bucks, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral other Animals very good meat, though utterly unknown in <hi>Europe.</hi> That the <hi>Moors</hi> were not to be fear'd, and that there was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent fiſhing.</p>
               <p>After Dinner he return'd to the Fort, deſiring us to go on to <hi>Gambay</hi> where the <hi>Engliſh</hi> had a ſmall Fort with eight pieces of Canon plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the Government worth 2000 <hi>l. per ann.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rio-Freſca,</hi> is a Town in <hi>Africk,</hi> near which, we came to Anchor in the <hi>Bay de France,</hi> which is firm and gravelly at the bottome, and is ſix Fathoms deep at low water.</p>
               <p>After Dinner our Secretary was ſent on Shore to carry the <hi>Alcair,</hi> or Governor, his Preſents, (which were
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:53662:15"/> Knives, and Brandy) and to take a view of what Commodities they had there and to procure freſh meat.</p>
               <p>At his return, he told us the <hi>Alcair</hi> had receiv'd him very civilly in his own houſe, which is built in the midſt of ſeveral others, that he made him ſit down by him upon a very neat Mat, and regal'd him with ſuch Wine and Fruits as the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey did afford.</p>
               <p>That as to Commodities, the coaſt was at preſent unfurniſh'd, but if we would have patience for a fortnight, he would give notice to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants of the Country, who would doubtleſs ſupply us, eſpecially ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral <hi>Portugals</hi> which they then had amongſt them: and as to freſh Vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuals he would furniſh us next day.</p>
               <p>Whilſt our Notary was a ſhore, there came a <hi>Canoe</hi> aboard us from the <hi>Alcair,</hi> but ſo mann'd, as ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed me very much: they were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:53662:15"/> black, their <hi>Mine</hi> not much better than our Beggars in <hi>France,</hi> and naked as they were born, except a little linnen before.</p>
               <p>They demanded what we were; we told them <hi>French:</hi> they ask'd if we were come to ſtay, or had put in only for Proviſions; we reply'd for Proviſions, but we would return to continue; to which they anſwer'd <hi>Bon, Bon:</hi> the <hi>French</hi> are more worth than all the reſt of the World.</p>
               <p>There came ſeveral other <hi>Canoes</hi> to us with great quantity of fiſh, which they barter'd for knives and ſtrong waters, which they fancy exceedingly.</p>
               <p>That night we ſtood to our arms, apprehending ſome attempt from <hi>Goure</hi> to ſurpriſe us. The next mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, the <hi>Alcair</hi> himſelf, called <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donſech,</hi> came aboard us in our Shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lop, accompany'd with his Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, and the principal of the Town.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:53662:16"/> He was a perſon of about 35. or 40. years of age, well proportion'd, and underſtood his intereſt well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough. He was in a long white Robe made of Cotton, which came no lower than his knees, the ſleeves long and wide like a Surplice, only gather'd cloſe at the hands, about his neck great quantity of locks of Red Wool, with a <hi>Callecon</hi> of the ſame; he had a Cap upon his head not much unlike the <hi>Capuches</hi> worn in <hi>Hungaria.</hi> The Officers had all of them old Mantles of ſtript Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton about them, partly white, and part blew, not unlike our Gipſies.</p>
               <p>We made them ſit and dine with us, after which they deſir'd the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers of the Veſſel that they would return thither and continue, which we promiſing, they enter'd into a Contract of allyance, which was ſign'd and ſeal'd on both ſides.</p>
               <p>We ask'd them where their King
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:53662:16"/> was; they reply'd three days jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney up into the Countrey: That he was call'd <hi>Damel Biram,</hi> and his kingdom <hi>Caillor,</hi> that he loved the <hi>French</hi> beſt, as being more frank, and liberal, and leſs addicted to their intereſt and profit.</p>
               <p>It's a wonder to ſee theſe people, they can neither write nor read, and yet all of them ſpoke <hi>Portugais;</hi> but the <hi>Alcair, French, Engliſh,</hi> and <hi>Dutch,</hi> as perfectly as thoſe that were born there: about Noon he took his leave of us, and we fill'd him a great Gourd with ſtrong wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which he had brought full of Palm Wine, which is the beſt in their Countrey; I went on ſhore with him, and interrogating him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout thoſe following things for ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral hours, he inform'd me, that</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rio-Freſca</hi> is a Town of about 200 houſes, that it hath a conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient Harbour on the Weſt-ſide of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:53662:17"/> it, and capable of a ſhallop: That the houſes are but ſmall, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my computation, like our thatched houſes in <hi>Normandy,</hi> built only with mud and ſticks layed a croſs. That there were not above 300 men in the Town, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides women and children.</p>
               <p>The Eaſt-ſide is covered with a Wood, thorow which I paſt four or five hundred paces, and diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered large fields beyond it, which my eye could not compaſs. This Wood conſiſts of Palm-trees, and other very lofty Trees, which in <hi>Europe</hi> are unknown.</p>
               <p>The aire (though the place be fourteen degrees on this ſide the Line) is as good and as warm, as any on theſe coaſts; for which reaſon both women and men, go naked, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a little linnen before, to cover their <hi>pudibunda,</hi> which the men doe not ſcruple to laave off when they go to Sea.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:53662:17"/>
               <p>Their Religion is ſo various, and intermixt, that beſides the <hi>Portugal Catholicks,</hi> which are there in great numbers, they have other <hi>circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed Catholicks,</hi> that come near to the <hi>Jews,</hi> as alſo <hi>Mahumetans</hi> and <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters.</hi> Theſe latter have little baggs of leather which they wear con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly about their necks, and call them <hi>Fetiches,</hi> which is as much as to ſay <hi>their Gods,</hi> (as I ſhall demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate more at large in my Chapter of the Superſtition of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> which inhabit the <hi>Golden Coaſt</hi>) in which likwiſe they have ſo great confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, they beleive that unleſs it be the Whites, there is no body can doe them any harm.</p>
               <p>They eat very little fleſh, though they have Oxen, Cows, Sheep, Goats, Kids, Hens, Pidgeons, a kind of Pheſants, and ſmall Birds in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance; Their chief diet is Fiſh, as the <hi>Guilthead,</hi> the <hi>Shadfiſh,</hi> the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:53662:18"/> 
                  <hi>Pilcher,</hi> which they take day and night in great numbers, beſides ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other unknown among us. Their fiſhing is in little <hi>Canoes,</hi> cut out of the Trunk of a Tree, and made hollow, with a ſtick, (inſtead of a Maſt) ſet up in the middle when the wind is down, but otherwiſe when it is high, they ſtand right up, and row with a kind of oares, ſome four or five foot long, and as broad at the end as a good large plate.</p>
               <p>The men of this place are very perſonable and well, not many of them <hi>Camous,</hi> and from hence it is they have the beſt ſlaves in <hi>Africk.</hi> The women and daughters are for the moſt part very common, court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſolliciting of Strangers by that time they are fourteen years old, and that in the midſt of the ſtreets, ſo great a kindneſs and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination they have for them.</p>
               <p>The men have as many wives as
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:53662:18"/> they can keep, will proſtitute them for a ſmall matter, and ſomtimes offer them for nothing. They have their haire tied up upon their heads (which are always uncovered) to which they faſten certain little pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of wood, and think them great preſervatives againſt the heat of the Sun. All of them both men and women ſpeak a kind of corrupt <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugais.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The commodities this Country affords, are Skins, Gums, Feathers, Ivory, Indigo, Civet, and great quantity of a kind of Cotten cloth, ſtript with white and with blew, which is immediatly put off again at the <hi>Golden Coaſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Though they are naturally great lyars, and not to be beleived, yet it is certain the <hi>Alcair</hi> gave adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement to the Inhabitants up the country as he promiſed us, but we thought it not fit to truſt him
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:53662:19"/> according to the advice of another Veſſell of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> which made advantage thereby.</p>
               <p>We bought that day ſome Hens, Pullets, and Kids, and delayed our time ſo long on ſhore, our camerades were forced to give us a ſignal, by diſcharging a great Gun, that we ſhould come back, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending ſome miſchief might befall us from the <hi>Hollander.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That night we ſet ſayle for the <hi>Sierra-Leoane,</hi> or <hi>Mountain of Lyons,</hi> neither thinking it convenient to make up the other Rivers, or to paſs directly to <hi>Gambay.</hi> And on the ſix and twentieth of <hi>December</hi> we came to an anchor within three leagues.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:53662:19"/>
               <head>The Coasts of MALEGETA, with the Kingdom of Sierra-Leone.</head>
               <p>THe next day by the benefit of the Tyde, we came to an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor in the River of <hi>Sierra-Leone;</hi> aboot noon the <hi>Mores</hi> came aboard us to conduct us into the <hi>Bay de France,</hi> which is the 4th from <hi>Cap-Ledo</hi> at the mouth of the River.</p>
               <p>At ſix fathom deep, low water, we came to an anchor within muſquet ſhot of the fountain, where we took in freſh water, and having landed, we went that night to ſupper upon the banks of it, where we killed a Goat which came thither to drink, and found the water more pleaſant and delicious (in reſpect of our thirſt) then the beſt of our Wines.</p>
               <p>We put out the colours of <hi>Oſtend,</hi> and not of <hi>France,</hi> becauſe there
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:53662:20"/> was an <hi>Engliſhman</hi> living in one of thoſe Iſles a long time, where he had a faire houſe and four pieces of Canon, and was beſides well beloved and protected by the Kings of that Country.</p>
               <p>The next day we ſent two of our Officers up the River, about ten leagues, to wait upon the King of <hi>Boure,</hi> with our uſual preſents, and to deſire permiſſion to trade, and to furniſh our ſelves with freſh water, &amp; wood; and in the mean time our people fell to work to cut down wood, and carry water, the Notary, my ſelf, &amp; one of my ſervants, going along with them as a guard. Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring our abſence there came aboard our ſhip five or ſix <hi>Canoes,</hi> in one of which there was one <hi>John Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> (Captain of one of the Iſles in that River) who brought ſome quantity of Ivory along with him. The Captain (who was the only
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:53662:20"/> Officer aboard) received him very civilly, ſaluted him at his entrance with a volley of great ſhot, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galed him as much as was poſſible, but he bought none of his Ivory be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too dear, which gave ſo much diſſatisfaction to <hi>Mounſieur Thomas;</hi> he went away in a huff about five a clock, and landed with 15 or 16 <hi>Mores</hi> in his company, near the bank of the Fountain I have ſpoke of before. The Clerk and my ſelf were returning in our great ſhallop laden with balaſt, and advanc'd as much as the tide (which was then coming in) would give us leave, in ſo much that our ſhallop was afloat: which being obſerved by the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and his <hi>Mores,</hi> they put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into their <hi>Canoes</hi> again, and made with all ſpeed to our men, who were cutting down wood upon the banks of the Bay. At the ſame time they gave us a ſignal from the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:53662:21"/> Ship by furling our colours, which made us double our ſpeed, in appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion there might have been ſome mutiny or ſedition aboard; but when we arrived, we found it was only to give notice of the deſign of the <hi>Mores,</hi> who were ſeen making to our men with their weapons in their hands, but the man I left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind me, having his muſquet with him, ſtopt their proceedings, and the reſt defended themſelves ſo well with their <hi>Axes,</hi> that there was none wounded or kil'd of the whole company, only one antient man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a ſcratch in one of his arms. We ſail'd immediately towards them, but as ſoon as we came with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in muſquet ſhot, and they percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved our Guns in our hands, they run ſtrait into the woods, where they lay cloſe all day long, but at night we could hear them making great noiſe about the fountain a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid.</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:53662:21"/>
               <p>The next day being the 29 <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember,</hi> the Clerk, the Pilots Mate, ſeveral ſervants, and about 20 of our Seamen, went a ſhore in our ſhallop for freſh water and wood. At their landing the <hi>Mores</hi> aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned the fountain, and betook themſelves to the Woods, where they made a great noiſe likewiſe, but without any attempt, for our men having run towards them, and fired 5 or 6 muſquets at a venture into the woods, they took their heels, and from that time we heard no more of <hi>Mounſieur Thomas,</hi> nor any of his crew.</p>
               <p>After dinner our Embaſſadors returned from the King of <hi>Boure</hi>'s Court, having ſtayed there with his moſt Auguſt Majeſty but one night: but they brought moſt of the <hi>Canoes</hi> thereabout along with them, laden with Ivory, which was bought off indifferent cheap.</p>
               <p>The next day the King of <hi>Boure</hi>'s
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:53662:22"/> Brother came aboard us, and brought with him a <hi>Portugais</hi> (which we had ſeen before, and is imployed in the affaires of that Prince) we know it was ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of quality as ſoon as we diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned his <hi>Canoe,</hi> which we di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed by the ſound of his Trumpets, and immediately ſent out our boat to receive him, into which he entred with his Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet and Drum, and at his coming aboard our Ship, was ſaluted with a volley from the great Guns.</p>
               <p>The Brother of the King of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erra-Leone</hi> is a perſon of about fifty or threeſcore years of age, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins now to grow gray: his ſtature is but indifferent, but grave, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligent enough in his affairs. His habit was not much unlike that of the <hi>Alcair</hi> of <hi>Rio-Freſca,</hi> unleſs it be that the <hi>Alcair's</hi> habit was of white cloth, and this of cloth
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:53662:22"/> ſtrip'd with black and blew, he had a gray hat upon his head, a ſtick like a muſquet reſt in his hand, his Attendants had all of them Robes of Cotton cloth, only the <hi>Portugal</hi> was dreſt <hi>ala Portugaiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whileſt we were treating him, we gave him an accompt of the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of <hi>John Thomas,</hi> to which he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered that he was a mutineer and a rebel, and that in caſe wee ſhould catch him, we ſhould not only have his pardon, but thanks.</p>
               <p>After he had dined, he pulled out about twenty little ſtones, out of a little purſe, which he threw upon the Table, demanding ſo many <hi>Barres</hi> (as they call them) in diſcharge of their Kings duties, as well for the buſineſs they had nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiated with him, as for their freſh water and wood. Though theſe people can neither read nor write, yet they make uſe of this way
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:53662:23"/> of gathering their Rights, and the frequency of their Commerce with the <hi>Portugals,</hi> has brought them to talk altogether by <hi>Barres,</hi> which is the word they do moſt ordinarily uſe.</p>
               <p>According to their demand, the 20 <hi>Barres</hi> were payed him, that is to ſay, in Iron 12 <hi>Barres</hi> a little Barrel of Strong-waters at 4 <hi>Barrs,</hi> a Kettle at 2 <hi>Barres,</hi> a Hat at 2 <hi>Barres,</hi> and ſo on: He was himſelf upon his own ſcore preſented with 2 Bottles of Brandy, and his Reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue with Knives: at the cloſe of the evening he returned, well ſtuft and well ſatisfied, as the greateſt part of his Attendants were alſo; at his departure he had ſeveral Guns given him, and was diſmiſt with all poſſible civility. He is in great reſpect among the people, his Trumpet and Drum are always carryed along with him, even when
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:53662:23"/> he goes about his moſt natural af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs. During theſe three days, we had ſeveral <hi>Portugals</hi> came aboard us with their Commodities, of whom I endeavoured what I could to inform my ſelf of the manners of that Country.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>The Deſcription of Sierra-Leone, or the Mountain of the Lyons.</head>
               <p>THe Countrey of <hi>Sierra-Leone,</hi> is called <hi>Boulombel</hi> by the <hi>Mores,</hi> which in their language is as much as the large Countrey. In reſpect of the extraordinary height of the Mountaines towards the South, which are much higher then either the <hi>Pyrenaean</hi> or <hi>Alps,</hi> and the multitude of Lyons which are conſtantly to be ſeen there, it was called <hi>Sierra Leone</hi> by the <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugals,</hi> which in our Language amounts to no more then the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:53662:24"/> 
                  <hi>Mountain of Lyons:</hi> Their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey begins a great way up in the land Eaſtward, and ends North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſt with the <hi>Cap-Ledo,</hi> which throws it ſelf into the Sea: from the point of that <hi>Cape,</hi> as on paſſes up the River, there are ſeveral Bayes, the fourth of which is the <hi>Bay de France,</hi> either becauſe the <hi>French</hi> were formerly poſſeſſed of this Coaſt, or that they burn'd a Town there heretofore, and this is the only Bay in that River where they can take in freſh water.</p>
               <p>I had one day the curioſity to trace one of the three Fountaines which are there, and having fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed it a league to the foot of the Mountaines, obſerving the tracks and Print of the wild beaſts, which are very ſtrange, and dreadful, I returned as I went, and have been ſince informed by one of the <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugals,</hi> that it riſes in the midſt of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:53662:24"/> the woods, which are above 15 leagues over, and that if I had purſued my deſign, and traced it to its ſpring, I muſt never have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected to come back, as well for the vaſt number of Lyons, as for the Tygars, Elephants, and Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>codiles which are there, and would probably have devoured me.</p>
               <p>Thoſe Mountains are covered with Trees very full of Gumme, always green, and for the moſt part not unlike our Laurel.</p>
               <p>The Northen parts of this <hi>Sierra-Leone</hi> lye very low; and are in the poſſeſſion of the King of <hi>Boulom,</hi> as the Southern parts are of the King of <hi>Boure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Kingdom of <hi>Boulom</hi> is not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verwell known, either to the <hi>French</hi> or <hi>Hollander,</hi> their affections being principally inclin'd to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Portugals,</hi> of which laſt, there are ſeveral that inhabit there.</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:53662:25"/>
               <p>The River which bears the name of <hi>Sierra-Leone</hi> likewiſe, runs a great way Eaſtward up into the Countrey, is about 3 leagues over at the mouth; and one about 14 or 15 leagues higher. The Harbour is not above two fathoms deep, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that in entring into it, we were fain to come as neer the Mountains as we could, where we found 10, 12, and 16 fathoms wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. It has ſeveral little Iſlands in its channel, the moſt of them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habited, and covered with green Trees, eſpecially Palm trees, of which they make great quantities of Wine; It is very full of Fiſh, and breeds Crocodiles near the head of its Fountain.</p>
               <p>The borders of theſe Iſlands are ſet with certain Trees whoſe bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches do never extend themſelves further out one then another, but the ſhutes or ſiences growing
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:53662:25"/> downwards, as ſoon as they touch the water or the earth, they take new root, and by that means make a Hedge ſometimes of 10 or 12 yards broad.</p>
               <p>The Inhabitants of this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey are very well made, I obſerv'd very few of them Camous'd, the men much more civil than at <hi>Cap-Verd,</hi> they are always clothed, and for the moſt part more modeſt.</p>
               <p>In the Town of <hi>Boure</hi> there can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be above 300 houſes, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the eſtimation of ſome of our men who were there, and told me among other things, that the Pallace of their King is built like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in the middle of the Town, and would not make a good reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence for a Juſtice of Peace.</p>
               <p>Their Women are generally common, every man has as many of them as he pleaſeth, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutes them to Strangers, as he
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:53662:26"/> thinks good, except only the firſt, which are kept with great jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy, and circumſpection all along theſe Coaſts, ſo as properly the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are nothing but Concubines.</p>
               <p>According to the computation of every body I ſpake with, there may be in <hi>Boure</hi> about 4 or 500 men, beſides women and children: Their King is a Roman Catholick his name <hi>Philippes,</hi> and has a <hi>Capu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin</hi> and a <hi>Jeſuit</hi> in his Court.</p>
               <p>In an Iſland called <hi>Saint Andrew,</hi> I entred into one of their houſes, and found it built of ſticks and dirt, on one ſide a little window cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with leaves, a hole for the dore, and a ſmall fire in the middle; they lye upon matts, made of great ruſhes, which they place in a corner, and have their Arms by their ſides, which for the moſt part are ſwords, daggers, darts, bows and arrows, the head of which
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:53662:26"/> they impoiſon with fruit of a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain tree, whoſe poiſon is ſo incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveably ſubtil and quick, it runs immediatly into the blood, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects it ſo ſuddenly, it is no eaſy matter either to prevent or cure it: Which fruit is long like a rad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh, and green. Some of them have their Guns, which they all of them are fond of, and do uſe with great dexterity.</p>
               <p>Their Religion alſo is various, the great Commerce the <hi>Portugals</hi> have in this place, and the great numbers that inhabit there already have converted many of them, the reſt being <hi>Mahumetans,</hi> and <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lators.</hi> They pay a reverence ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary to certain extravigant figures, which they call <hi>Fetiches,</hi> worſhip them as Gods, pray to them punctually Morning and Night, and when at any time they have any thing better then ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:53662:27"/> either Meat, or fiſh, or their Palm-Wine, they throw it all down upon the ground in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to their Gods.</p>
               <p>As I went a ſhore one day in the <hi>Canoe</hi> of a certain <hi>More,</hi> I heard him muttering to himſelf, and having diſtinguiſh'd theſe words <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> I asked him what he was doing, he told me he was giving thanks to his <hi>Fetiche,</hi> for having preſerved him at Sea, and that the reſt of the <hi>Mores,</hi> as they had occaſion, did always the ſame: They all of them carry their <hi>Fetiches</hi> in little baggs, either upon their hearts, or their ſhoulders, tendring them meat Night and Morning conſtantly, they trim them up with <hi>Raſade;</hi> or little grains of glaſs of all colours, which they take to be the greateſt Ornament in the world.</p>
               <p>This Country produces great
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:53662:27"/> quantity of <hi>Rice,</hi> of <hi>Millet,</hi> and <hi>Mays,</hi> which is a kind of <hi>Turkiſh Corne,</hi> they make their bread off, and is not very ill: Some of them having waſh'd their Rice in Sea water, will eat it raw, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ill effect.</p>
               <p>Their common diet is fiſh, and great ſtore of fruits, as Berrys, Figgs, Pears, Prunes, Oranges, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons, and a kind of Cheſtnut, not altogether ſo good as in <hi>Europe,</hi> but it has the virtue to quench the thirſt though one be never ſo dry.</p>
               <p>Theſe Mountains produce great quantities of Goats, Hoggs, Lyons, Tygres, Elephants, wild Bores, Harts, and Roebucks, which laſt are ſo numerous, they bring them on Ship board, and truck them for little or nothing: But the Serpents (if we may believe either the <hi>Mores</hi> or the <hi>Portugals</hi>) doe increaſe ſo unmeaſurably, that
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:53662:28"/> ſome of them will ſwallow a Man at a gulpe. The <hi>Mores</hi> are perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually at wars with them, and doe uſe a certain herbe (which is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirably good againſt poiſon) againſt the bites of all the Beaſts they encounter.</p>
               <p>The Apes run up and down every where in great Troops, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying their plants where ever they come, upon which ſcore the <hi>Mores</hi> are their implacable ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies (as well as the Elephants) hunting and perſuing them per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually, and ſometimes eating them when they have done. I have taſted of their fleſh, which is not bad, and in my judgement comes very near our Beef.</p>
               <p>All of them ſpeak <hi>Portugais,</hi> and are very apprehenſive of being drunk, for which reaſon (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially amonſt us) they drank but little ſtrong water.</p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:53662:28"/>
               <p>The Merchandiſe this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey affords is Rice, excellent Ivory, Civet, and ſome Amber Greece. Of all the Coaſts, this is one of the beſt for matter of trade, ſeldome yeilding leſs profit then <hi>Cent pour Cent:</hi> But the <hi>Portugals</hi> gain is much greater, they buying their I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vory up higher in the Countrey, and afterwards ſelling it again at the Sea ſide to other Merchants; Four or five men might live in one of the little Iſles in this River, and be very well ſuſteined by the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of two or three Slaves.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Engliſh</hi> have a Ware-houſe in one of thoſe Iſlands, and the Factor thereof writ to us ſeveral times to deſire he might come to us and trade, we told him he might doe it with ſafety, and on the laſt of <hi>December,</hi> upon our parole, when we had finiſh'd our bargains for Ivory with the <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugals,</hi>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:53662:29"/> and Natives, the ſaid <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhman</hi> called <hi>Abraham,</hi> came aboard us in his ſhallop (rowed by three Slaves) accompany'd by a certain <hi>Hollander,</hi> and two others which belonged to him; he was well received, but after Supper, contrary to the advice of all the reſt, the Captain made him a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner, and the three <hi>Mores</hi> which were with him, to their no ſmall aſtoniſhment, and on the firſt of <hi>January</hi> 1667. the great ſhallop was mann'd out with 30. men, the Captain, the Chyrurgion, and my ſelf, with one piece of ordnance, to beſiege and plunder his houſe.</p>
               <p>It is built of Brick, and free ſtone, defended with four pieces of Canon, carrying a four pound bullet, and incompaſs'd with a fair wood of Palm-trees, which ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed him with Wine. On one ſide there are fifteen or twenty
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:53662:29"/> Cabines for the Natives, and on the other, a ſpring of very good wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. This Iſland is the beſt and moſt beautiful upon the River: As we were about to land, we diſcovered ſome 200 <hi>Mores,</hi> got together a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the houſe, with their firelocks, and a greater number up the woods at farther diſtance: which obliged us to make a ſhow of paſſing on higher, as being the weaker, and by conſequence in more need of the advantage of the wind. They ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined we had been going to <hi>Boure,</hi> and immediately diſpatch'd a <hi>Canoe</hi> to give <hi>Boulom</hi> the alarm, and to adviſe him to come to them; we perſued this <hi>Canoe</hi> with all poſſible diligence, but could not perſwade them to come in till we fired 3 or 4 times into their boat; They were two young Slaves, belonging to a <hi>Portugal,</hi> that was with the <hi>Engliſh Man,</hi> but we could not make them
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:53662:30"/> confeſs any thing, by all the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogations we could uſe: Thoſe of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> party obſerving what was paſt, fired at us with their Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, and 3 of their bullets fell with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ten paces of our boat. We put our ſelves out of the reach of their Guns for the preſent, and came to an anchor, attending the comming in of the tide to accommodate our return: The weather being calme, about half an hour after, there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd two <hi>Mores</hi> belonging to one of the neighbouring Iſlands, in a <hi>Canoe,</hi> which made directly up to us, and came within piſtol ſhot, but would by no means be perſwaded on board; whereupon we ſhot off 2 or 3 Guns (not with intention of doing them harm) but to inſtruct them of the truth: They no ſooner heard the noiſe of our Guns, but they run away immediately, plying their cars as faſt as they could, and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:53662:30"/> ſtooping (upon ſight of our fire) ſo low, they ſeem'd to us no higher then Cats: In the mean time the Canon of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> were not idle, playing ſtill upon us, though they ſaw we were out of their reach, which they did not ſo much to do any execution, as to let the Natives ſee they had undertaken their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and deſired their friendſhip: However the tide comming in, we paſs'd by ſeveral little Iſlands, and made our retreat.</p>
               <p>We found ſeveral <hi>Mores,</hi> and <hi>Portugals</hi> aboard our Veſſel, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the reſt, the King of <hi>Bou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loms</hi> Son called <hi>Bombo,</hi> who was a perſon of about 30 or 40 years old, well proportioned, and (bating his complexion) a very handſom man, his aire was courteous, and maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick, he was an intimate friend of <hi>Abrahams,</hi> but knew nothing till ſupper, of his impriſonment: He
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:53662:31"/> no ſooner underſtood it, but he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceded for his ranſome, and went immediately with the <hi>Portugal</hi> (that manages the affairs of the King of <hi>Boure</hi>) to procure it: On <hi>Munday</hi> at noon they came aboard again with a 100 Elephants teeth, weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing 900 pound weight, and two live Civet Cats, upon the delivery of which he was diſmiſt, and went home after dinner, we giving him a little barrel of Strong-waters, a rowl of Tobacco, a Cheeſe, and a <hi>Salvo</hi> of 3 Guns, when he went off.</p>
               <p>Some ſew <hi>Portugals</hi> ſtay'd behind till they made up their Markets, and having diſpatch'd them the fiſth, they returned out of hand.</p>
               <p>That day we intended to have been gone, but happening upon a calm, and to have a tide againſt us too, we were forc'd to attend a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle longer then we deſigned. About noon there came a <hi>Canoe</hi> aboard us,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:53662:31"/> with two <hi>Mores,</hi> which pretended to belong to <hi>Boulom,</hi> who brought us fruit, but having no Ivory, we lookt upon them but as ſpies, and ſent them back again about five.</p>
               <p>That night we ſet ſail, and having paſt <hi>Cap-Ledo,</hi> we ſteer'd a South South-Eaſt courſe, to avoid the the Banks of <hi>Saint Anne,</hi> and the next morning diſcry'd a little Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of <hi>Holland,</hi> coaſting upon the ſhore as we did to make the <hi>Cap de Monte,</hi> which is about 60 leagues diſtant from the <hi>Sierra-Leone.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On Friday the 7th of <hi>January,</hi> we paſt by the mouth of the River of <hi>Madre-Bomba,</hi> where the <hi>Engliſh</hi> have a houſe alſo, and not inferior to that at <hi>Sierra-Leone.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the afternoon we came with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſight of the <hi>Rio de Gallines,</hi> ſo called by the <hi>Portugals,</hi> from the multitude of Hens there, and the cheapneſs of them, the people gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:53662:32"/> one, two, and ſomtimes three for a knife of a penny. The <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers</hi> had a houſe there former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: The Natives gave us a ſign to approach and put in, but the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> would not ſuffer us to hear on that ear, but we continued our coaſt to the Eaſt till <hi>Saturday</hi> morning, at which time by the aſſiſtance of a clear day, we diſcover'd the <hi>Cap de Monte,</hi> at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ten leagues diſtance.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CAP DE MONTE, and its Deſcription.</head>
               <p>THe wind being but little, we came not to an anchor till night, and then about half a league from the ſhore, at twelve fathom low water, and upon a ſand.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Cap de Monte</hi> is ſo called from a point of ground which gives it that figure, and riſing juſt
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:53662:32"/> by the Sea, formes its ſelf into a round Mountain, all the reſt of that coaſt lying very low.</p>
               <p>We could not deſcry either houſe or cabane all along, yet on the 19th we went on ſhore, and found 4 or 5 houſes at ſome diſtance, where the Blacks made their Salt.</p>
               <p>They appeared very joyful at our arrival; they told us their King lived three days journey up into the Countrey, that they would give notice to their neighbours of our coming that night, and that if we thought good to return the next morning, we might find ſuch ſtore of Ivory as could be ſuddenly got. That if we intended to keep our promiſe when we came on board, we ſhould give them two great Guns as a ſignal, and they would make fires to confirm us on their ſide, which was agreed and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed accordingly.</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:53662:33"/>
               <p>The tenth, and the eleventh days, were ſpent entirely in bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring, I being on board the 12th, I went on ſhore, though with ſome difficulty, the Sea breaking off. ſo abruptly, our ſhallop was left ſome 20 paces upon ground, and the Seamen forc'd to go out of the boat, and land the Officers upon their backs; where we found the <hi>Mores</hi> had made a large Arbor, covered over with leaves, and branches of trees, to keep our commodities dry, and ſhelter us from the violence of the Sun.</p>
               <p>Whilſt we were Negotiating our affairs, we heard a great noiſe on a ſudden, and ſaw the <hi>Mores</hi> in a great hurry, running Pell-mell from their houſes, and merchandiſe both: we apprehended we might be ſurprized, and took up our arms immediately, but being got out in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the air, we underſtood it was
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:53662:33"/> only their King was coming to us; whereupon ſome of our men went to meet him, and ſaluted him with a volley of five or ſix of our fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locks.</p>
               <p>Before him marched his Drum, and his Trumpet, 8 or 10 of his kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and friends, and the reſt were his Officers: his Wives, and his Daughters, marched on his ſide, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind him his Slaves followed, and a certain number of women carrying his dinner in bowls of Wood, and of Tyn, which they held up as high as they could poſſibly: By him he had four Slaves marching, two of them covering him with two large Bucklers, and the other carrying his bow and arrows, and javelin: As he approached, the <hi>Mores</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided themſelves, the Men on one ſide, the Women on the other, ſinging, and dancing, and leap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up and down, and teſtifying
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:53662:34"/> their joy in a thouſand different poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. The King took a dart, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to throw it at them, upon which they threw themſelves im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately upon the ground, and at the ſame time they which came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with his Majeſty took their turn, both to dance and to ſing. Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently the King took an arrow, which he ſhot up into the aire, and preſently all run to the place where it fell, and happy was he that could take it up firſt, and bring it to him; after this he made a ſhow of ſhooting directly amongſt them, &amp; they throwing themſelves down again, with great acclamation, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued this paſtime for a quarter of an hour: In this triumpth and gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour, he was conducted to us; we received him as honorably as we could, ſaluting him with volleys of ſmall ſhot.</p>
               <p>He was a grave and venerable
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:53662:34"/> old man of about threeſcore years of age, or upwards, they called him <hi>Falam Boure,</hi> he was very ſenſible and majeſtick: his habit was the ſame with the reſt of the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, ſaving that his was quite blew, and the Robes of the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Officers, and Nobility of that Countrey, are always ſtrip'd (like the Captains of <hi>Rio-Freſca</hi>) with white and blew: We payed him what reſpect vve could, and after vve had made him ſuch preſents as vvere uſual, he retired into another Arbor the <hi>Mores</hi> had made for him, and left us very graciouſly to our Negotiations.</p>
               <p>I vvaited upon him to his Arbor, vvhere he entertained me in <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gais,</hi> and told me, that it vvas four years ſince he had ſeen any Whites, and vvith teares (as it were) of joy aſſured me, that the <hi>French</hi> ſhould be alvvays vvelcome to him; that
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:53662:35"/> indeed they were a little quick and capricious, but otherwiſe honeſt men: that he and his Country (which he thought was not contemptible) I would be eternally at their ſervice.</p>
               <p>And in truth were all the reſt of <hi>Africk</hi> like this part of it, it was indubitably to be preferred to any part of <hi>Europe.</hi> No ſooner is your foot upon the ground, but you are preſented with a faire plaine, planted on this ſide and that, with curious groves per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually green, and in their leaves not unlike to our Laurel. The proſpect is bounded to the South with the Mountain of the <hi>Cape;</hi> and on the North by a large grove, which gives a ſhade to a little Iſland in a little River, which caſts it ſelf hard by into the Sea, though it be navigable for a <hi>Canoe</hi> only, or perhaps with ſome diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty for a ſhallop: Eaſtward
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:53662:35"/> there is no ſtop nor termination of the eye, it may delight and loſe it ſelf, in vaſt meadows and playnes, beautifi'd and perfum'd with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent verdures, and water'd with ſeveral pritty Rivers, which open and expan'd themſelves to the <hi>Mores,</hi> and ſeem to invite them to a communication with thoſe that live higher up in the Countrey.</p>
               <p>In this place their <hi>Rice,</hi> their <hi>Millet,</hi> and their <hi>Mais</hi> (of which their bread is made) is more plentifull, and grows in greater quantity, than in any other part of <hi>Guinee</hi> whatſoever.</p>
               <p>They have Citrons, Oranges, Amants, Berrys, Melons, Gourds, and a ſort of plums not much unlike our <hi>Brugnons,</hi> but not ſo well taſted.</p>
               <p>They have great variety of fowl, as Hens, and Pidgeons, and Ducks, and Mallard, and Teal, which
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:53662:36"/> muſt be very plentiful, by the price they are ſold for.</p>
               <p>Goats and Hoggs are very com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and Apes too, but ugly ones. They have great ſtore of Fiſh, both Sea-fiſh and in their Rivers, which I have ſaid they value much above fleſh, they have Tortoiſes likewiſe are excellent meat, but their ſhels not worth a farthing.</p>
               <p>They are very neat in their fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, they roaſt their meat upon wooden ſpits, turning them with great care, and obſerving very cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly leaſt one ſide be more roaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed then the other.</p>
               <p>Whilſt he was at dinner in his own appartment, I took the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to begin a health to on of his Sons Wifes, in their Palme-Wine, and ſhe anſwered me in French, <hi>Monſierje vous remercie,</hi> and told me afterwards in <hi>Portugais,</hi> that her Husbands Father had lived al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:53662:36"/> amongſt the <hi>French,</hi> when they were in thoſe parts, and that ſhe could diſtinguiſh eaſily by our aire, that my ſelf and Lacquey were the only <hi>Frenchmen</hi> in our whole company.</p>
               <p>The inhabitants are generally handſome, good natured, tractible, and ſpeak a kind of corrupt <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gais.</hi> They go all naked both wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and men, only a little cloth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, but the women wear theirs from their ſtomack, to their mid-legg: they are more chaſt then the reſt, and their Husbands com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly more jealous.</p>
               <p>For their Religion, do what I could, I could not inform my ſelf, only one of them told me the Whites pray'd to God, and the Blacks to the Devil: Yet I could perceive many of them were Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed, and all of them had their <hi>Fetiches.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:53662:37"/>
               <p>At our landing, there was not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove five or ſix houſes to be ſeen, and thoſe belonging to ſuch as made Salt there, and carryed it af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards into the Country: But within two dayes time, the plaine (which was about a league in cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference) was cover'd over with houſes, which the <hi>Mores</hi> from all parts had built, in order to their traffick with us.</p>
               <p>In the Kings houſes, or the hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of their Nobility, they have a diſtinct appartment where their beds are made, either upon plancks, or mat; about a yeard from the ground, about which they hang a cloth (in ſtead of curtains and val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence) and ſo ſleep all night upon them. For their repoſe in the day time, they have a ſort of delicate neat mats, exquiſitely made (of which the <hi>Hollander</hi> buys great ſtore for their Chambers) where laying
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:53662:37"/> themſelves down with their heads in their Wives lapps, they ſpend much of their time in combing and ordring their Husbands hair.</p>
               <p>For four days together we had a very good Trade. The commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties we bought were Mats, Rice, and Ivory, which in thoſe parts is plentiful and excellently good.</p>
               <p>And in this place certainly (if any where) a man may live hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily, all things contributing to make his life pleaſant; the beauty and bounty of the Countrey, the humour and diſpoſition of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the aboundance of all neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, the conſiderableneſs of the gain, and the aptneſs and conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience for building in all places wherever you come.</p>
               <p>On the thirteenth we went a ſhore again, but ſeeing they had no Ivory left, (though the King promis'd in three dayes time we
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:53662:38"/> ſhould have ten times as much as we had bought aleady,) we ſet ſayle that night for <hi>Cap-Miſerado.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CAP-MISERADO.</head>
               <p>THe next day being the 14th of <hi>January,</hi> ſteering or courſe Eaſt-South-Eaſt and by South, we diſcovered the <hi>Cap-Miſerado,</hi> but the weather being duskiſh, and a thick fog interrupting our proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, we were glad to caſt anchor at three leagues diſtance from the ſhore (imagining notwithſtanding we had been nearer then we were) and afterward we ſhot off 2 Guns to give the <hi>Mores</hi> notice of our arrival.</p>
               <p>The fifteenth we diſcovered our miſtake, yet by reaſon of calme, we were forc'd to continue at anchor till noon, at which time we percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a <hi>Canoe</hi> making towards us with 2 <hi>Mores</hi> in it, which coming up, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:53662:38"/> who we were, and of what Countrey, we told them of <hi>Holland;</hi> and they deſired us to come nearer land, but would by no means be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded on board us, till they ſaw us take the advantage of the wind, weigh anchor, and ſayle towards the ſhore.</p>
               <p>They entered then, and told us it was a full year ſince they had ſeen any Whites: that the next day they would bring good ſtore of Ivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Sea ſide for us, and that they might perform what they had promiſed, after we had made them ſome ſmall preſents, they took their leaves. We came up within half a league of the land, to the mouth of a little river they call <hi>Duro,</hi> at the foot of the <hi>Cape,</hi> where we found ſix fathom deep at low water.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Cape</hi> is called <hi>Miſerado</hi> by the <hi>Portugais,</hi> either becauſe it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compaſs'd by rocks that lye under
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:53662:39"/> water, and would inevitably deſtroy any Veſſel, which ſhould come nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer then half a league, or becauſe the <hi>French</hi> which were formerly maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacred there, cryed out <hi>Miſericorde, Miſericorde:</hi> Beſides the Natives of this place being very cruel, they have denominated the river, and called it <hi>Duro,</hi> as being hard and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal to the Whites. Upon which ſcore we fortifyed our ſhollop with a great Gun, to fright them and keep them in order.</p>
               <p>They ſet up a little houſe againſt we came in order to our negotiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but not another to be ſeen within leſs then half a league, and thoſe too in the woods.</p>
               <p>The River <hi>Duro</hi> caſts it ſelf into the Sea on that ſide towards the <hi>Cape,</hi> but is ſo ſmall and inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, it carrys nothing but <hi>Canoes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At our coming on ſhore, we found the Captain (who governs thoſe
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:53662:39"/> parts) with ſeveral of his Officers ſitting under a tree, we preſented them with two Bottles of Brandy, which they drank freely, and then conducted us to the houſe they had prepared, and ſtay'd with us till night came on, and we returned to our Ship.</p>
               <p>The Captain was a very luſty man of a ſevere aſpect, in a Robe like that of the <hi>Alcair de Rio-Freſca,</hi> ſaving that his was red, with a bonnet of the ſame colour, he was attended by 50 or 60 <hi>Negroes,</hi> with great darts, bows, arrows, and ſwords, and with ſome few women, which they ſent back again to the Woods, not above fifty paces from our lodge, from whence we never durſt truſt our ſelves above ten.</p>
               <p>They ask'd us whether we came as enemies or friends, obſerving it ſeems the Canon in our ſhallop; We told them that we could not
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:53662:40"/> but take notice, that they came with their armes, contrary to the cuſtom of all other places we had traded in, and that we did, was but to ſecure our ſelves, and our Merchandiſes, which we ſhould bring on ſhore by degrees, and according as we ſold what we had brought.</p>
               <p>Some of the Captains Women, lugging their children along with them, came to ſee us at our lodge, and we were forc'd to preſent them, though the Captain was ſo refracto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, what Ivory ſoever he expos'd to truck, or to ſale, he ask'd with that unreaſonable confidence, there was no reaſon to give it: They all of them ſpake <hi>Portugais,</hi> and were all of them clothed.</p>
               <p>Whilſt we were at dinner, the Captain demanded ſome one of us to ſtay with him, and I (very coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly) proffered to be the man, which he took ſo kindly, he took
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:53662:40"/> me by the hand, and put it into the hand of one of his daughters, with this complement, that he gave her me for my Wife, after which we grew very intimate and great; He took me and ſhew'd me to the reſt of the <hi>Mores,</hi> who called me their kinſman and friend, promiſed me S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aves, carryed me along with them, and ſetting me in the midſt of them, they made me drink of their <hi>Palm-wine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>One of the Officers that din'd with us, I obſerv'd to throw Wine up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ground, before he drank; I ask'd him the reaſon, and he told me, that if his dead Father ſhould be dry, he would come thither to drink.</p>
               <p>We had a ſight too of ſome of their Prieſts, but their habits being the ſame, with what we ſaw after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards upon the <hi>Golden Coaſt,</hi> I ſhall paſs them by in this place, with this animadverſion only, that they
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:53662:41"/> carry themſelves towards them with great deference and reſpect, believing every word they ſpake an Oracle. The Captain ſhew'd me one of them, and told me, if I had loſt any thing, he could tell me where it was, and cry'd him up as he had been a Prophet: But above all things, their greateſt ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is of their <hi>Fetiches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Their Traffick is principally I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vory, (which indeed is excellent) and Rice in great abundance.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Engliſh</hi> have a ware houſe beyond the <hi>Cape,</hi> and are in great favour with the <hi>Mores,</hi> who uſed us ill in no reſpect, but as they thought us enemies to them.</p>
               <p>When we returned to our Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, we promiſed to be with them again the next morning, but obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving they had brought us good quantity of Ivory at firſt, which was not afterwards to be ſeen, we had a
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:53662:41"/> ſuſpicion might be a deſign of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> to amuſe us with their Trade, whilſt they could get more men together out of the Countrey; Upon which grounds, that very night (though one of our Officers left a golden ring with the Captain, as a gage for his word) we weigh'd anchor and away for <hi>Rio-Sextos.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Being on the other ſide of <hi>Cap-Miſerado,</hi> we diſcovered fires, which the <hi>Mores</hi> had made along the ſhores, which is the ordinary ſigne they uſe, to ſignifie to ſuch Ships as paſs by, that they have Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe for them, upon which accompt we reſolved to caſt anchor.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>RIO DE J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NCO.</head>
               <p>ABout 9 or 10 a clock we came to an anchor, directly over againſt the fires upon the ſhore, we ſhot of 2 great Guns, to invite them
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:53662:42"/> aboard, but ſeeing none of them come, we mann'd out our ſhallop after dinner, and ſayl'd towards them with ſome few Merchandiſes, but we could not reach the ſhore, within fifty paces, without inevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table danger of bulging.</p>
               <p>Seeing ſome <hi>Mores</hi> upon the banks, we made ſignes to them to come to us, and they came ſwim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming half way, and went back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, nor could all our alurements win them aboard, till at laſt two of them ventured in a <hi>Canoe,</hi> and were kindly received, which they on the ſhore obſerving, three of them threw themſelves immediately into the Sea ond ſwam to us; we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented them with a bottle of Srong-waters, which they carryed on ſhore to their infinite ſatisfaction: we ſhew'd them our Kettles, and what other Commodities we had, at the ſight of which, they made a
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:53662:42"/> thouſand expreſſions of joy, and could have done no more, if Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe it ſelf had been ſhown them: they ask'd us if we had any large white <hi>Raſade.</hi> Thoſe which were upon land, held up great, and great quantity of Elephants teeth, to haſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en us them, but having uſed our ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt endeavour to no purpoſe, and finding it impoſſible to come at them, without manifeſt danger, we ſent back the 2 <hi>Mores</hi> (which came to us) to them: Who by their aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect and <hi>Mine,</hi> ſeem'd to be perſons of more then ordinary quality.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rio de Junco</hi> is a River which lyes five degrees and fifty minutes of Northern latitude, and of Eaſtern longitude, 9 degrees, 10 minutes. The mouth of it is known by three great trees which ſtand very high, and three great Mountains over a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, but at ſome diſtance into the land; the mouth of it is
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:53662:43"/> near five hundred paces over, but ſhallow, the banks ſo well decora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with trees, and flowers, that conſidered with the ſmoothneſs and ſerenity of the ſtream, they make a moſt admirable landſhip.</p>
               <p>Orange-trees, Citrons, and Palme-trees, are planted all along, and in exquiſite order, and (as the <hi>Mores</hi> which came aboard intimated to us) they have abundance of all things, eſpecially Poultry and Palme-Wine. We went aboard, and perceiving no body came at us, we ſet ſayle that night, and came the next moring before <hi>Petit Dieppe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>PETIT DIEPPE.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PEtit Dieppe</hi> is a Town not far from a River, which caſts it ſelf into the Sea, and in its paſſage, twiſting about a ſpot of ground, forms it ſelf into no contemptible
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:53662:43"/> Iſland: it was formerly in the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the <hi>French,</hi> but deſerted long ſince; at the diſemboguement of this River, there are many Rocks, which make the entrance more then ordinary difficult: We diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered a little Veſſel upon this Coaſt, and gave chaſe to it, but without any ſucceſs.</p>
               <p>The 22d we came to <hi>Rio-Sextos,</hi> whoſe deſcription follows,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>RIO-SEXTOS.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>RIo-Sextos</hi> is a River, which comes a great way down the land, North and North-Weſt, and is about half a league over at the mouth of it. On both ſides it is ſet very pleaſantly with Trees, very large, and very tall; about three leagues up the River, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> had formerly a houſe, but there is nothing of it left but the Walls.
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:53662:44"/> This River will carry a Yacht or a large Barke a douzaine leagues and more up in the Countrey.</p>
               <p>It was called <hi>Rio-Sextos</hi> by the <hi>Portugais,</hi> from a certain kind of Pepper which grows by it, and is called <hi>Sextos</hi> by them, the ſame I ſuppoſe with what we call <hi>Mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guette</hi> which I ſhall ſpeake of more particularly in the next Chapter: We were told by their fiſherboats, that about a fortnight before there paſs'd two <hi>Flemiſh</hi> Veſſels that way to the <hi>Mine,</hi> that we might finde good quantities of Ivory, but that their <hi>Canoes</hi> being ſo ſmall, it would be neceſſary for us to carry our Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanhiſe on ſhore: whereupon we anchor'd about half a league from land, in about 16 fathom water.</p>
               <p>Some of our Officers went a ſhore in our ſhallop, and carryed ſome Commodities along with them, to begin the Commerce; they carryed
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:53662:44"/> them three leagues up the River, and their King (who lived yet high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er into the Countrey) came down to ſee them, and according to Cuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome had his uſual preſents.</p>
               <p>They came back very late, and the Notary at his return gave me this accompt of him, that he was a very luſty man, with a ſtern and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>percilious aſpect; that he profeſs'd great frienſhip for the <hi>Engliſh:</hi> That he brought down great ſtore of Ivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with him, but having furniſhed the two <hi>Flemiſh</hi> Veſſels ſo lately, he held it ſo dear, there was no dealing with him for it. That they ſeem'd worſe natured then the <hi>Mores</hi> at <hi>Miſerado;</hi> But that the River was very fine, and is full of little ſtones upon the ſhore like our Flints, only theſe are harder, and give more fire upon any colliſion.</p>
               <p>Whileſt they were amongſt them, there came about 10 or 12 of their
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:53662:45"/> 
                  <hi>Canoes</hi> aboard us with a kind of Sea-Pike (an excellent good fiſh) and ſeveral other ſorts, of which we bought ſome.</p>
               <p>The people are generally well proportioned, and bearing eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of them the name of ſome Saint or other, I had a great curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity to know how that cuſtom came upon them. I took one of them aſide, and having cajoled him with a glaſs of Wine, and ſtrong-water (which they love better then their Wives) I asked him the reaſon, and he told me, that when any Veſſels paſſed that way, and did the Natives any kindneſs, it was uſual to begg their Names at their departure, which they gave afterwards to their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, in memory of the courteſie they had received from them: Which convinced me, being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belliſhed with ſo noble a virtue as gratitude, they could not be ſo bad
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:53662:45"/> as they had been repreſented to me, and the rather, becauſe the King of them having upon the death of an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchant ſeized upon all his Ivory and goods, did upon the arrival of the firſt <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ship, vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily, and without any ſolicita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, deliver all to the Captain: An invincible argument of their piety and ſaith. I gave him that gave me this accompt, two little knives for his pains, and he was ſo ſurpris'd at the preſent, he deſired my name, and I having told him, he oblig'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, if his Wife (which was big at that time) was brought to bed of a boy, he ſhould carry my name, and if ever I return'd that way, he would bring him to ſee me.</p>
               <p>All along this Coaſt, their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ſalutation is the ſame, they take our ſore finger and thumb, into their hands, and putting them into a certain poſture, they pull them
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:53662:46"/> hard, and make them ſnap, crying out <hi>Aquio</hi> when they have done, which is as much as <hi>your Servant</hi> with us.</p>
               <p>This Countrey is very fertil, well furniſh'd with Fowl, and Rice, and Millet, of which they make all the bread, which they carry with them in their <hi>Canoes</hi> when they go out a fiſhing, which (as I obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved) they are very neat and axact in keeping clean.</p>
               <p>He that would ſtay upon the place, might make very good advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage either by Rice, or Pepper, or Ivory, which is excellently good; their kindneſs has been always more conſpicious to the <hi>French,</hi> then either to the <hi>Hollander</hi> or <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugal,</hi> neither of which they would ever ſuffer to cohabit with them.</p>
               <p>On the 32th. by break of day, we diſcovered a little Fleet of <hi>Canoes</hi> of about 40, which were go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:53662:46"/> a fiſhing, and within a quarter of an hour they diſperſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves every way: Of the whole <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mada,</hi> there was but one came to us, with ſome few Elephants teeth, which he held ſo dear he had his labour for his paines, and carryed them off as he brought them; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon we alſo weighed anchor for <hi>Rio-Sanguin,</hi> which is the firſt place upon the Coaſt of <hi>Malaguette,</hi> and about twelve leagues from <hi>Rio-Sextos;</hi> for four hours together we ſteer'd Southward to avoid the Rocks which ly in great numbers betwixt <hi>Rio-Sanguin,</hi> and <hi>Rio-Sextos,</hi> after which we ſteer'd Eaſt and by North, and came ſafe to <hi>Rio-Sanguin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the <hi>French</hi> had the preoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupancy of theſe Coaſts, in reſpect of all other Nations of <hi>Europe,</hi> I think is clear from the Names of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Bayes, and a hundred other monuments of their glory: But at
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:53662:47"/> preſent we have nothing left there, nor indeed any body, but the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh,</hi> who by means of ſeven or eight houſes, doe carry away as it were the whole pofits of the place.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Portugais</hi> ſucceeded the <hi>French,</hi> but being over-power'd by the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and the <hi>Dutch,</hi> and beaten off from the Coaſts, in the year 1604. they retreated farther into the Countrey, and marrying with the Natives, have begot that generation of people, they call <hi>Muletto's,</hi> or Olive-couler'd, and have by that means acquired ſuch an intereſt amongſt them, as have been the cauſe we have made no farther diſcoveries there, and that they doe to this day go away with the whole Iſland Trade; he that ſhould endeavour to ſhare with them being certain to be deſtroyed by their great influence and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority with the <hi>Nigros:</hi> So that
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:53662:47"/> they have ingroſs'd that whole commerce to them ſelves, paſſing up and down every where as they pleaſe, and running up the <hi>Niger,</hi> as far as <hi>Benin,</hi> which is more then 800 leagues.</p>
               <p>They it is that have been the loſs of <hi>Cantozi</hi> to the <hi>Danes,</hi> which is a little Iſland upon the <hi>Niger,</hi> two hvndred leagues above the mouth of the <hi>Gambie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Their authority over the <hi>Mores</hi> upon the Coaſts is ſo great, they manage them as thy think good, and we can never read that they have at any time rebelled<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> againſt them, as they have frequently done againſt the reſt of the <hi>Euro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peans;</hi> Nay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo abſolute is their Empire, they are many times ſerved at the table by the Sons of that King, which is ſo ſuperlative a command, there can be nothing beyond it; Yet if any other <hi>Euro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pean</hi>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:53662:48"/> does but quarrel or affront any of their Grandees, there is nothing but they will attempt which may contribute to their revenge. One of them who came to traffick with us at <hi>Sierra-Leone,</hi> told me, he did uſe every year to go to <hi>Senegal,</hi> which is two hundred leagues from <hi>Sierra-Leone,</hi> and that where he had not the conveniency of a river, both himſelf and his Commodities were carryed up into the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey on the backs of the <hi>Mores.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They have all of them little Chappels built near their houſes, in which they uſe all poſſible means for the converſion of thoſe people, and when they have had any ſucceſs, and made a proſilite, they hang Chappelets about his neck, and have a particular care of them ever after.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:53662:48"/>
               <head>THE COAST OF GRAIVES CALLED MALAGUETTE</head>
               <p>UPon the three and twentieth of <hi>January,</hi> the ſame day we ſet ſayle from <hi>Rio-Sextos,</hi> we came to an anchor before <hi>Rio-Sanguin,</hi> where the Coaſt of <hi>Malaguette,</hi> or <hi>Manigette</hi> begins, and extends it ſelf ſixty leagues to the <hi>Cape de Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes,</hi> about three degrees and forty minutes of Northern latitude, comprehending all theſe places, <hi>Ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>-Sanguin, Cestre-Crou, Brova, Baſſou, Zino, Crou, Crouſeſtre, Wapo, Batou, Grand-Seſter, Petit-Seſter,</hi> and <hi>Goiane,</hi> all which places we vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited in ninteen days, which we
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:53662:49"/> dedicated to our traffick in thoſe parts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rio-Sanguin</hi> runs into the Sea South South-Eaſt, and will carry a <hi>Petach</hi> about twelve leagues, and no more; upon its bank it has a Town of about a hundred houſes, and large Trees on both ſides of it, but is not five hundred paces broad at the wideſt part of it.</p>
               <p>That night there came a <hi>Canoe</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board us with three <hi>Mores,</hi> one of them was the Kings Brother, who having been three years in <hi>Holland,</hi> ſpake very good <hi>Dutch;</hi> he ſent back his Company, and his <hi>Canoe,</hi> and ſupp'd and lodged with us that night. At ſupper he told us, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove a Month before, there was a <hi>Flemiſh</hi> Ship put in at <hi>Rio-Sanguin</hi> for freſh water and wood, but that diſcovering an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Veſſel make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing towards them, he weigh'd an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> being a good
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:53662:49"/> ſayler, got off, and that the Veſſel that chaced them returned, and ſteer'd his old courſe for <hi>Rio-Sextos.</hi> He deſcribed the bulk of it ſo well, we concluded it was the Ship we had ſeeing cruſing up the Coaſt of <hi>Petit Dieppe.</hi> He told us moreover, that a while ſince the <hi>Engliſh</hi> had a houſe at <hi>Rio-Sanguin,</hi> but for four years laſt paſt, they had none; and that a little Veſſel going by lately, had ſurprized about a douzen <hi>Mores</hi> near <hi>Crouſeſter,</hi> and carryed them away.</p>
               <p>As we were hoiſting ſayle on the five and twentieth, the King of <hi>Rio-Sanguin</hi> came aboard us, attended with two other <hi>Canoes,</hi> and about ten or twelve <hi>Mores.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He was an ancient man, very grave, and venerable, his hair very white, yet his perſon large and luſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; his habit blew, like their habits at <hi>Cap de Monte.</hi> That which was
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:53662:50"/> moſt remarkable was, he drank nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Wine nor Strong-water, nor Palme-Wine, nothing but pure wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; he and his Brother both ſtayed with us till night, and having recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſome preſents they departed.</p>
               <p>We had paſſed the place above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, as far as from <hi>Rio-Sanguin</hi> to <hi>Wapo,</hi> where being at anchor, the third of <hi>February,</hi> about Sun-riſing we diſcryed a Veſſel at Sea, making towords us with all the ſayle ſhe could make: We thought at firſt it had been the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Piqueroon we had been told of, for which reaſon we ſtood all that night to our armes, but the next day the hopes we had of over-powring and take<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her, vaniſhed with the Veſſel, which we could never ſee more.</p>
               <p>Till <hi>Saturday</hi> the fifth we ſpent our time wholly in traffick, on which day having come to an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor at <hi>Batou,</hi> we diſcovered ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:53662:50"/> Veſſel coming towards us alſo with full ſayles: The number of <hi>Mores</hi> who were then aboard us, hindered us from diſcovering them perfectly, but coming nearer, we could diſcry the Veſſel to be as bigg as ours, whereupon we diſmiſt our Merchants, weigh'd anchor, and ſtood towards them directly, reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved not only to defend our ſelves, but to venture upon them. When we were come within a league of him, he hung out his <hi>Dutch</hi> colours, and clapt his <hi>Cornette</hi> upon his <hi>Sprit-ſayle,</hi> and we hung out our <hi>French.</hi> When we came nearer, we knew the Ship to be a Frigat of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> of about 400 Tunn, and 36 pieces of Ordnance, ſet out by a private perſon, and by the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and conſent of the <hi>Eaſt-Indy Company,</hi> ſent to <hi>Ardres.</hi> The Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain called <hi>Wilere,</hi> having boaſted when we were in the <hi>Texel,</hi> that if
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:53662:51"/> he found us upon theſe Coaſts, he would either ſink or take us; we took down our <hi>French</hi> colours, and put up a red flagg, endeavouring, and tacking three hours together, to get the wind of him, he had all his ſayles out, and his caps up, and yet ſayled worſe than we. About Sun-ſetting he furled his ſayles, and having loſt the wind, and we with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in 20 paces of him, he made ſignes with his hat to know if we were not the <hi>Europe:</hi> he told us his name; and calling for a glaſs of Wine, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan a good ſoup to our healths, and we did him reaſon in our turn. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which he took his leave, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued his courſe to the <hi>Mine,</hi> and we came that night to an anchor before <hi>Grand Sestre,</hi> called for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly by the French <hi>Paris;</hi> where the reſt of our time we ſpent in our Negotiations and Trade.</p>
               <p>This Coaſt is called the Coaſt of
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:53662:51"/> 
                  <hi>Malaguette,</hi> in reſpect of the Pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per (which I have mentioned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) at <hi>Rio-Sextos,</hi> which amongſt the <hi>French</hi> is called <hi>Malaguette,</hi> or <hi>Maniguette,</hi> which commodity is more profitable than can be imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, eſpecially if Pepper be dear, and the <hi>Indy Fleet</hi> comes not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luckily in, but if that falls out, it ſells not altogether ſo well: This is the principal Commodity of this Coaſt, and is ſharper and hotter than the ordinary Pepper, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly than the white.</p>
               <p>All the Towns along theſe Coaſts are built upon the backs of ſome little River, or other which gives them their Names: The chief are <hi>Rio-Sanguin,</hi> the <hi>Grand Seſtre,</hi> which runs a good way up into the Countrey, and is deep enough to carry a <hi>Petach:</hi> which the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of <hi>Dieppe</hi> called <hi>Paris,</hi> in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of the aboundance of Pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per at both places.</p>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:53662:52"/>
               <p>All theſe Coaſts are bordered with great Trees, the land very low, and fatt, and water'd with ſo great a number of Brooks, and Rivelets, that they render the aire ſo very unhealthful, there are but few of the Whites can ſtay long there without being ſick.</p>
               <p>We underſtood nothing of their language, ſo they were put to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain themſelves by ſigns, they have no ill Phyſiognomy, their propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is good, they go always naked with their head, and have only a little piece of linnen before, for the ſhelter of their whole body: And though the aire be ſo ill, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wholſome, yet they are ſo hardy and ſtrong, I ſaw one of them that had a Rupture hung down to the middle of his legg, and a luſty cut over the Pate, that had lay'd his skull as naked as his back, and yet he came aboard us every day,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:53662:52"/> ſmoaking and drinking Strong-waters, with the beſt of them, as if he ail'd nothing at all.</p>
               <p>They work excellent well in Iron: at <hi>Grand Seſter</hi> they mended our ſhears for us, with which we cut out our barrs of Iron, and gave them ſuch a temper as made them incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parably better than they were at firſt.</p>
               <p>Beſides this Pepper, this Coaſt affords <hi>Rice</hi> and <hi>Millet</hi> (of which they make their bread, and brought us good ſtore of it) excellent Peas, (very tender and good, boyled) Beans, Citrons, Oranges, Bullys, and a kind of admirable Nutt, the ſhell ſomething thicker than ours, but without any skin over the ker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell, but all round like your Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds or <hi>Piſtaccios</hi> of <hi>Spain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They have likewiſe ſtore of Oxen, Cows, Goats, Hoggs, Pullen, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Fowl, which may be collected
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:53662:53"/> from the price that they bear.</p>
               <p>Their Palme-Wine is very good, and eſpecially the Plums, which are ſo pleaſant, I have ſeen them on Ship-board refuſe all that could be offered, to be crawnching of them; and this is all I can ſay of the Coaſt of <hi>Malaguette,</hi> for as to their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and manners, underſtanding but little, I ſhall ſay nothing at all, only I imagine they have as many Wives as they can keep, for the <hi>More</hi> at <hi>Rio-Sanguin,</hi> told us his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had fifty, and himſelf fifteen.</p>
               <p>The Inhabitants of <hi>Dieppe</hi> have traded long upon theſe Coaſts, and were grown ſo cunning at their Trade, they had found the way of mingling this Pepper with that of the <hi>Indies,</hi> before it was grown ſo common, and the <hi>Portugais</hi> had diſcovered the Iſland of St. <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas,</hi> and from thence diffuſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves all over <hi>Guinee,</hi> by which it
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:53662:53" rendition="simple:additions"/> appears we Traded there formerly, and every thing contributes to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm it, for beſides the <hi>Grand Seſter,</hi> which retaines ſtill the name of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> that little language they ſpeak intelligibly is <hi>French:</hi> They call not Pepper <hi>Sextos</hi> with the <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gals,</hi> nor <hi>Grain</hi> with the <hi>Hollander,</hi> but <hi>Malaguette</hi> with us and if a Veſſel at any time comes in, when their ſalutations are over, they cry out as loud as they can, <hi>Malaguette tout plein, tout plein, tant a terre de Malaguette,</hi> which is <hi>French</hi> they learned from us, and nothing elſe.</p>
               <p>If they meet any of their friends from a different place, they take one another by the upper part of the arm, and ſtretching them out, they cry <hi>Toma,</hi> then they come to the elboe, and graſping it hard they cry <hi>Toma</hi> again; and at laſt catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one another by the fingers, as I have obſerved at <hi>Rio-Sextos,</hi> they
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:53662:54"/> make them ſnapp as they did there, crying out <hi>Enfa Nemate, Enfa Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate.</hi> Which the <hi>More</hi> that ſpeak <hi>Dutch,</hi> interpreted to us, and told us it was no more then, <hi>My dear friend how is it, all that I have is at your ſervice, even to my life it ſelf.</hi> From which very complement we may conclude the language is more ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant then we imagine, to one that underſtands it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>THE COAST OF ELEPHANTS TEETH.</head>
               <p>ON <hi>Friday</hi> morning the 11th of <hi>February,</hi> we weigh'd an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor before <hi>Goyane,</hi> and ſteered a South-Eaſt courſe, to double the <hi>Cape de Palmes,</hi> and avoid the Rocks which incompaſs it, which we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:53662:54"/> for a while, and came at laſt to an anchor before <hi>Grova,</hi> which is the firſt place upon the <hi>Teeth-Coaſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This <hi>Cape</hi> is denominated from the Palme-trees, which doe ſhadow it on all ſides near the Sea, it riſes in ſeveral hills, covered all over with theſe kind of Trees, and lyes in four degrees and ten minutes of Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern latitude, and twelve and a half of longitude Eaſtward.</p>
               <p>The Coaſt alſo takes its name from the vaſt quantity of Elephants teeth ſold there, which is ſo great, that though all the Ships that are bound for <hi>Ardres</hi> or the <hi>Mine,</hi> doe paſs that way, yet they ſeldome or never have any Merchandiſe left, which they bring thither to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change.</p>
               <p>It extends it ſelf four and twenty leagues, from the <hi>Cape de Palmes</hi> to to the River <hi>d' Aſene,</hi> where the <hi>Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Coaſt</hi> begins, and contains theſe
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:53662:55"/> places upon the Sea: <hi>Crova, Tabo, Petit-tabo, Grand-drouin, Tao, Rio S. Andre, Giron, Petit-drouin, Bortrou, Cap la hou, Jacques la hou, Vallochk,</hi> and <hi>Gomma,</hi> where the ordinary trade is, where we ſpent ſeventeen dayes, without any conſiderable ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident, unleſs it be that which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd at <hi>Cap la hou.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On <hi>Saturday</hi> the 26th. being at anchor there, the Seamen diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a Ship making towards us with full ſayl; we imagin'd at firſt it might be the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Privatier the <hi>More</hi> had given us notice of at <hi>Rio-Sanguin;</hi> we weighed anchor imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately, and made as faſt towards him, having put out our <hi>French</hi> co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, which he ſaluted with a vol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley of Canon, and hung out the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours of <hi>Holland,</hi> which we gratify'd with another. He ſent forth his ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lop forthwith to diſcover us, and although he which commanded
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:53662:55"/> underſtood very well the greateſt part of our Equipage were <hi>Flemings,</hi> he could not be perſwaded aboard us, but return'd; a while after, the ſhallop came to us again, bringing their Lieutenant along, who came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board, was civilly recieved, &amp; ſtaid with us two hours; and in the mean time, this little Veſſel of <hi>Brittainie</hi> (though commanded by a <hi>Zelander,</hi> and was not above 100 Tunn) made like a Pinnace with 8 guns, and 40 men) ſayled round about our Veſſel, the Captain making his Drums and his Trumpets ſound all the while, with a thouſand other oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of joy. He told us for news, that at his departure from <hi>Fluſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> he came out with 26 other Privatiers in his company, but that they were diſpers'd in a Storm, and he heard nothing of them ſince: that as he was entring into <hi>Sierra Leone,</hi> he found the little
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:53662:56"/> Veſſel we ſaw as we came out, who complained, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> man which we had impriſoned and ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom'd again, had ſiezed his long boat or ſhallop, with nine of his men, whilſt they were fiſhing, and that the ſame <hi>Portugals</hi> we had tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded withall, had aſſiſted them; whereupon he thought himſelf ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to vindicate himſelf, and did it ſo effectually, that he beat the houſe down with his great Guns, killed ſeveral of the <hi>Mores</hi> which defended it, and reſcued his nine men, paying three thouſand weight of Ivory for their Ranſome, which had not been done, had not the <hi>Mores,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the approach of theſe two Ships, carryed them all into the Woods; we gave him a Collation, and then he took his leave. About midnight, the Captain himſelf came aboard us to drink and be merry with our Officers,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:53662:56"/> but he told us no more then his Lieutenant, only this, that the <hi>Mores</hi> who were by us when we weigh'd anchor to meet him, had come to him, and told him, in theſe words, <hi>If you be Engliſh, you muſt run for it, but if Dutch, you are ſafe enough.</hi> After which they all clapt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves down cloſe in their <hi>Canoes,</hi> to attend what would follow, and in caſe we had fought, and one of us been ſunk, to have had the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of the pillage: At his departure we gave him three Guns for a fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well, which he repayed exactly when he got aboard; we gave him a Cheeſe, two Barrels of Powder, and four Bullets, he told us he was bound for the <hi>Mine,</hi> from thence to <hi>Ardres,</hi> to <hi>Capolopo</hi> and <hi>Gonſalves,</hi> and that if he met with no prize there, he would go unto the Iſles; but we heard afterwards at the Iſle of S. <hi>Thomas,</hi> that he paſs'd by there
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:53662:57"/> with 400 <hi>Negroes,</hi> which he had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken about the <hi>Cap de Lopes,</hi> out of 2 Veſſels, which had put in there for freſh firſt water; the firſt yeilded without any reſiſtance, the other having loſt his maine maſt, he ſunk to the bottom.</p>
               <p>The ſame day the <hi>Mores</hi> percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving we were friends, came aboard us again, to finiſh their Markets, which being done, the next we ſet ſayle for the <hi>Golden Coaſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Countrey produces a great quantity of Rice, Peaſe, Beans, Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rys, Citrons, Oranges, Cochonuts, &amp;c. Beſides which the Natives brought us Suger-Canes aboard, of a very conſiderable bigneſs. 'Tis one of the beſt Countreys in <hi>Guinee,</hi> the Hills and the Valleys are admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, the great Rocks of Mountains, which are red, with the conſtant verdure of the Trees wherewith they are covered, by the variation
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:53662:57"/> of Colours make delicious proſpect: But even of theſe places the <hi>Grand Drouin,</hi> and the <hi>Rio</hi> S. <hi>Andre</hi> are the beſt.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Grand Drouin</hi> is ſituate in the midſt of a little River, which winds about a little Iſland betwixt 2 Mountains; it is encompaſs'd with excellent Meadows, and is waſh'd ſo gently by the water, you would think it was affraid to come near it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rio</hi> S. <hi>Andre</hi> of all <hi>Africk</hi> ts the propereſt place for building, the River of the ſame name, runs up far into the Countrey, and not far from the place where it falls into the Sea, it divides its ſelf into two branches, one running North-Weſt, and the other Eaſt: It is bordered on both ſides with very fair Trees, environed with fine Meadows and Fields, and is deep enough to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry a Yacht an indifferent way up. The Rock at the Sea ſide, at the
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:53662:58"/> mouth of the River, is three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred paces in circumference the top, which being flat, commands all the Countrey about it without any conteſt. 'Tis very ſteep to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Sea, and on the Eaſt-ſide, and indeed inacceſſible, unleſs by the River on the Weſt, which makes it ſo near being an Iſland, that the cutting but of 15 paces of earth, would make it one entirely; On all other ſides it is encompaſs'd with Rocks under water, upon w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> even a ſhallop would be loſt: The freſh water which comes out of a Fountain at the foot of a large Mountain, which covers this Rock on the North-ſide, may be defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from thence with the ſhot of a <hi>Faucon;</hi> and the Towns of <hi>Petit-Drouin, Tao,</hi> and <hi>Groua,</hi> are at no greater diſtance then the <hi>Grand-Drouin,</hi> which is only one league and no more: From the top of this
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:53662:58"/> Rock <hi>Giron</hi> may be diſcerned on the Eaſt, built upon the ſide of a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licate large Meadow, and <hi>Tabo</hi> on the Weſt at the end of a fair Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagnia, planted up and down with curious Woods, which run up a good way into the Countrey, and terminate at the foot of ſeveral great Mountains, which are viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble from thence.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturday</hi> the 9th of <hi>February</hi> we came to an anchor, and took in freſh water all the reſt of the day, as well as on the <hi>Sunday</hi> and <hi>Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> following, which gave me op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of conſidering theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing obſervations: The water we took in at this place ſerved us almoſt till we came at the Iſle of <hi>S. Thomas:</hi> The Fountain is very pure, but being ſhadow'd by a large Tree, at the fall of the leave, when they fall into the Fountain, they ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it ſomething black for a time.</p>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:53662:59"/>
               <p>Upon theſe Coaſts they have great quantities of Bullocks, Goats, Kids, Hoggs, and Dear, which are ſo cheep, one may buy a good Beef of them for a douzain of knives of about twenty pence, and a good Roe Buck for the ſame price.</p>
               <p>The People are well made, ſtrong, luſty, their limbs large and fat, but their looks auſtere and dreadfull, and 'tis reported they do eat the Whites: I never heard of any houſe built by the <hi>Europeans</hi> in theſe parts where they land but very rarely, and have as little to do with them as they can.</p>
               <p>'Tis not above thirteen or four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen years ago, ſince fourteen <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers</hi> were killed, and eaten at <hi>Rio S. Andre,</hi> as they were taking in freſh water, without any occaſion of quarrel; for which reaſon, we went alwayes well armed, and were alwayes upon our guard.</p>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:53662:59"/>
               <p>The common people wear only a linnen cloth before but the Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dees and Nobles of the Countrey are conſpicuous by a kind of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle they wrap about them, and a Ponyard by their ſides. They are great lovers of great heads of hair, which they breid for one another very handſomly, and then bind them up upon their heads, but the Womens hair they uſually cut.</p>
               <p>The women of <hi>Giron,</hi> and <hi>Petit-Drouin,</hi> had the curioſity to come and look upon us as we were take<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in water, and to bring their daughters along with them, the liniaments and features of their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were ſo juſt and regular, that (bate them the unhappineſs of their complexion) they were abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute beauties: Amongſt fifty of them which I ſaw, there was not any fat or tall, wheras on the contrary, not one of a hundred amongſt the men
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:53662:60"/> but are both: The women have only a cloth before, and the leaſt covered I obſerved any where upon thoſe Coaſts; if there be any thing beſides their colour amiſs in their faces, it is, that they threaten re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge and miſchief a little too much. When they come aboard any Ship, the Captain of it muſt come to them, and it is their cuſtom whilſt they have one foot upon their <hi>Canoe,</hi> and the other upon the Ship, holding by one hand upon the Rope, they dip the other in the Sea, and throw their handfull upon his head, which is intended as a great inſtance of kindneſs and ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and in this they are ſo perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiouſly ſuperſtitious, that without it they will never be forc'd nor perſwaded to enter any Ship: and when they would affirm any thing with more vehemence than ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, they uſe the ſame ceremony:
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:53662:60"/> They are ſo diffident and diſtruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, they will never begot with all the art can be uſed, either under deck, or into any of the Cabains, which the <hi>Mores</hi> of all other parts, would do very freely.</p>
               <p>They have a great fancy for brace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets of Iron, with rings and bells up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, with which kind of Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantry, moſt of their arms, and legs, are plentifully furniſh'd; they have great ſtore of <hi>Mulettoes</hi> among them.</p>
               <p>We could not underſtand their language, nor they ſpeak one word of <hi>Portugais:</hi> When they came firſt aboard us, they cryed <hi>Qua, Qua, Qua,</hi> which we found after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to be as much as, <hi>you are welcome,</hi> or <hi>good morrow;</hi> for which reaſon the <hi>Hollanders</hi> have given the name of <hi>Quaqua</hi> to a good part of this Coaſt: they made great uſe of that word, eſpecially if their Gutts had been filled.</p>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:53662:61"/>
               <p>The Commodities which this Countrey yeilds, are Elephants teeth, ſo large ſometimes, that they weigh 200 weight a piece, and then they are worth 10000 livers: If we may credit thoſe that live on the <hi>Gold Coaſt,</hi> which are their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, they have ſo great number of Elephants, that they are forc'd for their ſecurity againſt them, to make their houſes under ground: They kill as many of them as they can: but that which accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dates them with ſo many teeth, is, that the Elephants doe ſhed them every three year, as the Staggs doe their Horns.</p>
               <p>This Countrey affords likewiſe good ſtore of Cotton, of which they make a pritty ſort of ſtuff, ſtrip'd with white, and blew, about three quarters broad, and three or four ells long, which is much valued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, and ſold afterwards
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:53662:61" rendition="simple:additions"/> at a good rate upon the <hi>Gold Coast,</hi> to cover their Peſantry there.</p>
               <p>They have Gold amongſt them likewiſe undoubtedly, for without any Commerce or communication with their Neighbours, they bind up their hair for the moſt part with hair laces of Gold very curiouſly made; I made a ſign to one of them, to know which way they came by it, and he ſhow'd me the great Mountaines up the Countrey afar off, and ſign'd to me from thence. for which reaſon, he that ſhould make further diſcovery of theſe parts, would queſtionleſs encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter many rarities, and without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great difficulties, in regard the Countrey conſiſts for the moſt part of Plaines. The Inhabitants here are more afraid off fire armes, then of all the inventions in <hi>Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 26 of <hi>February</hi> we weigh'd
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:53662:62"/> anchor, and continuing our courſe all <hi>Sunday,</hi> about evening we made the <hi>Golden Coaſt,</hi> and ſtood to it directly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>COSTE D' OR, <hi>OR THE GOLD COAST.</hi> With a Relation of our occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences there.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>M<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nday</hi> the laſt of <hi>February,</hi> we came to an anchor, at ſixteen fathom low water, at <hi>Asbini,</hi> the firſt place upon the <hi>Gold Coast:</hi> The Countrey thereabouts is very low: the Town is ſeate'd upon the mouth of a River of that name, which runs up North-Weſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Hills, and South into the Sea, we ſtay'd there 3 days bartring for Gold-Sand.</p>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:53662:62"/>
               <p>The 4th of <hi>March</hi> we paſt before <hi>Albiani, Tabo,</hi> and other Towns, upon that Coaſt: The Countrey there is but low likewiſe, very full of Trees, but no River at all: Thoſe <hi>Canoes</hi> which came aboard us ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving aſſured us, they had no Gold, we gave them the go by, and paſt on.</p>
               <p>We thought to have doubled the <hi>Cape</hi> of <hi>Apollonia</hi> that night, but two of their <hi>Canoes</hi> coming up to us, and promiſing fair, we beleived them and caſt anchor.</p>
               <p>The next day ſome of their <hi>Canoes</hi> brought ſome Gold, which we bought of them, though it was not much: This <hi>Cape</hi> throws it ſelf a far into the Sea, and raiſing it ſelf by degrees into Hills, and then into a Mountain, makes no unpleaſant proſpect. But it is of no good acceſs, the Sea beating ſo violently upon it, there is great danger in approching: We weigh'd
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:53662:63"/> anchor again that night, but the weather being calme, we could not reach <hi>Axime</hi> before <hi>Sunday</hi> in the afternoon, at which time we came to an anchor.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Axime</hi> is a Fort belonging to the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> ſome twelve leagues di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant from the <hi>Cape Apollonia,</hi> ſituate upon the ſide of a River, which runs up Northward alſo into the Countrey, and abounds with Gold-Sand, which is eſteem'd the beſt of all that Coaſt. Its banks are higher than either <hi>Asbini,</hi> or <hi>Cape Apollo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia:</hi> Before this place we ſtay'd all <hi>Sunday</hi> and <hi>Munday,</hi> but perceiving the <hi>Dutch</hi> obſtructed the <hi>Mores</hi> coming aboard us, we weigh'd an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor on <hi>Tueſday,</hi> and doubled the <hi>Cape de Tres-Puntas,</hi> ſo called from three Mountains which appear ſo at a diſtance, and by the conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of their poſition, do make two little, but convenient Bayes.</p>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:53662:63"/>
               <p>In the afternoon we appear'd before <hi>Botrou,</hi> which is another little Fort belonging to the <hi>Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> ſituate beyond the <hi>Cape</hi> upon an eminence, at whoſe foot runs a brook that is not unpleaſant: We ſtay'd here as long as we had any Trade, and departed the 11th. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Friday.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We weigh'd anchor at that time, and came to anchor again betwixt <hi>Saconde</hi> and <hi>Takorai,</hi> about ſix leagues diſtant from <hi>Botrou,</hi> they are ſeated amongſt the Mountains, which lean as it were upon the banks of the River they lye ſo near it; at which place, we received Letters from the Governour of <hi>Frederisbourg,</hi> not far from <hi>Cape Corſe,</hi> offring us his road (if we pleaſed) in conſideration of the alliance betwixt <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark,</hi> deſiring us alſo to ſecure ſome of his Merchandiſe for him.</p>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:53662:64"/>
               <p>We remained there <hi>Friday</hi> and <hi>Saturday,</hi> and it was no ſmall trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to me to ſee an antient Fort which had been formerly ours, in its ruines and rubbiſh; it was at <hi>Takorai,</hi> upon a Mountain which commanded the whole Countrey, the ſides of it ſpake it but barren, being quite naked of either Trees or Graſs, and the ſtone of a reddiſh complexion.</p>
               <p>On <hi>Sunday</hi> the 23th. we weigh'd anchor, and in two hours appear'd in the road <hi>de Comendo,</hi> whoſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants are greater lovers of the <hi>French,</hi> than of any other <hi>Europe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans:</hi> The Town (that may conſiſt of about a hundred houſes) is built on the Sea-ſide, and watered by a Rivulet, which falling into the Sea likewiſe on the South, forms a prit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Channel and Harbour for <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noes,</hi> and Shallops: The Eaſt-ſide lyes low, but the Weſt riſes into a
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:53662:64"/> hill, which being flat a top, is very convenient to build upon. The houſe appertaining formerly to the <hi>French,</hi> ſtands upon the North-end of the Town, which runs up into the Countrey, and rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes it ſelf into little hills by degrees, at whoſe feet there are very fair Fields, and Meadows, planted up and down with variety of fruit.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Mores</hi> which came aboard us, were in great anxiety and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order to reſolve which way they ſhould ſignifie their joy. Their King held his Court ſome four leagues from us in the Town <hi>de Grand Comendo,</hi> he ſent us freſh meat, and other preſents, invited us a ſhore to his Court, proffer'd us all the commodities af the Town, and ſent us word, that he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus'd a banner which <hi>Walkembourg</hi> (who was General for the <hi>Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> at the <hi>Mine</hi>) had ſent him, and
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:53662:65"/> return'd him this anſwer; <hi>That the Countrey had been alwayes in the poſseſſion of the</hi> French, <hi>and that they only ſhould be welcome thither.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We returned him many thanks, ſent him our preſents, and ſtay'd where we were to the 16. of <hi>March,</hi> and then ſet ſayl for <hi>Frederisbourgh,</hi> and came before the Caſtle of <hi>Mine</hi> before night: we found three Veſſels in that road, but not conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable. This Caſtle I ſhall ſay nothing of being ſo famous both for its ſituation, the commiodity of its Harbour and Fort, and the great Trade which is drove there.</p>
               <p>Two hours after we paſt before <hi>Cape Corſe,</hi> where the <hi>Engliſh</hi> have a very ſtrong Fort, which made re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance to all the <hi>Dutch Fleet,</hi> under the command of <hi>du Ruiter.</hi> The Harbour is very ſafe, and the Caſtle fortifyed with three Batteries, one above the other: The Town con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:53662:65"/> of more than 200 houſes, in the middle of which there is daily kept ſo conſiderable a Market, that it is eminent for its plenty all over thoſe Coaſts.</p>
               <p>At length about 3 hours after we came before <hi>Frederisbourg,</hi> and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luting the Governour with 5 Guns, he returned our civility with 3, which we again requited with one.</p>
               <p>The Caſtle of that name was built by the <hi>Danes,</hi> in aſſiſtance to the <hi>Mores,</hi> after they were beaten from <hi>Cape Corſe</hi> by the <hi>Dutch,</hi> which was taken from them again by the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> with the aſſiſtance of the <hi>Dane,</hi> and as a mark of their intereſt, he retains a great houſe at the end of the Town, with a <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> Officer and Garriſon, and the colours of <hi>Denmark</hi> ſet out upon the top on't.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Frederisbourgh</hi> is ſeated upon a high Mountain, which runs up
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:53662:66"/> into a point: The whole circuit of it amounts not to 300 paces, and commands all about it, even <hi>Cape Corſe</hi> it ſelf, which is not above Muſquet ſhot from it: The forme of the Plott upon which it is built is round, but the Fort triangular, fortifyed with three Baſtions, one of them playes Southward upon the Road, the other Weſtward up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Cape Corſe,</hi> and the third to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Fort <hi>de Naſſau</hi> or <hi>de Moure</hi> to the Eaſt. The foot of this Mountain (which is not above 100 paces high) and cannot be aſcended but by going about) is compaſs'd by houſes which the <hi>Mores</hi> have built that inhabit there.</p>
               <p>We were no ſooner at anchor, but we diſpatch'd one immediately with our complement to the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, called <hi>Henry Dalbreckhe,</hi> a <hi>Hamburger</hi> borne; he was but a little man of his perſon, but fierce,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:53662:66"/> and brisk, and yet courteous with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, witt enough; and very civil.</p>
               <p>He ſent his Secretary aboard us, by name of <hi>Daſſe</hi> of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> who had been there ſix years; he came in a <hi>Canoe;</hi> conducted by 8 Slaves, which ſang and ranted all along as they row'd, which it ſeems is the cuſtom when they bring any Whites with them, and before they put them aboard, they row three times about the Veſſel, with as much force and expedition as they can row. As he enter'd, we gave him 3 Guns, and ſpent the reſt of that day and night in his entertainment: This night we had the greateſt ſtorme we had ſeen all our voyage, in ſo much, we were oblig'd to caſt out our greateſt anchor, but it ceaſt at laſt, and the next day having lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by ſuch commodities as the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral had deſired, he took his leave and returned.</p>
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:53662:67"/>
               <p>On <hi>Saturday</hi> morning our Nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry going aſhore with the Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe he deſired, they ſhot from <hi>Cape Corſe</hi> at our ſhallop, and the bullet fell within ſix or ſeven foot of them: The Governour of <hi>Frederisbourg</hi> immediately fired a great Gun up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Caſtle, and the bullet fell at the foot of the ſecond Battery, to which they replied, but without balls, ſeeing the General took us in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his protection, and after that u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed no act of hoſtility more. The reaſon was, becauſe, though there be war declared betwixt <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Denmark,</hi> upon the <hi>Hollanders</hi> account, yet the Generals of theſe two Forts have made an amicable agreement, to commit nothing of hoſtility betwixt themſelves, and it is ſo punctually obſerved, the Souldiers of both Garriſons meet daily, eating and drinking toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at their pleaſures.</p>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:53662:67"/>
               <p>The two and twentieth I went on ſhore my ſelf, &amp; was receiv'd with all civillity, and very good cheer by the General, he enquired of me what news, I anſwered him in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin, which he ſpake very well, but no French at all: I underſtood from him, that the Kings of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey had been at wars four years, which was a great impediment to their Trade; that we ſhould find three <hi>Engliſh</hi> Veſſels in <hi>Ardres</hi> road, and that he was obliged to ſend proviſions to <hi>Chriſtiansbourgh,</hi> where the war was yet ſo hot, all that Countrey lay unmanured: in ſhort, I was ſo much engaged to him, that upon ſeveral occaſions which I had to converſe with him, he us'd all means to ſatisfie my cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity, and to inſtruct me in the manners of the Countrey.</p>
               <p>All the reſt of that month, and the four firſt dayes of <hi>April,</hi> we
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:53662:68"/> ſpent in traffique, and on the fifth we diſcern'd a <hi>Petach</hi> paſſing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the <hi>Mine,</hi> with a great ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lop full of Souldiers which the <hi>Dutch</hi> General ſent to <hi>Cormentin,</hi> a Fort which belongs to them: we were ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly ignorant of the deſign, but were told afterwards by the <hi>Mores,</hi> that the Governour of that Fort being gone to <hi>Anembou</hi> with ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of his Souldiers to drink and be merry (there being the beſt Palm-wine in <hi>Africk</hi>) had been ſeized upon, and all his company with him, by the King of that Countrey, in whoſe dominions <hi>Cormentin</hi> ſtood, and that two of them en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to defend themſelves, were killed: the ground of this Inſurrection was this; The King of <hi>Fantin</hi> having ingaged himſelf to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> at <hi>Cape-Corſe,</hi> to put them again into poſſeſſion of that Fort, had given them his Son in
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:53662:68"/> hoſtage, and deſiring to have him reſtor'd, and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> refuſing till his Articles were perform'd, he had ſeized upon the Governour, and 4 other <hi>Hollanders,</hi> with deſign to exchange them for his Son.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thurſday</hi> the 7th of <hi>April,</hi> we had news that the Controuler ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral of <hi>Holland</hi> was killed at <hi>Axime,</hi> and the <hi>Mores</hi> of thoſe parts had un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>animouſly declared for the <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That day we arreſted two <hi>Mores</hi> in our ſhip, and kept them priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, to ſecure a debt due to us from two Merchants on ſhore; they continued two days with us, but the <hi>Denmark</hi> General interpoſing, we gave them their liberty, and were paid by the Merchants with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in eight days afterward.</p>
               <p>On <hi>Good-Friday</hi> the 8th of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pril,</hi> we weighed anchor in order to our paſſage to <hi>Eniacham,</hi> a Town about four leagues diſtance from
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:53662:69"/> 
                  <hi>Frederisbourg,</hi> who gave us his guns when we went off, and we return'd ours in requital. We ſail'd by <hi>Moure,</hi> where the Fort of <hi>Naſsau</hi> is, which belongs to the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> &amp; is ſome two leagues and a half from the Caſtle of the <hi>Mine.</hi> This fort is ſcituate upon a Rock, flank'd with four Baſtions, the Sea waſhes the foot of it, and the Town of <hi>Moure</hi> (which conſiſts of about two hundred houſes) encompaſſeth it about on all ſides but towards the Sea: it holds of the King of <hi>Acanis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petit,</hi> as well as the Town of <hi>Icome,</hi> which is not above a quarter of a league from it, on the Sea-ſide too.</p>
               <p>In the afternoon we came to an anchor before <hi>Eniacham,</hi> where the <hi>Engliſh</hi> have a little Fort upon a little Eminence, about ſix hundred paces within land: near which the King of <hi>Sabou</hi> has a Town, of whom <hi>Eniacham</hi> holds likewiſe.
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:53662:69"/> We ſaluted the Fort with 3 Guns, which they return'd immediately.</p>
               <p>On <hi>Eaſter</hi> day the tenth of <hi>April,</hi> the <hi>Mores</hi> brought us good ſtore of their Palme-Wine, and aſſured us their Merchants would come down the next day, and bring us gold enough: On <hi>Munday</hi> they ſent us a <hi>Fricaſſee</hi> of Pullets; (which they dreſs as well as in <hi>France,</hi> as I ſhall mention hereafter) and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted us, that the King of <hi>Fantins</hi> Souldiers had entred <hi>Sabou</hi> in the night, killed four men, &amp; ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſeveral Priſoners. Upon which the Town of <hi>Sabou</hi> had ſent away their Wives and Children, and put themſelves in arms: We ſmelt their deſign, and reſolved to return that night to <hi>Frederisbourg,</hi> having nothing to do at <hi>Cormentin,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> nor at <hi>Akara,</hi> by reaſon of the wars that King had with <hi>Tacara.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:53662:70"/>
               <p>From <hi>Eniacham</hi> we could ſee <hi>Cormentin,</hi> but not diſtinguiſh the Fortifications by reaſon of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance: It is ſituate upon a Hill, and belongs to the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> who have a houſe at <hi>Fantin</hi> alſo, and another at <hi>Nemabon,</hi> a Town in the ſame Kingdom.</p>
               <p>On <hi>Tueſday</hi> in the afternoon we ſet ſayle for <hi>Frederisbourg,</hi> by the benefit of a North wind from the Hills, which blows conſtantly on this Coaſt from midnight till noon, and about nine a clock we came to an anchor again: We ſtay'd there till we had put off all our commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, and then away for the Iſle of <hi>Saint Thomas,</hi> having been two months upon the <hi>Golden Coast:</hi> and forty dayes in <hi>Frederisbourg</hi> road, where I went on ſhore again, to inform my ſelf more particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the Manners and Cuſtoms of the Inhabitants of the <hi>Golden Coast:</hi>
                  <pb n="131" facs="tcp:53662:70"/> I had the good fortune to ſee the moſt of their curioſities, and to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie and inform my ſelf of the reſt from the General, the Miniſter, and the <hi>Mores</hi> of <hi>Frederisbourg,</hi> who all of them ſpake <hi>Portugais.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>The Deſcription of the <hi>GOLDEN COAST.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Golden Coaſt lies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt four degrees and a half, and ſix and a half of Northern lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and betwixt 17 and 20 of lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude Eaſt: it has taken its name from the vaſt quantity of Gold is brought yearly from thence, as well from their Mines, as the Sand in their Rivers, and contains (beſides the places above mentioned) <hi>Rotou, Ronate,</hi> and <hi>Akara,</hi> which lye more to the Eaſt; its extent is a hundred
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:53662:71"/> and thirty leagues. The bank of <hi>Asbini,</hi> which is but low in <hi>Ax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ime,</hi> riſes near <hi>Achema</hi> to a Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and then humbling it ſelf to <hi>Cape Corſe,</hi> it raiſes it ſelf again, and continues ſo the reſt of the Coaſt; the circumference compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending the in-land Countrey and all, contains about four hundred leagues, divided into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of <hi>Asbini, Axime, Comendo, Fetu, Acanis-Petit, Sabou, Fantin, Akara,</hi> and the Seignories of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brambou</hi> and <hi>Takara,</hi> all which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon the King of <hi>Acanis le grand,</hi> who is called <hi>Akim,</hi> (whoſe Imperial Town is ſitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate 90 leagues Northward of the <hi>Mine</hi>) and may be called an Emperour.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:53662:71"/>
               <head>Of the Stature and Proportion of the People of this Countrey, of their Wit, I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>clination, Induſtry, and Habits.</head>
               <p>THe Inhabitants of the Golden Coaſt are handſome, and well-proportioned, they have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing diſagreeable in their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, but the blackneſs of their Complexion; ſome of them have flattiſh noſes, and all of them little ears; their eyes are quick and ſpark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, but above all, their teeth as white as Ivory, of which they have a particular care, and for their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, are perpetually champ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a certain wood which grows in the kingdome of <hi>Acanis,</hi> which has a peculiar quality of making them white, of preſerving their gums, and preventing any black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or rottenneſs in them. Though
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:53662:72"/> their beards appear not ſo ſoon as ours, yet they affect them exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, and their Grandees and Officers wear them very long upon their chins, and ſome of them like the <hi>Capuchins</hi> with us. Their skin is black indeed, but ſmooth and delicate, without any hair, but as they grow old, their blackneſs leſſens, and their hair which is ſhort, black, and frizell'd, grows grizled by degrees.</p>
               <p>Their Stomachs are generally ſo hot, they do not only digeſt all kind of meats that are roaſted or boyled, but raw likewiſe; and ſome there are among them which prefer that to the other.</p>
               <p>They are great lovers of cleanli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and waſh themſelves dayly to prevent Vermin, rubbing after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward with oyl of Palmes. They are not at all aſhamed of their nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity, but they have ſo great an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horrency
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:53662:72"/> and deteſtation of belch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or any ſuch thing, that they will ſooner die than do it; and if it happens at any time they be in the company of any <hi>Europeans</hi> that are guilty of it, they run out of the room immediately, making the horribleſt faces imaginable.</p>
               <p>They have a great deal of wit, are ſolid in their judgements, cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and ſo dexterous and quick, one need never ſhew them the ſame thing twice: they are lyers to the higheſt degree, their memory tranſcendent, and though they can neither write nor read, yet they manage their Trade with the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt exactneſs: they never diſpute the commands which are laid upon them: you ſhall have a Merchant negotiating and managing 4 Marks of gold for 20 ſeveral perſons, every particular man deſiring five or ſix ſeveral Commodities, which he
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:53662:73"/> performs without haſitation or miſtake.</p>
               <p>Their addreſs appears abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly by their dexterity in their Commerce, they are all of them given to pilfering, covetous to that point, eſpecially to the Whites, that they think they do a mighty act, if they preſent them with a little fruit: they are drunken, luxurious, and much ſubject to the <hi>Lues Venerea,</hi> which is no ſcandal amongſt them: they are but ill paymaſters, and ſatisfie their debts with great difficulty and unwillingneſs: they are great enemies to cold weather, and endure it with much impatience: ſo proud, that their Merchants, (who are all of them Nobles, Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, or other great Officers) march up and down the Streets with their eyes fix'd upon the ground, not vouchſafing ſo much
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:53662:73"/> as a glance upon the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: behind them they have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly a Slave with a chair in his hand, that they may ſit down when they pleaſe, it being thought diſhonourable to be too long upon their leggs; they never anſwer any ordinary perſon, but with great ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perciliouſneſs, and never ſpeak to them but with great Majeſty: to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther people they are civil enough, and pay very much reſpect to the Whites, eſpecially if they be Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, to whom they never ſpeak but with their hat in their hand. The ſureſt way of gaining their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, is to be civil to them which they value more than any other thing one can do.</p>
               <p>Though the manner of their habits be much different from ours yet they are as curious and as proud in them, as the beſt of us. When their Officers or Mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chants
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:53662:74"/> walking the Streets, or are in tranſaction with any Stranger, they take a piece of Silk, Taffaty, or fine Indian Damask, about two or three Ells long, which they tye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout their waſte, and afterwards bringing it betwixt their thighs, they let the two ends hang down before and behind almoſt to the ground. Sometimes they wrap o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Stuffs about them, from their breaſt to their mid-legg, or elſe throw it over their ſhoulders like a Mantle.</p>
               <p>They order their hair in ſeveral ways; but rich, and poor, and all, are very curious in adjuſting it hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomely, and inventing new modes and gallantries to adorn it, it being the only buſineſs almoſt which gives their women imployment. Moſt of them dave hats, ſome of Straw, ſome of the Bark of trees, ſome of Goats-skin, but their Slaves
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:53662:74"/> are diſtinguiſh'd by going bare-headed: they trim themſelves up with divers Necklaces of <hi>Raſade,</hi> and Bracelets, which they beautifie with little works of Gold, in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to their God, after they have muttered out ſome of their Prayers over it: they have Rings or Jewels upon the ſmall of their Leggs, or elſe a ſtring of Coraile, of the bark of the Tree, under which they pay worſhip to their <hi>Fetiches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Though they love exceedingly to be ſpruce yet, they are good houſe-wives of their cloths, never put on their finery but upon ſome ſuch extraordinary occaſion as I have mentioned, and then whip and off with them again as ſoon as they come home, folding them up care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and putting them into cheſts, which they buy of the <hi>Europeans</hi> for that purpoſe, where they lye ſnugg till ſome new opportunity
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:53662:75"/> brings them abroad again: Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs from the King to the Cob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler they affect change of apparel, to make themſelves more conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and that more or leſs accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their riches or gains. And yet for all this in the main they are frugal enough, will buy nothing that is ſuperfluous, but what they do buy, let it be ſtuff, or any thing elſe, they will be ſure it be laſting and good, or they will be ſure to have none of it, for all ſlight things they laugh at and deſpiſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Of the Women, their genious, humour, and habits.</head>
               <p>THE Women upon theſe Coaſts are generally well ſhap'd alſo, but ſome of them are little, and ſome great and corpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent: the young Women do place their principal care upon the
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:53662:75"/> whitening their teeth, and adorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their hair.</p>
               <p>They have witt enough, good <hi>mine,</hi> honeſt, and obliging, but much more curteous then the men; they are very grave, addicted to frugality in their houſes, but to pompe and oſtention abroad: But their laſciviouſneſs is above all, which they ſuck as it were with their milk, playing hoyty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toyty amongſt the young fellows ſtarke naked. There are but few of them barren before, but when married they are ſeldome over fertile, which may be attributed to their temper and complection, for there is ſeldome any of them have above four or five.</p>
               <p>The Virgins, (to pleaſe, and to enamour the young men, as ſoon as they are up every morning) take water and waſh, and then combe their haire (which they
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:53662:76"/> have in twice the plenty the men have) with great curioſity, pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and diſpoſing it in a hundred ſeveral modes and gallantries, gum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming it with oyl of Palmes, inſtead of mouth glew, tying it with ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands if they have any, if not, adorning it with little pieces of gold, or a certain red cockle ſhell, which is very common amongſt them. Some of them paint their foreheads with red and white, and ſometimes their eye-brows, and cheeks: they cut and carve their skins about their ears, and temples, which riſing up in little bliſters, they paint them over with divers colours, and fancy it a great addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to their beauty: they have all of them Pendants at their ears, they all of them love the Ribbands, and above all Ribbands, the red; they wear necklaces of Corail, or of <hi>Raſade,</hi> and bracelets not only
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:53662:76"/> upon their wriſts and their armes, but upon their leggs, and their ankles; the maidens for the moſt part have their bracelets made of the bark of that tree which is dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to their <hi>Fetiches,</hi> which are their Gods as I ſhall ſhew hereafter. When they go abroad, if they be the Wives of Merchants, Officers, or Captains, in that Countrey, they have a piece of Silk, Taffaty, or other Stuff, either red, or blew, or violet-colour'd (which are the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours they are moſt pleaſed with) which they take and wrap about them, from the breaſt to the mid-legg, ſtuffing it out behind with a great Rouler. They have alwayes a great bunch of keys at their gir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, though they have many times never a Cheſt in the world: they wear bracelets of Ivory, and Gold, and Rings in that abundance, one can ſee no fingers that they have
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:53662:77"/> ſometimes; and in this poſture they are fit to be ſeen: the common ſort dreſs them ſelves as fine as they can too, but when they come in again, they are mighty careful to ſold them up handſomely, putting on a kind of coarſe linnen with which they make ſhift to cover themſelves from the Navel, to the midſt of their Thigh. They love variety of habits too as well as the men, but the Virgins eſpecially, who make it their whole buſineſs from morning to night to ſpruce up themſelves, and make themſelves acceptable, above all to the Whites, whom they ſeem to careſs much more than thoſe of their own Complexion.</p>
               <p>Their Ladies of pleaſure, are not diſtinguiſhable in any thing, they are welcome where-ever they go, and handſomly received by every body; but they are more mercena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:53662:77"/> and covetous than in any other part of the world.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Of their Marriages, and the Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of their Children.</head>
               <p>I Happen'd to be preſent at a Marriage whilſt I was at <hi>Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derisbourg,</hi> which was conſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in no unpleaſant manner. The Father of a young man finding him at age to get his living himſelf, looks out immediately for a Wife for him, &amp; having pitch'd upon one he thinks will be proper, he goes to his Son, tells him what he has done, adviſes him to ſee her, if they like one another, his Father deſires her of hers, if they agree, they go all of them together with one of the Prieſts who gives them <hi>Fetiches,</hi> and in the preſence of the whole Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, the Bride takes a ſolemne Oath upon the <hi>Fetiche</hi> to be true
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:53662:78"/> and faithfull to her good man; her Groom promiſing on the other ſide as much to her very civilly, but no Oath of fidelity in the caſe. The Parents preſent one another reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procally, and give in the bride and the Bridegroom what they are able to ſpare, they ſpend the reſt of the day in feaſting and jollity, and there's an end of the Marriage.</p>
               <p>However this Lady has this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage over her Spouſe, by being his firſt love, that he can never take another, but by her permiſſion, which yet her Ladyſhip is ſeldome ſo moroſe as to deny. But it was my fortune to ſee a young Merchant of the <hi>Mine</hi> who had worſe luck, his name was <hi>Anthony,</hi> he came ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times aboard our ſhip, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver with leſs than 10 or 12 Marks of Gold; amongſt other diſcourſe, I ask'd him one day how many Wives he had, he told me but one,
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:53662:78"/> and the reaſon was, ſhe was ſo croſs grain'd a Jade, ſhe would let him have no more; and then told me very ſeriouſly, that amongſt them that cuſtome was inviolable.</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs, all women know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very well, that variety of Wives and Children is the greateſt honour and reputation to their husbands, and what they themſelves will boaſt of to Strangers: when they ſee their husbands grow wealthy, and in a capacity of maintaining them, they themſelvs wil preſs them to take more, which to ſpeak truly, are no other then Concubines, they being not at all concern'd for their liberty or incontinence: the firſt has this priviledge alſo, that ſhe lyes 3 nights ſucceſſively with the good man, whilſt the younger brood muſt be contented with one, and that according to the priority of their Marriage. In ſhort, they live
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:53662:79"/> very lovingly together, and have ſeldome any jealouſies or animoſity amongſt them. A good Merchant, or Officer, will have twenty or thirty, according to his abilities. The King of <hi>Fetu</hi>'s Son-in-Law had forty, by whom he had a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zain of daughters, fourteen to the douzain of the other Sex, and kept conſtantly a hundred Slaves to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend them.</p>
               <p>In thoſe parts, who will may come into the Chamber of any Woman when ſhe lyes in: as ſoon as the Child is ſafe in the world, they bring the good Woman a bottle of drink made of Rice, and Mays, and Water and Wine, and <hi>Malaguette,</hi> (not unlike our Pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Poſſet) which having taken off kindly, they cover her well, and then leave her three or four hours to her devotions, which being over, ſhe riſes immediately, waſhes her
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:53662:79"/> Child, falls to her buſineſs, and there's an end of that labour; but (to be ſober) I could not but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire very much the force of their temper, when I ſaw the very ſame thing done by a Slaves Wife at <hi>Frederisbourg.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As ſoon as they have waſh'd their Child, the Father and Mother give it commonly a name, and for the moſt part, of ſome <hi>European</hi> or other they have been beholding to, that done, they wrap it in a kind of blanket, and then lay it in a skin upon the Ruſhes, where it lyes quietly till it be three weeks or a month old, after which time the Mother carries it at her back upon a piece of wood with the leggs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der her armpits, tying its two hands about her neck, where it hangs all day, and never comes off, but when ſhe goes to bed; and this is the reaſon why the Children of
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:53662:80"/> their Nobles, or better ſort, have ſeldome camous noſes, becauſe their Wives do not labour, nor carry their Infants about them, as the others do, whoſe Children ſleeping many times whilſt the Mother is walking or at work, knock their noſes againſt their Shoulders, and ſo in time they become flat: if they cry out for the teat, they throw their breaſts over their ſhoulders, and let them ſuck. Every morning they waſh and rub them with Oyl of Palmes.</p>
               <p>By that time they be 7 or 8 months old, they lay them along upon the ground, drawing them forward upon all four, like Kitlings, which poſſibly may be the reaſon the Children go much ſooner in theſe Countreys than in <hi>Europe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whilſt they be thus tender and young, the Parents put little works of gold about their necks, wrapt up
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:53662:80"/> in the rind of the tree where they worſhip their <hi>Fetiches,</hi> for fear the Devil ſhould run away with them, and when they come to be about 4 year old, they bind little branches of it (which they buy of their Prieſts) about their arms, and their leggs, wreathing and bending them into a round figure, which they look upon as a great Antidote a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any ſickneſs or diſaſter what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever. In this manner they conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue their care of them till they be 7 or 8 years old, but after that they feed upon the ſame as the Father and Mother does, heaping up ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny time ſuch naſty things as they find in the Streets, which they eat afterward very heartily, when they are hungry: the boys and the gyrls, being higledy-pigledy to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and all naked, it takes off much of their modeſty, and is a cauſe they are never aſhamed of
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:53662:81"/> any thing; to which may be added their want of correction, their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents being ſo far from whipping them, they never ſo much as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke them in the leaſt.</p>
               <p>From the ſeventh or eighth year of their age they learn to ſwim, which they do with ſo much ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs and perfection, that when they are grown up, if their <hi>Canoe</hi> over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſets at any time at Sea, they are not affrighted, but ſwim back again ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry quietly from whence they came, they will dive excellently well too, and fetch up goods or any other thing that is accidentally caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, upon which ſcore one may ſee the ſhore ſo full ſometimes of little Blacks, one would think them ſo many young Devils.</p>
               <p>At 12 year old they fall under the juriſdiction of the Father, who ſhews them which way to get their livelyhood: if he be a fiſherman he
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:53662:81"/> carries them to Sea, ſhews them how to make a <hi>Canoe,</hi> and which way to take fiſh; if a Merchant he teaches them the miſtery of Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, brings them acquainted with Forreigners, and inſtructs them in this manner till they be 18 or 20, and can begin to do ſomething for themſelves, then he gives them Slaves to do their work, and all the care that is behind, is to help them to Wives, which from that time forward they are alwayes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triving.</p>
               <p>The Gyrls are imployed in keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing clean the houſes, in picking their Rice, beating their <hi>Mays,</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king their bread, managing their Kitchin, and buying or ſelling at the Markets what is to be bought or ſold, ſometimes they make bas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets of ruſhes, ſometimes matts (in which they are tranſcendantly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent) ſometimes weave, but above
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:53662:82"/> all their care is greateſt of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Mother, to ſee that they have their meat and drink in good hours, and that nothing of their goods be imbezled; in ſhort there is nothing of good houſewivry or frugality, that is wanting amongſt them, and when they are once marryed, they may teach that leſſon to moſt of the Women of <hi>Europe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Of their Houſes, Houſhold-ſtuff, Drinke, Meat, Palme-Wine, and how it is made.</head>
               <p>THe great Commerce they have had with the <hi>Europeans</hi> having learned them the art of building, the Officers and great Merchants of this Countrey have follow'd their directions and built themſelves houſes, with high and lofty roofes, ſeveral appartments,
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:53662:82"/> with one chamber opening into a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, and uſually at the door of their chamber 2 Slaves conſtantly attending with darts in their hands in the nature of guards, which are releived at certain hours.</p>
               <p>All their houſes are made of earth, but the common people have their walls ſo low, they ſeldome exceed the height of a man. Their beame and rafters, and the whole frame of the houſe reſting only upon them: the houſes of the Grandees as well as the commons are all thatch'd, and have all of them but one little ſquare hole, which ſerves for a door, to which they faſten a piece of board, without either lock or hinges, like the poor Peaſants in the Countrey to their Garden-doors, and are contented to faſten them only with a rope, either with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out or within. Their windows are ſmall, the earth they make their
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:53662:83"/> floors with, very cloſe and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact, they have at leaſt two cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers to a houſe, and this character muſt be given them, that they are very curious in keeping them neat, and paint them very frequently both without and within.</p>
               <p>Amongſt the common ſort, there is nothing of houſhould-ſtuff, or what is us'd commonly about the houſe, to be ſeen, all is locked up in their Coffers, which they buy of the Whites; except they be Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants or great men, and then their Tables and Chairs appear ſometimes, but never no Beds, for they lye alwayes upon Skins ſpread upon the ground, or elſe upon Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſes made of Ruſhes, covering themſelves with the Skins of Oxen, or ſome other Beaſt, without any Boulſter, except they be of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and then they have Pillows under their heads, and a good fire
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:53662:83"/> in the middle of their Room, but not the leaſt hole for a Chimney.</p>
               <p>Every woman has her appart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or little houſe, joyning to her Husbands, conſiſting of one or two Chambers, where ſhe mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges her own affairs by her ſelf, ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome eating or drinking together. Some of them go a Goſſipping to their Neighbours, and carry ſuch as they have along with them. The good man takes the ſame courſe, and he viſits his Merchant, not ſo much as concerning himſelf how ſquares go at home, the women be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alwayes very punctual to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodate them with every thing neceſſary, and to bring up their Children carefully; yet ſometimes on their Feſtivals, or upon ſome great occaſion, their Stomachs come down, and they feed very lovingly together.</p>
               <p>As the women have the charge
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:53662:84"/> of the houſe and the money, ſo they make it their whole buſineſs that neither of them miſcarry in their hands. The men employ themſelves conſtantly abroad, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in matters of Trade, or in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Palm-wine, or fiſhing, as every mans genius inclines him: when they have got any money, they give it ſtill to their wives, who order it ſo well, they never make the leaſt unneceſſary disburſement; they go every night themſelves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the granaries, delivering out ſuch a proportion of corn as they judge will be neceſſary for the whole fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily the next day.</p>
               <p>By break of day the young girles are up and at work, beating their <hi>Rice,</hi> and their <hi>Mays</hi> (which is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Turky</hi> wheat amongſt us) in a wooden Mortar, and when it is bruis'd, they grind it (as the Paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers do their colours.) betwixt two
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:53662:84"/> ſtones, and ſo reduce it to powder, then kneading it with water and ſalt, they divide it into a kind of penny loaves, and put it into a great earthen pot that ſtands upon the fire, with a little earthen lid, they throw embers upon it, &amp; 'tis done; if it be well bak'd, 'tis very good, and without any ill reliſh at all.</p>
               <p>Their food generally is fiſh, though they have great ſtore of fleſh alſo, which they boyl or roaſt as they think good, but their fiſh is moſt commonly bak'd, being ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon'd firſt with water, and pepper, and ſalt: the great Merchants who have Slaves to wait on them at the Table, do eat <hi>a l' Europeenne,</hi> and have their <hi>Ragousts</hi> as well made as in <hi>France,</hi> which they learn'd of us, and the Cook at the Fort of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark;</hi> yet there are ſome <hi>Mores</hi> will make a <hi>Pottage,</hi> or a <hi>Ragouſt</hi> with the beſt <hi>Cuiſinier</hi> in <hi>Paris.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="160" facs="tcp:53662:85"/>
               <p>They eat great ſtore of fruit, of Peas, Beans, and ſuch like: they make uſually but two meals a day, that is, at Sun-riſing, and Sun-ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, where they feed like Cormo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, and when they have eat ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo much, are hungry ſtill, which I impute to nothing but an exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive heat within them, which gives them a <hi>Canine,</hi> and perpetually in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatiable appetite, inſomuch that I have obſerved them when they have been at dinner a Ship-board, one Black has eat as much as ſix of us could do.</p>
               <p>Their Mornings draught is either of water, or a kind of ſmall beer, which they call <hi>Poitou,</hi> and is made of <hi>Mays,</hi> but 'tis night before they drink any Wine, and the reaſon is becauſe the Peaſant never brings it to the Market till after dinner.</p>
               <p>The Palm-Wine comes out of a Tree, not unlike our Date-trees;
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:53662:85"/> the <hi>Mores</hi> make a hole at the top of the tree, to which they faſten a pott, like one of the Monks pitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and the next day, or the day after, they find it full of a kind of juice like Milk, ſweet and very pleaſant, but with a quality to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ebriate The <hi>Mores</hi> have got a trick of late to ſophiſticate it, and put water amongſt it for their gain, but 'tis no hard matter to diſcover it. This Wine cannot be kept till next day, but will grow ſower in a nights time, upon which grounds, the Merchants, and other good fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows do meet, and drink ſmartly many times, but with this ceremony alwayes, that they leave a little in the bottome, which they throw upon the ground in honour of their <hi>Fetiches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thoſe who have no proviſion, nor means to make any, are forc'd to buy what they want (at a little
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:53662:86"/> Market hard by) with what they have got by fiſhing, by making Palme-Wine, by building or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing of houſes, carrying home what the Merchants have bought on Ship-board, and ſuch other ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile imployments as our Mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicks in <hi>France</hi> live by: to which Market the Whites go alſo ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times when their Stomach hangs after fiſh.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Of their Markets, their manner of buying and ſelling, with a deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their Meaſures and Weights.</head>
               <p>THe beſt Market in all <hi>Africk</hi> is held every day at <hi>Cape-Corſe,</hi> but we being at wars with <hi>England,</hi> I could have no ſight of that, and therefore muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with the Market at <hi>Frede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risbourg,</hi> which is not indeed ſo bigg, but there is the ſame thing obſerved in a place deſigned for
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:53662:86"/> the ſame uſe, and that is, that it be ordinarily in the midſt of the Town.</p>
               <p>By break of day the Peaſants come in with their Sugar-canes, bound up like Fagots, their fruits of all ſorts, <hi>Plums, Potatoes, Turnips, Carrets, Citrons, Oranges, Rice, Mays, Malaguette, Bread, Pullets, Fiſh, Eggs,</hi> and whatever is neceſſary for the life of man; after Dinner their Palme-wine comes in, and what Fiſh is taken ſince the morning.</p>
               <p>They have never no confuſion in their Markets, each Commodity has a peculiar place aſſigned for it by the Merchant, which is obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with great order; their Tobac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co is ſold in the leaf, which being dryed by the fire, they light it and ſmoak, their induſtry as yet not having been great enough to make it up into Rowls.</p>
               <p>There is no ſuch thing amongſt them as truſting or credit, no Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:53662:87"/> no Merchandiſe there, every one brings his Gold in his hand. If the Commodity be of ſmall price, they take their Gold and poiſe it upon the end of their finger, adding or ſubſtracting as they think fit; but if conſiderable, and of great value, they out with their Scales and weigh it.</p>
               <p>Their Scales are made of two flat pieces of Copper ſomething broad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than our Crown pieces, which they hang by a thread at the end of a ſhort ſtick, and ballancing ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly, there can be nothing more true. Having no Needle, they make a nooſe of thread with their thumb and faſten to the middle, in which, inſtead of weights, they hang a certain red grain they call <hi>Tacous,</hi> each of which grains weighs about two-Penny weight, with which <hi>Pian Piano,</hi> they will weigh a <hi>Mark of Gold,</hi> yet there are
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:53662:87"/> ſome great Merchants which have Scales like ours, which they have bought lately of us.</p>
               <p>All that comes to this Market, (which is kept every day in the week (<hi>Sunday</hi> excepted) is Tribute free, and pays no duty to the King.</p>
               <p>There are others that reſemble our Fairs, and fall out not above twice in the year, to which all the whole Countrey repairs, for there is never in any of thoſe Kingdoms two Fairs kept in one day, left one ſhould be a hindrance and diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to the other. By the report I have had, 'tis to theſe places they bring the beſt and fineſt of their things, and whatever they buy of us, as likewiſe to the ordinary Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets which are kept farther up into the Countrey, but to thoſe Markets which are kept nearer the Sea, there is nothing comes but what is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to humane life, which the Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:53662:88"/> bring (like ſo many Mules) upon their backs, and that but from 5 or 6 places: yet ſo ſtrict are they in their Religion, and doe ſo much poſtpone the conſiderations of their advantage and gain, that if any of theſe Fairs does happen to fall out upon a <hi>Sunday,</hi> it is <hi>ipſo facto</hi> put off till the next day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>THEIR RELIGION.</hi> Of their Sundays, Feaſts, Devotions, Gods or <hi>Fetiches,</hi> of their Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, Priests, and Habits.</head>
               <p>THough amongſt theſe poor people, there is not the leaſt tincture of the true Religion to be ſeen, yet they obſerve a Sabbath (which is our <hi>Tueſday</hi>) very ſtrictly: Every man reſts that day from his labour, the Peaſants bring nothing
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:53662:88"/> to the Markets, and no man is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to traffick, unleſs it be thoſe upon the Sea ſide, who have liberty to go aboard, any Veſſel in the Road, and to truck and make bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gains as they pleaſe. The reſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy their times wholly at their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions, and doe obſerve it with much more punctuality then we doe our Sundays with us.</p>
               <p>They meet altogether in a place, in the middle of which there is a great Tree, called the Tree of their <hi>Fetiche,</hi> of the barke off which they make the fillets, with which they bind their little pieces of Gold to their armes, and their leggs. At the foot of this Tree a Table is ſpread, (the feet dreſt with ſeveral Crowns and Garlands made of the boughs of trees) upon which they ſet Rice, Millet, Mays, Fruit, Meat, and Fiſh, with Wine, and Oyl of palmes, to eat and drink to their
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:53662:89"/> 
                  <hi>Fetiches,</hi> they dance, and ſing, and jump up and down all day about this Tree, making a moſt obſtrepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous noiſe with Copper Baſons, and other inſtruments for the purpoſe.</p>
               <p>They waſh their faces that mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with particular care, and more exactly then all the week after. The firſt bit of what ever they eat, they throw down upon the ground in honour of their Gods, and at night the Captain or the Governour di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributes Palme-Wine to all the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants, the Peaſants being obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to bring it to him that evening.</p>
               <p>Ask them about any thing of their faith, and they will look down upon the ground, but never give you an anſwer; only one of them told us that we had a very good God, that gave us ſo many fine things: They all of them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve an other life, but where, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther above or below, they cannot
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:53662:89"/> tell. For which reaſon, leſt their Father or Mother ſhould be hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry and ſtarve, they put meat and Palme-Wine very often into their graves, to the end that if they be thirſty or hungry, they may repair thither, and be relieved.</p>
               <p>When they hear it thunder, rain hard, or the wind blow very ſtrong, there is not one of them to be ſeen in the ſtreets, all hide themſelves in their houſes, and cry, <hi>the Gods of the Whites are angry.</hi> I ask'd one of them of what colour his God was, and he told me black: The Devil is ſo dreadfull to them, they tremble at his very naming, they ſay he beats them, and makes them do ill things for their <hi>Feti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,</hi> for whom they have an incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible ſuperſtition, though they be all of them inanimate, and ſome of them ſo naſtily villanous, one would not touch them with a pair of tongs.</p>
               <pb n="170" facs="tcp:53662:90"/>
               <p>They every body carry ſome of them about with them, ſome are made of the end of horns, fill'd up with ordure, others of little figures, as the heads of ſome creature or other, and a hundred ſuch like im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinences, which their Prieſts ſell them at their own price, and pretend they found them under the tree of the <hi>Fetiche.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They tye this tree about (which is the place where they ſacrifice) with little roaps of ſtraw, and after their Ceremonies are over, they take thoſe ropes, and ſtringing their gold work upon them, they faſten them to their arms and leggs, and then think themſelves ſafe againſt any miſchief whatever.</p>
               <p>For the preſervation of their houſes, they have a ſort of <hi>Fetiches</hi> which are planted at their dores, and they are no better than our poles, or hooks, we pull down the
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:53662:90"/> boughs withall when we gather our fruit: Of theſe <hi>Fetiches</hi> their Prieſts ſet a great number about a ſtone, which (by their tradition) is as old as the world, and when they have been there a certain time, the Prieſts ſell them to the people.</p>
               <p>If at any time any trouble befall them, they repair immediately to their Prieſt, for a new <hi>Fetiche</hi> (the old one is to be truſted no longer) who moſt graciouſly ſupplies them for their money, and into the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, <hi>he gives them a piece of Suet, or Tallow, with two or three Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rets feathers ſet right up, or elſe a certain hearb;</hi> the King of <hi>Fetu</hi>'s Son-in-Law had the head of an Ape for his <hi>Fetiche.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They do all of them abſtein from ſomething or other, in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of their <hi>Fetiche,</hi> with this opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that if ever they eat or drink
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:53662:91"/> of that, after they promis'd abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence (which is uſually at their Marriage) they ſhall dye upon the ſpot; for which reaſon, one eats no Beef, another no Goat, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther no Hens, this man drinks no Wine, and the other no Strong-waters, which they obſerve ſo exactly, they will ſooner dye than be perſwaded or forc'd to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
               <p>Theſe <hi>Fetiches</hi> I have ſpoken of hitherto, are but private <hi>Fetiches,</hi> and belong but to particular men: but they have another ſort of <hi>Feti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches</hi> which are tutelary to the whole Countrey, as for example, ſometimes ſuch a Mountain, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſuch a kind of Tree, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſuch a Stone, ſometimes ſuch a ſort of Fiſh, or ſuch a Species of Birds, which they look upon and worſhip as ſo many Gods. If a <hi>Negroe</hi> by accident kills any
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:53662:91"/> of thoſe Birds, he is puniſh'd ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently, and if a White, he runs a great hazard of his life. I ſaw one of theſe Birds at <hi>Frederisbourg,</hi> a little thing about the bigneſs of a Wrenn, with a Beak like a Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, mark'd with black and white, and the Feathers a kind of light brown: if any of theſe at any time are ſeen flying about in the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens of a <hi>More,</hi> 'tis look'd upon as a good Omen, and he throws it meat immediately.</p>
               <p>The Conſecrated Trees are or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily thoſe about which their Sacrifices are perform'd; they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve whoever cuts ſuch a one down, deſtroys (without more adoe) all the fruit in the Countrey: and therefore if there be any ſuch Malefactors, they are puniſh'd with death, as it happen'd to the <hi>Hollanders</hi> at <hi>Moure</hi> in the year 1598, before they had built the
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:53662:92"/> Fort of <hi>Naſsau,</hi> where 8 or 10 of them were killed the 8th. of <hi>May,</hi> for having cut down a Tree dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to their <hi>Fetiches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The higheſt Mountains, and ſuch as are moſt ſubject to Thunder and Lightning, they imagine are the Reſidences of their Gods, and therefore they pay great honour and reſpect to them: at the bottom of them they will lay <hi>Rice, Millet, Mays, Bread, Wine, Oyl,</hi> and other things, that they may eat and drink if they be hungry or dry.</p>
               <p>Their Stones (which they fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to be <hi>Fetiches</hi>) are like our great Land-marks in the Countrey, (or ſuch as are laid to diſtinguiſh and determine the bounds or li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of a Countrey Pariſh) and they believe them as old as the world: about theſe it is their Prieſts do ſet their Cruches which they ſell afterwards to the people for
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:53662:92"/> conſervation of their houſes, as I mentioned before.</p>
               <p>Beſides theſe <hi>Fetiches</hi> aforeſaid, if five or ſix Neighbours build near one another, in any place divided from the reſt of the Town, they will have a <hi>Fetiche</hi> to themſelves, and will ſacrifice and pray to him for their preſervation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thurſday</hi> the fourteenth of <hi>April</hi> being at <hi>Frederisbourg,</hi> whilſt they were at Prayers above, I went down, and at the entrance of a houſe which ſtood alone by it ſelf, I obſerved a man and a woman, bleeding of a Hen (which they had prick'd on purpoſe) upon cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain leaves which they had plac'd upon the ground, and after it had done bleeding, they cut it into mamocks, threw them down upon the leaves, and then turning their faces upon one another, and kiſſing their hands, they cry'd, <hi>Me Cuſa,
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:53662:93"/> Me Cuſa, Me Cuſa,</hi> which is as much as to ſay, <hi>Make me good.</hi> I let them alone till their ceremony was done, and then ask'd them what they were about, they told me, that the <hi>Fetiche</hi> of that quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter had beaten them, and they by way of attonement, had given him a Hen for his dinner: As I was looking down upon their leaves, (or an herb rather which grows upon the Sea-ſide) they deſired me not to touch them, and told me whoever eat of that Pullet, in half an hours time, would be as dead as a herring; but I was ſo ſtout-hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, I took it up, had it broyl'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the coales, by my Lacquey, eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome part of it in their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and throwing the reſt to the piggs: the poor people were ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, and ſtood gaping to ſee me fall down dead, or ſink over head and ears into the earth immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:53662:93"/> I ask'd them to ſee their <hi>Fetiche,</hi> they carried me into a little Court, to a kind of a Tyle wrapt about with ſtraw, and told me that was the <hi>Fetiche</hi> which had beaten them. Well ſaid I, I'le be reveng'd, and throwing it on the ground, I break it into a hundred pieces, and planted a Croſs in the Room on't. I taught them to ſigne themſelves alſo, broak all their Cruches about the door, and having given them each a little croſs for their pockets, and bid them when ever the <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiche</hi> came to plague them again, that they ſhould ſigne themſelves with the ſigne of the Croſs, take that out and kiſs it, and they ſhould hear no more of their <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiche</hi> ever after; they heard me very patiently, and made ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations at home, that a whole Church of them came to me next day, deſiring to ſwop a <hi>Fetiche</hi> for
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:53662:94"/> a Crucifix: We came immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to a bargain, and when I began to examine my <hi>Fetiche,</hi> I found it nothing but a piece of putrified earth, nointed over with ſuet, and greaſe, and oyl of Palmes, with five or ſix Parrot-feathers bolt upright in the middle, to which morning and night they pay'd their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant devotions.</p>
               <p>I perſwaded them afterwards to ſhew me to their <hi>Fetiche General,</hi> which they did: I found it in a plain where they made all their Sacrifices; it was nothing but a ſtone covered with earth, which I routed immediately, and brake five hundred of their poles which they had planted about it; from thence I went to their Prieſt, to ſee what <hi>Fetiches</hi> he had to ſell, he told me I had one, which was one of the poles I had brought along in my hand, and would have had me
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:53662:94"/> pay'd him for't: I took him by the elbow, and carry'd him to the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster Fetiche,</hi> and when he ſaw he was demoliſh'd, Lord! what a pickle he was in, he roar'd and cry'd out to his Neighbours, and all of them look'd upon it as a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle that I was not as dead as a door-nail in the twinkling of an eye. I told him, Sir, for your pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment I have ſet up this Croſs, and whoſoever touches it (unleſs upon the knee) is a dead man in a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute; at which words, they ran home as faſt as they could, yelling and crying out to one another, whilſt I return'd to the Caſtle.</p>
               <p>They have ſo great an opinion, and veneration for their Prieſts, the whole world is not able to diſabuſe them: if they have one bit better than other, 'tis kept for them; they are the only people amongſt the <hi>Mores,</hi> that are ſuffer'd not to
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:53662:95"/> work, are nouriſh'd at others coſt, and chareſs'd all ways they can think of, to the end they may af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford them their prayers. They ſell <hi>Fetiches</hi> (as I have ſaid before) to the common people, perſwading them, they found them hanging upon the <hi>Fetiches</hi> Tree, which they believe ſo obſtinately, their own eyes are not ſufficient to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince them; for if at any time they ſee the contrary, they will ſooner believe it an illuſion, than imagine their Prieſts would deceive them: ſo blind are theſe poor people, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing led by thoſe who are blinder than themſelves.</p>
               <p>The Habit of their Prieſts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembles a Coat of Arms, and is made of ſome courſe linnen, or ſerge, about which they have a ſcarf, ſet with little bones of broyl'd Pullets, like the Cockle-ſhells worn by the Pilgrims of St. <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael;</hi>
                  <pb n="181" facs="tcp:53662:95"/> the reſt of their bodies is quite naked, they have garters a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout their legs, made of the Fibers of their <hi>Fetiche</hi> Tree: all people, even to the Kings themſelves, are ambitious of their friendſhip, that they may intreat their <hi>Fetiches</hi> to be favourable to them, either in their Trade, or any thing elſe.</p>
               <p>For my part, I believe they are made all of them by the Prieſt, and that they talk and converſe with the Devil, who communicates with them, and teaches them which way to cheat the people ſo eaſily; and that which makes me ſay it, is this, they alwayes mutter out ſome words to their <hi>Fetiches,</hi> before they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="182" facs="tcp:53662:96"/>
               <head>Of their Superstition, their Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon their <hi>Fetiches,</hi> their manner of pacifying them, when they think they are angry, and the Burials of the Dead.</head>
               <p>THeir Superſtition towards their <hi>Fetiches,</hi> is ſo poſitive, and dogmatical, nothing in this world is able to convince them. Their chief end in carrying them about them, is to keep them from any ill might befall them, and when any does, they believe the fault is in themſelves, and that they have not perform'd their duties towards them.</p>
               <p>They dread Swearing by their <hi>Fetiches</hi> above all things, believing it impoſſible to live an hour after, if they ſwear falſe; for which reaſon when the good woman goes to the Market, or abroad at any time, the good
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:53662:96"/> man takes his <hi>Fetiche,</hi> and putting it into a cup of drink made with Palm-wine, he gives it her, and makes her ſwear to be faithful to him in his abſence, and ſwears her again (whether ſhe has or not) when ſhe returns.</p>
               <p>When we were before <hi>Asbini,</hi> there was one called <hi>Attire,</hi> who complain'd that he was robb'd of a Mark of Gold in our Ship: Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>Wantesk</hi> took a cruſt of bread, and bid him ſwear by his <hi>Fetiche,</hi> and then (eating that) wiſh the Devil might carry him away in an hours time, if it were not true; but his Conſcience being too tender, he refus'd it, and made himſelf ſo ridiculous amongſt his Brethren, he never durſt appear in our ſhip afterwards.</p>
               <p>The eight and twentieth of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pril,</hi> being with the <hi>Daniſh</hi> Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral about Supper time, the King of
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:53662:97"/> 
                  <hi>Fetu</hi>'s Son-in-law (called <hi>Janque Senece</hi>) arriv d, the General ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected he had nimm'd away a Ring from him, but his Excellence proteſted the contrary, offering to ſwear, and to ſwallow his <hi>Fetiche</hi> upon the premiſes. I had a great mind (upon the tidings) to be preſent at the Ceremony; I went in, and found a Faggot of Thorns in a Basket which a Slave carried under his arm, covered over with a Skin, I made bold to uncover it, and in the middle of the Fag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got, I ſaw a piece of Suet and Wax, with Parrots Feathers, little burnt bones of Pullets, Plumes of the Bird which was <hi>Fetichiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo</hi> of that Countrey, and ſeveral other naſtie things with them. One of their Prieſts was preſent, who told him he had made it as ſtrong as was poſſible, and that if he lyed, he could not out-live it a
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:53662:97"/> quarter of an hour; for all that, he took a piece of bread, and a glaſs of Wine, and was falling to work, but the General ſtopt him, and would not ſuffer him to drink it. I put my hand to this <hi>Fetiche,</hi> the Prieſt ſaw me, ſtarted, and bid me have a care, <hi>If I took it up, I was a dead man.</hi> I lifted it out of the basket for all that, he ſtept back, and cryed out to me, if you turn, or move it, the fire will fall down from Heaven, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume you: I took it and twirl d it three times on the right hand, and as many on the left: and then threw it daſh againſt the ground, leaping upon it, and breaking it into a thouſand pieces. They ſaid I would dye in the morning, and were very much amazed to find me alive afterwards. But they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collected, and told me, <hi>I was not dead, becauſe I did not believe:</hi> I
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:53662:98"/> anſwered, <hi>They were fools, not to be as great Infidels as I?</hi> They replyed, <hi>It was impoſſible, their</hi> Fetiches <hi>would not ſuffer them:</hi> Quoth I, Who is this <hi>Fetiche?</hi> They told me, <hi>It was a great black Dog,</hi> that appeared very frequently at the foot of a great Tree. I asked them, <hi>If they had ſeen him?</hi> they told me, <hi>No,</hi> but their Prieſts and he were very great, conferr'd notes often, and they gave them a relation of their diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>Beſides the wayes of appeaſing their <hi>Fetiches,</hi> which I have menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned before, they have other whim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeys as memorable: If they have not ſo good fortune a fiſhing, as they uſe to have, they imagine their <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiche</hi> is offended, and has driven them away. If their Trade be but dull, they are of the ſame opinion, believe them to be the cauſe, &amp; fall to their devotions immediately.</p>
               <pb n="187" facs="tcp:53662:98"/>
               <p>If a poor fiſherman goes out, takes little, and returns after all his patience and pains, not much rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than he went, he concludes his <hi>Fetiche</hi> is diſgruntled, repairs pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently to his Prieſt, preſents him with a token of his Love, and with tears in his eyes, begs of him, that he would ſet them to rights again; after which he marches with his Wife and Children (as neat, and as trim, as hands can make them) to the Sea ſide, with great branch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of their <hi>Fetiche</hi> Tree about their necks, which after certain cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies they throw into the Sea, with <hi>Rice, Millet,</hi> and <hi>Mays,</hi> crying out a thouſand times, <hi>Me cuſa, Me cuſa.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If the King obſerves that Gold comes not down ſo plentifully as formerly, or that his traffick and duties decreaſe, to work he goes inſtantly with his <hi>Fetiche,</hi> he
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:53662:99"/> prayes, he ſacrifices, he treats, ſpreading of meat, and drink, about the Mountains and Trees that are conſecrated to him, which the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of <hi>Frederisbourg</hi> told me he had many times ſeen.</p>
               <p>Having ſeiz'd upon two <hi>Mores</hi> on <hi>Holy-Thurſday,</hi> to ſecure ſome debts we had owing us upon the ſhore. On <hi>Friday</hi> morning we ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved one of them to waſh his face more than ordinary, to mutter out ſome words to himſelf, and to take water, and throw it behind him: we ask'd him for what rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon he did ſo, and he told us, it was to implore the <hi>Fetiche</hi> for rain, that Gold might be waſhed down from the Mountains, and the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants inabled by that to ſet them at liberty.</p>
               <p>After they have ſowne their Corne (of the manner of which I ſhall give a relation by and by)
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:53662:99"/> that night they burn all the thorns they can find in the field, and then skipping, and dancing, and ſinging, whatever they have more than or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily precious, they throw it (with Palme-Wine) into the fire, conceiving thereby to render their <hi>Fetiche</hi> more favourable in their Harveſt: By which we may ſee the deplorable blindneſs of thoſe poor Creatures, and be excited to give God thanks, who has illuminated us with the rayes of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>The General of <hi>Frederisbourg,</hi> having notice that there was one of them dead in the Caſtle, gave me advertiſement immediately that I might be preſent at the Funeral Ceremonies, a thing which the <hi>Mores</hi> will never permit, but by conſtraint.</p>
               <p>When any one dyes amongſt them, they put the body into a Coffin made of Oſiers, the barke
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:53662:100"/> of Trees, or of Ruſhes, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is no more than a panier, the women, the relations, friends and neighbours that are there, run up and down the houſe, crying, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting, and interrogating the dead perſon why he would leave them.</p>
               <p>If it be a woman that dyes, her daughter or ſome other woman, (for the men are never called to their funerals) goes from houſe to houſe complaining and making her moan, and with the gold ſhe finds about her, or in the houſe, buys an Ox or a Sheep, which ſhe gives to the Prieſt, to pray to the <hi>Fetiche</hi> of the dead perſon, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct her into a place of repoſe: the Prieſt orders this Ox, or Mutton, to be killed, and then ſprinkling the blood about in honour to her <hi>Fetiche,</hi> he begs of it, that it would not interrupt her in her paſſage to
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:53662:100"/> the other world, and that it would pardon whatever ſhe had done amiſs. Thoſe who are preſent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing put by him into a ring, in a corner of the Chamber, he places himſelf in the midſt, and dreſt ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſprucely with <hi>Raſade,</hi> Corail, or plates of Gold, ſets a great quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of Peaſe, Beans, Rice, Mays, and Oyle of Palmes about them, and then ſprinkles them with the blood of a Pullet, which is killed, and afterwards makes a kind of a necklace of certain hearbs, which he hangs about his neck, whilſt the good women cut the Pullet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to morſells, and preſent them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Fetiche.</hi> After this the Prieſt having muttered out ſome prayers to himſelf, he takes water, or Palme-Wine in his mouth, and ſpirts it upon the moſt antient of the <hi>Fetiches,</hi> from which he takes a proportion of ſuet and greaſe, and
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:53662:101"/> mingling it with the leaves of his coller, and other things, he ſtamps and bruiſes them altogether with his feet, till they be brought to a conſiſtence, then making them up into a great maſs, he ſeparates again into ſeveral little pieces, which being wrapt up in the rind of a conſecrated tree, he diſtributes to the whole company, reſerving a part to be buried with the corps, to make her journey more proſperous into the other world, and theſe <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiches</hi> are lookt upon as the moſt propitious of all.</p>
               <p>This Ceremony being over, the body is expos'd about half a day, with the head bound about, and the arms extended, after which the women carry it to the place of its Sepulture (it being their Province to bury the dead) the men never ſtirring in that caſe, unleſs the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial be to be in ſome other Village,
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:53662:101"/> which is frequent by reaſon of a cuſtome they have of burying eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry body in the Town they were born, and then they attend the Corps with their weapons in their hands; but this perſon I ſaw being buried hard by, I had the opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of being a Spectator of the whole Ceremony.</p>
               <p>The Corps being brought to the place of its Burial, the men which inhabited there, digged a hole of about four or five foot deep, and put it in, but ſo, as the Earth came not near it, then turning about the Grave, they bid him adieu, with great noiſe and ejulation; that Wife which he had moſt kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for, threw his <hi>Fetiches</hi> into the hole, and at laſt laid a good part of his houſhold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuff (as his Kettles and Cloaths) by his ſide, and his Arms a top on him: if he loved any thing more
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:53662:102"/> than ordinary, as Palm-wine, or any thing elſe, they plac'd it by him, with Rice, Millet, Mays, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they thought neceſſary for the life of man, that he might want nothing whither he was a going. Over his Grave they ſet up a little Shedd, to keep it from the weather, which continues there till it be rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, without being touch'd by any one. He which makes the Grave, and buries the dead body, has the liberty to take his choice of ſuch things which they put into the Grave with the Corps, and it is lookt upon as a due, if he be not paid otherwiſe for his pains.</p>
               <p>If a woman dies in Travail, and the Child dies alſo, they are buried together, and the Infant in the arms of the Mother.</p>
               <p>Theſe Ceremonies being finiſhed, they return weeping and lament<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their houſes, where both
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:53662:102"/> men and women do waſh them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves forthwith, after which they eat the Beef or the Mutton which was bought, paſſing the reſt of the day in feaſting, and jollity, only eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry year they carry meat and drink, and ſet it at his grave, leſt he ſhould be hungry or thirſty in the other world.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Of their old Men, their Slaves, their Lame, their Servants, the Diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes they are uſually ſubject to, with their Cures, and the way to prevent them.</head>
               <p>THough there is but little love loſt amongſt them, and the men, and the women (unleſs it be their firſt wives) quit one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as they pleaſe, yet they are troubled and concern'd when it happens. So great an averſion have theſe people againſt idleneſs, that amongſt them the aged men and women are not allow'd it, but are
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:53662:103"/> conſtrained to get their livelihood by ſuch employments as their age and infirmities will bear, ſome of them being ſet on work either to blow the bellows in ſome forge, to ſuperviſe the buſineſs of the houſe, or ſome ſuch trifling affair, which requires not much pains: the lame, and ſuch as by any other means are rendred incapable of working, are forced to the wars, or if unable for that, they are ſent to ſell and barter for their Commodities at the Market, or elſe aſſiſt at the making of their oyl of Palm, make Mattreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, or what elſe their ſtrength will admit.</p>
               <p>They have not many Slaves up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Coaſt, it not being permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to any but Nobles, to Trade in that nature by which means they are not allowed to entertain any but for their neceſſary ſervice in their families or fields.</p>
               <pb n="197" facs="tcp:53662:103"/>
               <p>Theſe Slaves are commonly ſuch poor miſerable Creatures, as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving not wherewithall to maintain or keep themſelves alive, are glad to ſell themſelves to the rich Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants of that Countrey (that are all Noble-men) who to know them from others, do give them alwayes a particular mark of their own, if they endeavour to eſcape, for the firſt time they cut off one ear, and for the ſecond the other, if they attempt it a third time, and be taken, they either ſell them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, or cut off their heads, as they pleaſe. The children of theſe poor people are Slaves as well as the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and obliged to do whatever they are commanded, as watring their fiſh, ſpinning <hi>Raſade,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The King has ſeveral ſorts of Slaves, ſome like theſe I have mentioned; others which are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited to him for want of paying
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:53662:104"/> their Fines, or other penalties im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed for ſome fault they have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted: and both of them ſent com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly to be ſold at the place ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part for the Trucking of Slaves.</p>
               <p>The Kings Slaves are diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able from other men, only by this that they have no hats, but go al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes naked with their heads. The Inhabitants will not be called <hi>Mores</hi> (which is an appellation they ſay belongs more properly to their Slaves) but <hi>Pretos,</hi> which is as much as <hi>Negroes.</hi> They generally uſe their Slaves very well, ſeldome or never giving them any corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
               <p>Though they have not ſo many diſeaſes amongſt them, as we, yet they are not without their ſhare, &amp; thoſe as troubleſome as ours: the moſt frequent are the <hi>Neapolitan</hi> diſeaſe, pains in the head, burning Feavers, (which for the moſt part
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:53662:104"/> are occaſion'd by their women) the Chollick, and worms which grow betwixt the fleſh and the skin, to which ſtrangers alſo being ſubject, I ſhall ſpeak a word or two anon.</p>
               <p>For the <hi>Neapolitan</hi> diſeaſe (which is not infamous amongſt them) they uſe only <hi>Salſeparilla,</hi> which they boyl in a Skillet to ſuch a height, and then ſtraining it, they uſe it as a diet-drink, and (as they ſay them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves) with very great ſucceſs.</p>
               <p>Their pains in their head they cure by fomentations made of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain herbs which they lay upon the Patients face, and it takes the pain away immediately. Sometimes they raiſe little bliſters upon it, which then applying to them a certain kind of Earth, they have amongſt them, it aſſwages and cures them alſo.</p>
               <p>The Chollick, and Wind in the Stomach, is not over frequent
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:53662:105"/> amongſt the Natives, but all Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers are much ſubject to them, till they be accuſtomed to the air of that Countrey.</p>
               <p>To prevent and fortifie ones ſelf againſt them, it is good to bind a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Stomach very hard, to keep ones ſelf warm in the night with a Waſte-coat, or ſome other thing, and if notwithſtanding all this, it be not prevented, it is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs to take 4 or 5 drops of balm of Sulphur in a little Strong-water, cover ones ſelf well, and ſweat, the next day let blood, then purge two dayes after, and 'tis odds but he will be well. 'Tis very dangerous ſleep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the ground, in three days many times they are dead of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curable cold.</p>
               <p>Sometimes they bath them with Mallows, Marſh Mallows, Pel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litory of the Wall, Powder of Caſſia, each half an ounce, then
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:53662:105"/> they boyl it upon the fire to a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain degree, and put ten or twelve drops of Oyl of Anniſeeds amongſt it, which makes it ſovereign; but the beſt way of all is to keep the Stomack warm, and have a great care of ſleeping upon the ground.</p>
               <p>As to the worms which grow betwixt the skin and the fleſh, Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigners are as much ſubject to them, as they: they breed over all the body, but principally in the thighs, legs, and moſt fleſhy parts. Sometimes they have them two years together, and never perceive it till about a fortnight before they come out. By the report of thoſe who have had them, there is no torment like them, &amp; it exceeds the moſt violent pain in the teeth.</p>
               <p>There has been great inquiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into the cauſe of it, ſome attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute it to their Palm-wine, others to the Fiſh which is eaten upon
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:53662:106"/> that Coaſt, others to their Water, every one arguing according to his fancy, but all of them wide of the Mark; for thoſe <hi>Mores</hi> who live but forty leagues up higher into the Countrey, know nothing of it at all, nor are in any danger of the Evening dew.</p>
               <p>The moſt probable cauſe is the dew which falls in the Evening upon the Coaſt, occaſioned by the Breezes from the Sea, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very cold, the <hi>Mores</hi> do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly make fires at their feet when they go to ſleep, and indeed nothing is of more importance to ones health, than to keep off the chilneſs of that Air, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve ones ſelf as warm as one can. The ill water they drink, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the naſtineſs of their diet, may add ſomething, but 'tis the nipping Winds and Rains which fall upon the Coaſt, and
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:53662:106"/> makes thoſe parts ſo ſubject to worms: in <hi>June, July,</hi> and <hi>Auguſt,</hi> (which are the moſt rainy months amongſt them) experience tells us, thoſe worms are moſt apt to engen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. In ſhort, every drop of their Rain is bigger than a large Pea: if in a ſhower of that nature, one be wet never ſo little, and lets his clothes dry upon his back, beſides that in three dayes his clothes ſhall be rotten, if he has no worms, he ſhall be ſure of a diſtemper that will be very dangerous.</p>
               <p>We may affirm therefore 'tis the rain, as well as the dew, which produces theſe worms, how, or which way, I leave to the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher, and Phyſician to reſolve; but this I am ſure, having many times put out a bit of fleſh in the rain, or in the evening dew, I found as ſoon as the beams of the Sun glanced but upon it, it turned
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:53662:107"/> all into Worms, which experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment I made very often, &amp; am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced by it, that they come but thoſe two ways, either by the rain or the dew. Of thoſe Worms which grow in the body, there are two ſorts, one leſſer, the other greater, and ſome of them as ſlender as a hair; the leaſt are half a foot long, the larger a foot, and ſome there are of an ell, but very rarely.</p>
               <p>When you are once plagued with them, there is nothing to be done till they are out, which is evident by the tumours they raiſe in the fleſh, and the ſwelling of the part where they lie. There is nothing like keeping ones bed, and opening the corner of the skin gently with a knife to give them free paſſage, if they perceive them advancing, they may haſten their journey, and pull them out by little and little, if they find any
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:53662:107"/> ſtop or reluctance in the Worm, they muſt let them alone (leſt they break them) and tye a hair or piece of ſilk about them, to keep them from going back: ſometimes ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of them will come out at one hole, but they muſt have patience, for their motion is but ſlow: above all things they muſt have a care of breaking them, for they are of ſo venemous a quality, there is no way to preſerve the perſon againſt its virulence, but by cutting off the part. When they are out, they uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally rub the place with butter and ſalt, and waſh it with Sea-water, which in that caſe is ſoveraign.</p>
               <p>Their beſt way to ſecure them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againſt them, is to put file-duſt into their breeches and ſhooes to keep their feet dry, and if at any time they be wet, to change their clothes and their drawers immediately, by no means to ſleep
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:53662:108"/> upon the ground, to have a care of the <hi>Seraine</hi> or evenings dew, to bind themſelves up cloſe, and keep their ſtomachs warm, to abſtein from Women, to uſe confection of <hi>Hyacinth, Alkermes,</hi> or <hi>Clarie,</hi> to keep ones ſelf clean, avoid the raine, which the <hi>Mores</hi> are as feard of as the Plague, ſhutting up themſelves as ſoon as it begins but to mizzle; if one be wett, to dry his cloths, and by theſe obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons they may be probably prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. I ſaw a perſon of quality who had been there 17 years, who told me he had never been troubled with them but the firſt year, and that was for want of theſe cautions. But to continue theſe ſtories of death and diſeaſes, is but to make the Reader <hi>chagrin</hi> and melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; it is time now I ſhould to ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of more pleaſure and diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="207" facs="tcp:53662:108"/>
               <head>Of their Dances, and Feaſts, both private and ſolemn.</head>
               <p>THe Inhabitants of the Coaſts of <hi>Africk,</hi> are great lovers of Muſick, and ſongs, but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of dancing, in which they ſpend two or three hours every evening before they go to bed: to this purpoſe the men and women both, dreſs themſelves as fine as they can, putting on their bracelets of Gold and Ivory, and trimming up their hair; the men carry little fanns in their hands, made of the tayls of Elephants, or Horſes, (like the boaſom of feathers wherewith pictures are duſted, ſaving that theſe are gilt at both ends) and meet all at a place about Sun-ſet; Being come together, thoſe who make the Muſick, draw into a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner by themſelves, their Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:53662:109"/> are a kind of Drum, or Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor, made of the trunck of a Tree, hollowed: A Cane with ſeveral holes in it, like a flute, a <hi>Tambour de Baſque,</hi> and an inſtrument ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing near our Guitars, with ſix ſtrings; all which playing toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, make no contemptible har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie. As ſoon as they ſtrike up, the men and women divide imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately, and putting themſelves (two and two) directly againſt one another, they begin their dance, marching up to one another, and then recoyling in good meaſure, clacking their fingers, as they paſs nodding their heads, whiſpering certain words into one anothers ears, toſſing about their fanns, with a thouſand poſtures and geſticula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and in this manner ſpending the evenings till they go to bed: this dance is not much unlike one of our <hi>Filoux</hi> in <hi>France;</hi> ſome of
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:53662:109"/> their women and maids will take a hoop and throw it upon the ground, then skip, and dance about it, and at laſt take it up with their toes. In ſhort, dancing is in ſo great requeſt amongſt them, they have Schools on purpoſe to teach them.</p>
               <p>Beſides Sundays, they have par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Feſtivals, and particular dances belonging to them; for the dayes which are obſerved by their Kings, I ſhall ſpeak of in a Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by themſelves.</p>
               <p>On the 26 of <hi>April</hi> being at <hi>Frederisbourg,</hi> I ſaw one of theſe Feaſts, which are commonly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted in memory of ſome advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage befaln the State: This that I was at, was celebrated by the King of <hi>Fetu</hi>'s Son-in-Law, who had gain'd a great battel againſt the King of <hi>Acanis,</hi> and the Lord of <hi>Abrambou,</hi> on the ſame day the
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:53662:110"/> year before, in which ingagement as the General of <hi>Frederisbourg</hi> told me, there were ſlain on both ſides above 5000 men. The Feſtival be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan at <hi>Cape-Corſe,</hi> where the Son-in-Law lived, who made a great Feaſt, diſtributed largely to all that were there, who troubled them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves that day with nought but their ſports, and at night came to finiſh their ceremony at the Caſtle of <hi>Frederisbourg;</hi> we were juſt ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting down to the Table, when on a ſudden we heard a great noiſe of ſhowts and acclamations, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately their Drums and their Trumpets ſtrike up. Their Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets are of Elephants teeth made hollow: we perceived preſently it was the Kings Son-in-Law, with his Drum before him, 15 or 20 Trumpets, about 12 of his Wives, and about 60 Slaves after him, two of which attended him with great
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:53662:110"/> Bucklers, carried on purpoſe to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver him, and two others with his, Darts, his Bow, and his Arrows. The Women were dreſt in Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mask and Taffaties, which they wrapt about them from their breaſts to their mid-legg, wearing ſeveral <hi>Fetiches</hi> upon their heads, ſeveral little plates of gold in bracelets, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout their wriſts and ankles, or elſe of <hi>Raſade</hi> or Ivory, their hair very well dreſt, according to the mode of that Countrey: the Kings Son in-Law had a piece of blew Taffaty about his waſt, whoſe two ends were drawn betwixt his leggs, and trail'd almoſt upon the ground. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him he had a little faulchion carried, he had a Cap trim'd with pieces of the skulls of ſuch perſons as he had killed, and covered all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver with plumes of feathers: on his arms and his leggs, he had ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral little pieces of gold excellently
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:53662:111"/> well wrought, and two little fanns in his hands made of horſe-hair; When they were received into the Court, after a hundred ſhouts and acclamations, the men put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves on one ſide, the women on the other, and the Slaves, Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, and Drums behind him, who ſounded as they paſs'd, and made all the noiſe and clamour was poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible; having ſeparated themſelves, they began their approaching, and retiring with great exactneſs, tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning themſelves this way and that way about half a quarter of an hour: after this he gave his 2 fanns to one of his Slaves, and taking his Dart in his hand, he pretended to dart it at the women, who were do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame thing on their ſide; but the Slaves got about him, and cover'd him quite with their buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers: this having laſted a pritty while, on a ſudden he claps his
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:53662:111"/> hand upon his ſword, and run a tilt at the women, who did the ſame to him with ſticks they had in their hands for that purpoſe, and then mingling themſelves pell-mell with the Slaves (who had ſwords alſo in their hands, and made as if they ſtruck them as hard as they could) they gave a great yell, divided again, and ſo made an end of their Ceremony.</p>
               <p>The General treated them very kindly with Strong waters and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things, and whiſper'd to me, that their manner of fighting was at that rate; in ſhort, this Son-in-Law of his Majeſty was not quit of this ſopperie at leſs charge than 500 Marks of Gold, from thence he went to the Governour of the <hi>Mores</hi> in <hi>Frederisbourg,</hi> to paſs that night with him, and as we heard, he ſtay'd very graciouſly with him till the next day at noon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="214" facs="tcp:53662:112"/>
               <head>Of their Exerciſes, their Workmen, their Trades, their Merchandiſes, their Fiſhing, which way it is uſed and the Duty they pay to their King.</head>
               <p>AS they have ſeveral Trades and imployments amongſt them, ſo are they very conſtantly imploy'd, eſpecially if there be no Ships upon their Coaſts to divert them. They have Goldſmiths which work very curiouſly, they have Carpenters that make their <hi>Canoes,</hi> they have people that Fiſh, they have others that cut down their wood, the women in the mean time keeping their Markets, and ſelling their Commodities to Merchants which come higher out of the Countrey.</p>
               <p>Thoſe who come aboard to ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiate with us are commonly Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, or Captains of ſome Town,
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:53662:112"/> who are all of them Merchants: their manner of coming aboard us, is in a little <hi>Canoe,</hi> very neatly made, rowed by two <hi>Mores,</hi> the Merchant in the middle upon a little chair, with his ſword lying by him.</p>
               <p>Being of ſeveral places, they have a different way of Trading, thoſe who live farther up the Countrey, and are neither acquainted with the language, nor manner of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, which is practis'd by the Whites, are conſtrain'd to make uſe of a ſort of Brokers to negotiate for them, and do uſually give them good recompence for their pains; this is an advantage accrews parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly to ſuch as live near the Sea-ſide, and (ſo generally are they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted to their profit) the greateſt Merchants amongſt them will not refuſe the imployment, if there be the leaſt proſpect and expectation of gain.</p>
               <pb n="216" facs="tcp:53662:113"/>
               <p>Moſt commonly, it is thoſe who live upon the Coaſts, or within 10 leagues diſtance of the Sea, that buy up the Commodities which are brought in by ſuch Ships as come into their Roads, and ſell them af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards when the Ships are gone, to the Inlanders, ſeldome for leſs profit than ſix <hi>per Cent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Having been deceived ſometimes formerly, they are now grown ſo ſubtil and wary, there is no cheat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them any more; it is our buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs now rather to be upon our guards, leſt they be too cunning for us. They have ſo great judgment &amp; inſight into Merchandiſe, they will diſtinguiſh whether a piece of Saye be dyed at <hi>Leyden</hi> or <hi>Harlem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When their bargains are made, and their buſineſs done, they fall a begging and bawling for ſome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent or other (which they call <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che</hi>) and will never be ſatisfyed
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:53662:113"/> without it. The <hi>Hollanders</hi> brought up this Cuſtom at firſt, to cajole, and work them off from the <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gais:</hi> But what they did volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily then, is become now ſuch a Cuſtome, that ſome of the <hi>Mores</hi> are ſo confident, as to demand what preſent they ſhall have, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they will admit any propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Traffick.</p>
               <p>They have one pretty odd kind of ſuperſtition amongſt them, if a Merchant ſneezes as he comes out of his houſe, and turns his head by accident, towards the right hand, (which they call <hi>Eninfan</hi>) they believe they ſhall run a great hazard of loſing their goods that day. If he turns it to the left (which they call <hi>Abnicon</hi>) though they were ſure to gain the profits of a Kingdom, they would not ſtir out that day from their houſes.</p>
               <p>When they return from our Ship
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:53662:114"/> they have alwayes ſtore of boys, &amp; young fellows attending upon the ſhore, to carry the Commodities they have bought to their houſes, for which the Merchant gives them ſome little pieces of gold as a reward. Thoſe who live higher up the Countrey have all their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities brought down upon the backs of their Slaves, making no uſe of horſe, or any other Creature in that buſineſs, which is no ſmall inconvenience to a Merchant that comes a hundred leagues to us croſs the Countrey, and forces them to travel with their Arms.</p>
               <p>Fiſhing being their principal im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, every morning there are twenty or thirty <hi>Canoes</hi> to be ſeen ſailing out of their harbours, &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding themſelves inſtantly into all quarters when they come out to Sea. In each of them they have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly two men, one to fiſh, &amp; the
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:53662:114"/> other to manage the <hi>Canoe,</hi> and by them they have their ſwords and their Victuals. Their <hi>Canoes</hi> are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry neat and beautiful, painted and adorned with all poſſible care; they faſten <hi>Fetiches</hi> to them, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them from ſtorms &amp; diſaſters, and when they have done fiſhing, they draw them up under a place on purpoſe to keep them dry. They are ſo light, two men will carry one of them as they pleaſe.</p>
               <p>In this manner they go a fiſhing every morning, yet not ſo much by deſign, as by natural impulſe, the wind from the hills forcing them as it were to Sea, and altering at night, and blowing hard upon the ſhore, they are brought home again by the ſame neceſſity and violence: and this they do conſtantly every day but <hi>Sunday,</hi> never failing when the weather will endure it.</p>
               <p>The moſt general way of fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:53662:115"/> is with little hooks, of which they faſten twenty (ſometimes) to one line; others make uſe of lines with a kind of ſlipping nooſes, but this is as rarely at Sea, as it is ordinary in their Rivers, and Lakes within Land. They are much delighted with fiſhing in the night, which they do by the light of Torches greas'd over with Oyl of Palm, or Roſen, hooking the fiſh up as they come near them. Others go up to the bellies into the Sea, with a lighted Torch in one hand, and a Net in the other, which they throw over them with great dexterity: and from hence we may collect how induſtrious they are, neglecting no time, nor labour to get themſelves a lively<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood. At their return, they are attended by ſeveral boyes, who are alwaies waiting in the harbour to help them home with their fiſh,
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:53662:115"/> and to make up their Lines and their Nets for them, for which pains, they uſually gratifie them with ſome little preſent of fiſh.</p>
               <p>But the Fiſherman and Merchant are no ſooner return'd, but the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver of the Office (in which the Duties and Cuſtoms are paid; for the King in whoſe Dominion that Port is) ſtands ready alwaies to receive them, and to carry with him a full third of whatever they bring on ſhore) to bring the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant to a higher compoſition, for there being no fix'd prices ſet, it is the Merchants buſineſs to get off as cheap, and the Receivers to hoiſt him as high as he can: beſides theſe duties, the foreign Merchants which are not of that Kingdom, are oblig d ſometimes to give a Mark of gold more for a free paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage through the territories of the neighbouring Princes.</p>
               <pb n="222" facs="tcp:53662:116"/>
               <p>But thoſe who live upon the Sea-ſide, are exempted from any tribute in this nature, provided the worth of their Merchandiſe exceeds not two ounces of gold at one time, if it does, they pay as other people.</p>
               <p>The duty upon their fiſh is paid punctually to the Receiver every day, who as punctually ſends it every day to the King; not one Fiſherman daring under a great penalty, to ſell one morſell till it be paid, this tribute being deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the ſuſtenance of his Royal Family; for which reaſon, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever fiſh is taken, is brought im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately to the Office, where the Receiver has a great meaſure about the bigneſs of a Peck, which he fills and delivers frankly to the Fiſherman; that done, he mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures the reſt, and reſerves a fifth part for the King, which is ſent away preſently by the Slaves for
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:53662:116"/> the uſe of the houſe. Theſe Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers are for the moſt part, the Sons, Brothers, or near Relations of their Kings.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Of the Kings of thoſe Countreys, their Courts, Authority, and manner of living with their Courtiers, of their Wives and Children, of the Succeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their Kingdoms, their Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues, Feasts, Deaths, Burials, and Elections of another King.</head>
               <p>THe Kings being the chief heads of ſo many people, I ought in juſtice to have given them the precedence, and have ſpoken of them in the firſt Chapter; but ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving never ſeen them my ſelf, and what I write is but from the report of ſuch as have lived there ſix or ſeven year, I have thought it beſt to put this, and the three ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent Chapters by themſelves, having been an eye-witneſs of
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:53662:117"/> what I have writ before, &amp; what I ſhall write hereafter of the Fruits &amp; Productions of that Countrey: But theſe Chapters I took out of the Memoires of the General, &amp; Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of <hi>Frederisbourg,</hi> who are in the Kingdome of <hi>Fetu:</hi> &amp; as their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and cuſtoms all along thoſe Coaſts are every where the ſame, ſpeaking of one, I ſhall give ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent proſpect, and information of them all.</p>
               <p>The King of <hi>Fetu</hi> as they repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented him to me, is no unhandſome man, he is a great lover of the Whites, &amp; has expreſt it upon ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral occaſions; he is about five &amp; forty, or fifty years old, Majeſtick, requires honour and reſpect, rich, and very liberal, he has come many times to viſit the Governour of <hi>Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derisbourg,</hi> &amp; made him ſeveral pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents: Liberality is very ordinary in theſe parts, and uſed, to inveigle the
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:53662:117"/> people, and oblige them to parties: He keeps a great Court, paſſing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the time in drinking &amp; laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a great Hall in the middle of his Palace; about Sun-ſet he ſets himſelf down at the Gate, dreſt ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſine, with his bracelets and neck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laces of Gold, &amp; clad in the richeſt habits can be bought for money; in this manner, if he be at peace, he paſſes away his time with his La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, whoſe principal buſineſs is to waſh and keep him neat againſt night, at which time he has dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing conſtantly and balls.</p>
               <p>His ſubjects have all of them a great veneration for him, &amp; are in much aw and apprehenſion of his diſpleaſure, by reaſon that whoever amongſt them has but once diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obey'd their King, he is <hi>ipſo facto</hi> by the Laws of that Kingdome; made incapable of any publick of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice. His authority is ſo abſolute,
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:53662:118"/> he does what he pleaſes, and no body dares to controul him.</p>
               <p>He has alwayes a great number of Slaves and Souldiers guarding his Palace, which is very large, and neat, and incomparably much handſomer than a houſe he has near the Sea-ſide: it conſiſts of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove two hundred chambers, and is built in the midſt of a Town, with large Courts round about it; when he goes abroad, he is always attended and carried upon the ſhoulders of his Slaves, all people endeavouring to pleaſe him where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he comes.</p>
               <p>To gain the affections of his Courtiers, and the Grandees of his Countrey, above all things it is neceſſary he be Noble, for they hate avarice, and look upon it as ignominious in a great perſon, on whom all people do depend, to be too parſimoniouſly intent upon
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:53662:118"/> hoording up Gold; Yet this libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity that is look'd for, conſiſts only in treatings &amp; banquets, which he makes very often for them, &amp; if the Whites at any time make him a preſent, he diſtributes it amongſt them, if it be of Strong-waters, he drinks it merrily amongſt them, preferring their company, in that caſe, to his Wives and Children, to whom notwithſtanding he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows a proportion.</p>
               <p>He has as many Wives as he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, who are all diſpoſed into ſeveral appartements, with whom he dines or ſups ſometimes as he thinks good, but very ſeldom, when they go abroad, they are carried likewiſe on the ſhoulders of their Slaves: they are abundantly proud, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy their whole time in diverting and indulging the King; ſome of them are admitted into his compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny after dinner in the great Hall,
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:53662:119"/> and are very happy if they may but waſh and dreſs him in the morning, they having ſervants enough to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch what elſe is to be done in the houſe: when they have ſpruc'd him up, they fall to work upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, combing, and curling their hair in ſeveral poſtures: their cloaths are very rich alwaies, and loaden ſometimes with ſuch abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Gold, it is a wonder which way they can bear them.</p>
               <p>Whilſt their Father lives, their Children are brought up at the charge of the publick when they go abroad out of the Palace, they are carried by their Slaves likewiſe, and have alwayes their Trumpets, and one Drum: by which formali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties they are diſtinguiſhed from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther people, and as they paſs, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e great honour and reſpect.</p>
               <p>The ſucceſſion of the Kingdom goes not to the Children, is it does
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:53662:119"/> in <hi>Europe,</hi> but devolves upon him that is next of Kin to his Majeſty, that the Crown may be ſure never to go out of the Royal Family: for this reaſon the Kings Children make hay whilſt the Sun ſhines, &amp; lay up what they can whilſt their Father is alive: they work and take pains too as well as the reſt, having no other advantage but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emption from tribute, living al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes with their Father: whilſt he lives himſelf, they have opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of getting &amp; laying up againſt an evil day. If they marry, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gives them only the quality of Nobles, not but he would wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly do more, but dares not: the greateſt priviledge they have, is to keep Slaves, but the King diſpoſes of all as he pleaſes. The principal Offices of the Kingdome are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd for them, as well as the chief Commands in the Armies in
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:53662:120"/> times of war: In time of peace they are ſent frequently as hoſtages to other Princes, to ſecure their Leagues, and to inform themſelves of their manner of Government: If they be brave men, and generous, they are reſpected when their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is march'd off, but if covetous and baſe, on the contrary they are abandon'd by their Relations, and contemptible to every body elſe; they will oftentimes complain that their Father durſt not do any thing indirectly to inrich them, that they are poor, and indigent, and yet have vaſt treaſures conceal'd.</p>
               <p>The Revenue of the King con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in Fruit, Fiſh, Wine, Oyl of Palm, Millet, Rice, Mays, Fleſh, and whatever elſe is neceſſary to the life of man; all which are brought in daily to his Palace, that he may have no cares upon him, nor no room left for any thing but diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
               <pb n="231" facs="tcp:53662:120"/>
               <p>The Revenue of the Eſtate ariſes from the Cuſtoms and Fines which are adjudg'd to him in Civil and Criminal caſes, which the Receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers deliver every 3 months to his Treaſurer, who makes the whole disburſement, both for matters of State, for the expence of his Court, for the payment of the Souldiers in time of war, for his privy purſe, buys all the Cloths for the King, his Wives, and his Children, upon which ſcore, he never ſtirs from him, accompanies him where ever he goes, and has an appartment in his Palace; this Office of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer, is the beſt Office in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and the Treaſurer is in more repute amongſt all people, then any child of the Kings.</p>
               <p>Beſides <hi>Sundays</hi> (which the King paſſes ordinarily after his devotions are ended amongſt his Wives and his Children) he obſerves ſeveral
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:53662:121"/> Feſtival days, in which he buys up all the Palm-wine, and Fowl, the Peaſants bring that day, and regales the Treaſurer, his Courtiers, &amp; No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of the Countrey, in the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his Wives and his Children.</p>
               <p>The firſt and chief Feaſt which he obſerves, is on the day of his Coronation annually, which they call the Feaſt of <hi>Fetiches:</hi> on that day he invites not only all his No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, but his neighbouring Princes, and whatever Whites are upon his Coaſts, who ſend him preſents at that time, and are preſent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves if they have any deſigns upon his friendſhip: if they come upon the invitation, he receives them ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well, feaſting them for three dayes together, and entertaining with Balls and Dances, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever may contribute to their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creations; to which they do wholly devote themſelves; after
<pb n="233" facs="tcp:53662:121"/> they have paſt their devotions, (which are finiſhed to their <hi>Feti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches</hi> uſually in a morning) and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they have left them meat and drink at the foot of ſome Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain or Tree, to refreſh themſelves if they happen to be hungry.</p>
               <p>The other Feaſts which they obſerve, are ordinarily in memory of ſome eminent accident for the honour, or advantage of the State, as upon ſome memorable victory, or ſo, in which caſes the <hi>Europeans</hi> are commonly invited, and muſt come too, if they mean to keep up a good correſpondence with them. Theſe Feſtivals conſiſt in Collati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Banquets, Dances, and Songs, by all which the liberality of that Prince is very conſpicuous, but eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially by his Feaſts. When their King dies, they expreſs their ſorrow by their complaints, their dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Songs, and horrible outcries;
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:53662:122"/> after the aforementioned Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies are over, he is expoſed for ſome days, and in the mean time, his meat and drink ſerved up to him, as duely as he were alive.</p>
               <p>When his body begins to ſmell, 2 or 4 of his Slaves take him, and carry him into the Woods, where they bury him as they pleaſe, no perſon yet having ever known where their King was buried: if any of their Wives follow him, the Slaves kill them, and bury them together, throwing in their <hi>Feti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches</hi> after them, and then his Arms, Sword, Darts, Bows and Arrows, Cloths, Houſholdſtuff, &amp; whatever he delighted in when he was alive: by his ſide they place good ſtore of Palm-Wine, Rice, and ſuch other neceſſary ſuſtenance, and when they have done, they preſent themſelves very demurely before the Palace to be killed, believing they ſhall be
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:53662:122"/> cockſure of the beſt places about their King in the other world.</p>
               <p>Whilſt the Slaves are imploy'd in the interrement of the King, the Inhabitants of the Town, run up &amp; down like mad, cutting the throats of man, woman, child, and ſlaves, to make his equipage as they call it, and attend his Majeſty into the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther world, inſomuch, that if he be a great Prince, they kill 4 or 5 hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred perſons ſometimes at the day of his funeral. If he loved any place better than ordinary, they ſet up a Tombe for him there, where his Succeſſor commands all things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be plac'd once every year, left he ſhould want any thing in the world where he is gone.</p>
               <p>When their Funerals are over, the next Kinſman is advanced to the Throne, and then conducted with great acclamation to his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace (which is lock'd up &amp; a Guard
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:53662:123"/> ſet upon it from the death of the former) their next buſineſs is to give him poſſeſſion of all the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure his Predeceſſor had ſcrap'd up, whoſe children cannot pretend to any part of it, or of any thing elſe, unleſs it be ſomething their Father was poſſeſs'd of before his advancement to the Crown. But this is true, the new King gives ſomething conſiderable alwayes to the Children, and takes care of his Wives, who are matches for the beſt Noble-men in the Countrey. Yet their condition ſometimes is ſo miſerable, that if they have not been good husbands, and lay'd up ſomething for themſelves, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſo abject and contemptible, they are forc'd to make themſelves Slaves for ſubſiſtence, and to live in perpetual infamy, to avoid dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with hunger.</p>
               <p>This done, the new King makes a
<pb n="237" facs="tcp:53662:123"/> Banquet for all comers, and a Feaſt, which continues 4 or 5 days, during which time he treats all people, the Whites, the Kings his Neighbours, &amp; his Nobles, who all of them ſend him their preſents. He takes new <hi>Fetiches</hi> that day, and prays to them afterwards, renewing this Feaſt every year, as I have ſaid before.</p>
               <p>Sometimes he changes his Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, and puts in his relations, and friends, but 'tis but ſeldome, for if they be old that were in before, he lets them dye in their places, not out of any affection to them, but to oblige and captivate the people by ſuch examples of bounty, to whom he gives great largeſſes that day likewiſe, &amp; then calling his Wives and his Children to Court, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to take State upon them, to leave off beating the Hoof, and to be carried in great Pomp upon the ſhoulders of their Slaves.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="238" facs="tcp:53662:124"/>
               <head>Of their Nobles, the manner of their making of War, the grounds upon which they do uſually make it, their Arms: of their Ceſſations and Peace.</head>
               <p>SO much are the <hi>Mores</hi> in love with the title of Nobles, they will not baulk any thing can poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly advance them to it, of which there are ſeveral ſorts amongſt them notwithſtanding: This honour is acquired two ways, either by ſome great and honorable Exploit for the benefit of the State, or elſe by his money: for if a common <hi>More</hi> finds himſelf rich enough; he muſt be ennobled immediately, though it drains him never ſo dry.</p>
               <p>The day he is ennobled, he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites all his friends, and all the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of the Country that are then in the Town. In the preſence of the King and his Lieutenant, his Slaves
<pb n="239" facs="tcp:53662:124"/> take him up upon their backs, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying him a pick-pack round about the City; the good women dancing, and ſinging, and jumping before him all day till Supper comes up and ſtops their recreations. This Feaſt holds three dayes, at the end of which he gives an Oxe to the poor, and a proportion of Palm-wine. He takes new <hi>Feti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches</hi> too that day, and obſerves it annually with his kindred and friends. 'Tis reported alſo, that the Nobility have a certain day in which they all meet and feaſt eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry year amongſt themſelves.</p>
               <p>The Priviledges which they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy above other people, are theſe, they can Trade in every place as they pleaſe, they can ſell and buy ſlaves, they may have their drums and their trumpets, and make them play as they think good; but thoſe who are advanc'd for any noble
<pb n="240" facs="tcp:53662:125"/> atchievment, have this prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, that they have alwayes the principal charges and commands in the Army.</p>
               <p>Theſe Kings being perpetually emulous, and jealous of one another to the higheſt degree, do common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declare warr upon the ſlighteſt occaſion; ſo that upon the leaſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of injury, the King calls his Courtiers together, tells them his diſguſt, requires their aſſiſtance, and they in hopes of booty and plunder conclude upon a warr. An Herald is immediately diſpatch'd to the Enemy, and a time and place appointed for the battel; his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects are advertis'd of the quarrel by his Guards, and a place ſet for the Randezvouz; there is an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal appearance of joy, every one prepares againſt that day, as cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, as it were to be his wedding; they paint and adorn themſelves
<pb n="241" facs="tcp:53662:125"/> with variety of colours, and from that inſtant conceive a mortal and implacable hatred againſt their Enemies: if the injury be great, and the warr likely to be long, they take their Wives and Children with them into the field, burning their houſes, leſt it ſhould be their misfortune to be beaten, and they become a prey to the Foe: if the quarrel be but ſmall, they ſend them to the next Town where there is peace, to attend their ſucceſs.</p>
               <p>They meet preciſely at the day and place, the Captains with Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques upon their heads, ſome of them made of the Skulls of ſuch people as they have kill'd in the preceedent wars, others of the Skins of Lyons or Crocodiles, with plumes of feathers upon them if they have any: on their left arm they carry a large Buckler made of the Skin of a Tygre or Oxe, with a Dart in
<pb facs="tcp:53662:126"/> thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> right hand; they have no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive armes, nor any thing at all upon their bodies, but a peice of linnen before, that they may be the more active and agile when they come to be ingaged; before them they have their ſwords carryed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind and of each ſide, their Slaves with their Bows and Arrows. The common Souldiers are armed with a kind of Battle-axe and Swords, and having of late by their Commerce with the <hi>Eu opeans</hi> ſome of them got Muſquets, they are look'd upon as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rave fellows, &amp; plac'd in the Front.</p>
               <p>Being come near one another, they give a great ſhout, and fall on, they threw their Darts immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately, ſhoot Arrows without num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, covering themſelves with their Bucklers againſt the blows of their Enemies; when they once come to the Sword, they are Devils and not men, the very Women and
<pb n="243" facs="tcp:53662:126"/> Children kill and ſlay, and adding their cries to the noiſe of the Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets and Drums (which are play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inceſſantly) they increaſe the fury in their Parents, and excite them to more inhumanity. The ſlaughter continues till one ſide be defeated, but when they ſee the victory clear, they give quarter then, and fall a taking of Priſoners, which are made Slaves out of hand, and can never be ranſom'd upon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny terms whatſoever.</p>
               <p>When the battle is over, ſome of them (as an expreſſion of their hatred to their Enemies, and devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to their Prince) will eat the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of thoſe they have kill'd, but all of them cut off their under Jaws, and hang them afterwards before their doors as a mark of honour, which is the 11 ſtep as it were of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commending them to the Nobility.</p>
               <p>As their wars are commenced
<pb n="244" facs="tcp:53662:127"/> upon frivolous occaſions, ſo they are like a wiſp of ſtraw, no ſooner kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, but extinguiſhed. Sometimes they laſt longer indeed than others, but ſeldome any conſiderable time. If after a luſty ingagement, they be any better inclin'd, they agree up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a place, where they meet exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, bring their <hi>Fetiches</hi> along with them, upon which they ſwear ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly on both ſides, to do no hurt for the future, to retain no malice, nor to remember their paſt hoſtili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and for their further ſecuritie, hoſtages are delivered, which are commonly the Sons of the Kings, or (if they have none) the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Perſons of the Countrey. The reſt of the day is ſpent by both par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, in mirth, ſinging, dauncing, &amp; making good cheer, after which, Trading revives betwixt them, and they live as lovingly, as if they had never had warrs.</p>
               <pb n="245" facs="tcp:53662:127"/>
               <p>Whilſt we were in that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, there was a very fierce War brake out upon this occaſion: <hi>Abrambou</hi> is a Seigneury which has ſix Towns under it, independant of any of their Kings, and holding of no body but the Emperour of <hi>Achim</hi> or <hi>Acanis Grand.</hi> The Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſor of him that poſſeſs'd it then, who was dead about 4 years before, would needs put a duty up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Merchants of <hi>Acanis</hi> the leſs, and all ſuch as paſt through his Dominions, nor was there any of the Neighbouring Kings durſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtulate the buſineſs, ſo great was his courage and power.</p>
               <p>After his death, the Merchants of <hi>Acanis</hi> demanded reſtitution of ſuch goods as had been taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by violence before, and were in poſſeſſion of the preſent Prince, but they were refuſed, whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe of <hi>Acanis</hi> declared warr
<pb n="346" facs="tcp:53662:128"/> againſt him: the King of <hi>Fetu's</hi> Son being by accident at <hi>Acanis,</hi> inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged generouſly with the Town, and was ſlain in the firſt battail. His Father having no more Sons, and reſenting the loſs of him, the more becauſe he was ſo extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily hopeful, joyned himſelf with the Town of <hi>Acanis,</hi> againſt the Lord of <hi>Abrambou,</hi> and ingaged all his allyes in the quarrel alſo, in ſo-much as the war continued above four years, had deſtroyed more then 60000 men, and put a ſtop to all Commerce and Trade; The Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals of the <hi>Engliſh, Danes,</hi> and <hi>Hollanders,</hi> uſed all poſſible means to accommodate the difference, but in vain; and in memory of a Battail gained by the King of <hi>Fetu</hi> in this war, was the great Feaſt at <hi>Frederisbourg</hi> I have ſpoken of before. There was a quarrel alſo betwixt the Kings of <hi>Fantin,</hi>
                  <pb n="247" facs="tcp:53662:128"/> and <hi>Sabou,</hi> about a Noble man of <hi>Fantin</hi> who had been in love with a Lady of <hi>Sabou,</hi> and ſtolen her away: the difference not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be compoſed in an amica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble way, both Kings having ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken cognizance of it, they were ſo highly incenſed, they ſell to war immediately, endeavouring to have ſurprized one another as I have mentioned before, for they doe not always come to a pich'd field, but ſometimes endeavour to deſtroy one another by ſurprizes and in-Roads, by burning, pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laging of their Towns, and taking all priſoners they meet.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Daniſh</hi> General told me, that ſometimes a Gentleman (if he were wealthy and rich) would be able to make war againſt his King, ſo ſtrangely are the <hi>Mores</hi> addi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>l to gain, and indeed it is no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der having ſo little affection
<pb n="248" facs="tcp:53662:129"/> or kindneſs for one another, they will ſcarce give a wounded man a drop of water to ſave his life, but will ſee one another die like doggs without any relief, and for the moſt part the firſt that forſake them are their Wives and their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Frederisbourg</hi> we ſaw a poor creature abandoned by all people, and the <hi>Mores</hi> admiring how we durſt come near him: but his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity being only an oppreſſion in his Stomach, our Chyrurgeon cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him with eaſe; we ſaw him afterwards merry and drinking with his Camerades, who uſed him then with a thouſand careſſes, though but eight dayes before his Wife and children had deſerted him, as not knowing his malady.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="249" facs="tcp:53662:129"/>
               <head>Of their Civil and their Criminal Justice, and of the Succeſſions of particular men.</head>
               <p>AMongſt theſe bruitiſh and barbarous Nations, Juſtice has its place, and all crimes are pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhable, though not capitally, but upon great offences. To begin with their criminal Juſtice, he which is accuſed of adultery, or fellony, is immediately cited by the Judge, who having heard what he could ſay, and found his defence to be impertinent, ſets a fine upon him out of hand, which he is obliged to pay down into the hands of the Receiver of the Cuſtoms. If he be not able to pay it, he is ſold as a Slave, and can never redeem him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf afterwards. If the criminal be eſcaped, his Kindred are to pay it, unleſs they will chooſe to leave the Kingdome rather, and
<pb n="250" facs="tcp:53662:130"/> that without hopes of ever coming into it again. If the accuſation be for adultery, (that is to ſay with the firſt wife of another Man) the Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band has power to divorce himſelf from her, but he cannot make her a Slave.</p>
               <p>If it be matter of homicide, fratri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide, or diſobedience to his Majeſties Orders, they are carryed before the King as crimes extraordinary: and if the thing be not very ſoule in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, he condemnes them only in a ſum of Money, one half to be pay'd to his Courtiers who are preſent at the Tryal (which is always in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique) and the other to be pay'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Kings Treaſury. If the Offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er be judged to dye, he is led out of the Town blindfolded, and at the place of execution, run thorow with a Javelin, his head cut off and hung upon a Tree, and the reſt of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy cut in mammocks and thrown into the aire.</p>
               <pb n="251" facs="tcp:53662:130"/>
               <p>If one be accuſed in any Civil, or Criminal caſe, and he deſires to purge himſelf by oath, in drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or eating his <hi>Fetiche,</hi> he is permitted, and if he be found dead the next morning, the informer goes to pot in his place, and pays a good round ſum as a penalty to the King: But if there be ſeveral witneſſes which depoſe againſt the Criminal, in that caſe he is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to ſwear.</p>
               <p>They hate adultery mortally, if committed with the firſt Wives, for which reaſon, they puniſh that as ſeverely as any other Crime, and ſo it happens ſometimes, that out of the malice they doe naturally <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to one another, the Father accuſes the Son, and the Son the Father: If an Offender eſcapes, and is taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, he has a large fine ſet upon his head, and is made a Slave into the Bargain, without all hopes of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</p>
               <pb n="252" facs="tcp:53662:131"/>
               <p>In their civil affairs, whether for debt or any thing elſe, they are ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted before the Judge of that place; which I ſaw my ſelf in the perſon of one called <hi>Pitre</hi> at <hi>Frederisbourg;</hi> being come before the Judge, the Plaintiff ſpake firſt, the Defendant anſwered, &amp; after they had pleaded what they could on both ſides, the Judge pronounced ſentence imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately, which is ſo peremptory and Authentick, there lyes no appeal againſt it in any other place, but 'tis executed forthwith.</p>
               <p>Sometimes the buſineſs is ſo dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult, the Judge will not undertake to determine it, but transferrs it to the King, in which caſes their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and indignation is many times ſo increaſt, that of civil Offenders, they become criminals, and chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenging one another, they come into the field with three or four ſeconds on a ſide, and a reſolution
<pb n="253" facs="tcp:53662:131"/> to decide it by the Sword: If one be killed upon the place, the other is obliged to run out of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom: If he be taken, he is brought before the King, who ſets a good luſty Fine upon him, upon the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of which he is diſcharged: This act of grace has ſuch an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence, and authority upon the people, no body dares aſperſe him in the leaſt with what is paſt, no not ſo much as the Widow nor Children of him that is ſlain, to whom, by the Juſtice of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, a moiety of the Fine does na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally belong: if he has not where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall to pay his Fine, he is made a Slave, and delivered up to them to be ſold into foreign Countries, after which he is never to appear in his own again.</p>
               <p>There was one <hi>Jean Claſse</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of <hi>Acanis,</hi> who came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board us every day, he told us,
<pb n="254" facs="tcp:53662:132"/> that having fought a duel upon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of a civil affair, and killed his adverſary, he had a Fine ſet upon him of an hundred and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venty Marks of Gold, and pay'd it every penny to the King.</p>
               <p>The Judges are ordinarily the Captains of the Towns, that the King may have no more Officers to pay than are neceſſary, &amp; that more advantage might accrew to his Treaſury, by the Feaſts and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents they are oblig'd to make him.</p>
               <p>For their inheritances (which amongſt us make the greateſt part of our ſuits) they have no contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie at all, the next kinſman inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riting always amongſt them, to the excluſion of Wife and Children, who have nothing left them, and are ſometimes conſtrain'd to ſerve for their living, though their Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band &amp; Father died never ſo rich; for which reaſon, the good man u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
<pb n="255" facs="tcp:53662:132"/> them to work betimes, that when he comes to dye, it may be no news to them, but that ſubſiſting by their labour, they need not be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to turn Slaves for a livelyhood.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Of their Beasts, their Birds, and their Fiſh.</head>
               <p>IN theſe Countries there are but few Elephants to be ſeen, but great ſtore of Lions, Tygres, Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pards, Panthers, and other beaſts of prey: they afford likewiſe multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of Oxen, Cows, Hogs, Goats, Sheep, Stags, Roe-bucks, Wild-boars, Deer, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ares, &amp; other beaſts which are very good meat, beſides Civet-Cats, &amp; Apes of ſeveral kinds</p>
               <p>They have Dragons alſo, and a ſort of great Lizards which are good to eat; they have Serpents of unmeaſurable bigneſs, as alſo Crocodils, and Cameleons; theſe
<pb n="256" facs="tcp:53662:133"/> laſt are about the bigneſs of our green Lizards in <hi>France,</hi> and do not change their colour, as is imagined, but having their skins firm and ſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly like glaſs, they repreſent variety of colours according to the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent reflections upon them, which is the ground of that errour.</p>
               <p>Their wild Fowl, and Birds of prey, are Eagles, of which they have ſeveral kinds, but one eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, and which is to be found only in the Kingdom of <hi>Acara;</hi> it has the feathers of a Peacock, the leggs of a Stork, the Beak of a Heron, and a Crown of feathers upon the head. The Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner at <hi>Acara</hi> ſent a live one to <hi>Frederisbourg,</hi> and another dead, which was very good meat, but the live one was ſent to the King of <hi>Denmark;</hi> From hence it is our gray Parrots, with red tayls and wings are brought, which
<pb n="257" facs="tcp:53662:133"/> are obſerved to ſpeak ſooner than from any other place: their <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quittes</hi> are very beautiful to the eye, they have their bodies and their heads green, and as ſmall as Linnets, their beak and feet like Parrots, edg'd with a kind of red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Orange colour, like our gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finch, their muſick is not very plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, but ſome ſay they learn to ſpeak well enough: they have a thouſand ſorts of little birds of all colours, black, red, yellow, green, and mixt, which they take com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly with nets.</p>
               <p>Their Fowl for the Table are Hens, Pigeons, <hi>Pintades</hi> Geeſe, Duck and Mallard, Pheſants and Partridge, but ſmaller than ours, Peacocks, Feldiſars, Cranes, Ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doves, Turtles, and Beet in great multitudes; in ſhort, they may be ſaid to abound with all ſorts of Birds which are viſible amongſt us,
<pb n="258" facs="tcp:53662:134"/> unleſs it be Larks, of which ſort I could never ſee any.</p>
               <p>Having ſpoken before of their Fiſh, and manner of fiſhing, I ſhall ſay nothing of their Fiſh again, but of ſuch as are to be ſeen upon the Coaſt, having indeed nothing to ſay of ſuch as are to be found in their Rivers and Lakes, which are far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther up in the Countrey.</p>
               <p>Their Sea-fiſh are the Gold-fiſh, <hi>Bonnittes, Jacos,</hi> as big as our Calves, Sea-Pikes, freſh-Cod, Tun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny-fiſh, and Thornback; Small fiſh they have in abundance, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially Pilchards, which are fat, and excellently good: they have a ſort of flying fiſh, the which are very good meat, and as white as ſnow: their biggeſt Oyſters (of which they have great quantities all along theſe coaſts) are no bigger than our ſmalleſt, but very good meat, as their Cockles are likewiſe.</p>
               <pb n="259" facs="tcp:53662:134"/>
               <p>It is very dangerous waſhing ones ſelf upon theſe Coaſts, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially near the Iſland of St. <hi>Thomas,</hi> in reſpect of a ravenous ſort of fiſh called <hi>Requiens,</hi> which abound there.</p>
               <p>From <hi>Cape-Verd</hi> to the Iſland of Saint <hi>Thomas,</hi> there is a fiſh which faſtens it ſelf alwayes to the Keel of the Ship, and will not be got off: the <hi>Hollanders</hi> call it the Ordure-fiſh, becauſe it lives only of the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure which is thrown out of the Ship: it is of the ſhape of a <hi>Grou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>din,</hi> but ſhorter, and without ſcales, it has the skin of an Eel, is flead and excoriated like that, and has much of its fat, and taſte alſo: it ſticks ſo faſt to a Ship by the help of a thing it has upon its head, about three fingers broad, and eight fingers long, that there is not a man living can put it off.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="260" facs="tcp:53662:135"/>
               <head>Their Fruits, Herbs, Bread, Millet, Mays, their manner of ſowing and making of Salt.</head>
               <p>THeir Fruits upon theſe Coaſts are Plums, Pears, Oranges, Citrons, Cuckoe-nuts, and Figgs, but of the laſt no great plenty.</p>
               <p>The General of <hi>Frederisbourg</hi> has made a Garden about Muſquetſhot from the Caſtle, where he has Cab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bage, and Roman Lettice, which grow very well, they have excellent Mellons, and the ground covered all over with a kind of Purſlane; Beſides which, they have in many places another herb they call <hi>Tetie,</hi> in its ſtalk and leaf not unlike our Rape, it is pleaſant to eat, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good for the Stomack.</p>
               <p>They have <hi>Potatoes</hi> good ſtore, which the <hi>Hollander</hi> has brought over, and calls them <hi>Field Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choaks,</hi>
                  <pb n="261" facs="tcp:53662:135"/> becauſe they have the taſte of our <hi>Ignames,</hi> which is a thick root very white within, which they cut in trenches, as they do Turneps in <hi>Limouſin:</hi> and this is the bread and ſole nouriſhment of the poor, and Peaſants of that Countrey: their Beans, and their Peas are of ſeveral coulours, red black, violet colour, and gray, and a ſort of Lentils in great abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, which are eaſily baked, and very good meat.</p>
               <p>They make their bread of three ſeveral ſorts of ſeed; ſome of them of Rice, which is very white; but heavy upon the Stomach; others of their <hi>Millet,</hi> which is ſomething browner than ours, but has not ſo good a taſte when 'tis made of that alone; the other of <hi>Mays,</hi> or <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ky</hi> Corn, which is well, and very common, but much better if ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with the flower of <hi>Millet,</hi> which makes it more pleaſant.</p>
               <pb n="262" facs="tcp:53662:136"/>
               <p>When the Month of <hi>April</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, they go to the Receiver of the Kings duties for permiſſion to ſow, (all the fields belonging wholly to the King) having ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained leave, they go up and down rooting up the buſhes from one ſide to the other, and then digging it once or twice, they let it lye for a day or two, and then ſow it with Rice, Millet, or Mays, for the King or the Governour, and when they have done for them, they begin for themſelves.</p>
               <p>When they have done ſowing, they bring all the buſhes they have ſtubb'd up, into a corner of the field, and then burn them, ſinging, and dancing, and throwing about their Palm-wine, in honour of their <hi>Fetiches,</hi> to the end they may ſend them a happy Harveſt: It appears in eight dayes after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and they reap it in three
<pb n="263" facs="tcp:53662:136"/> Months; thoſe who have not ſown, buy their proviſion for the whole year at that time; thoſe who have, and are obliged to go to the Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, carry him ſuch a proportion of gold as they think reaſonable, which the Receiver carries after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to the King, and is very well treated for his pains.</p>
               <p>Their <hi>Mays</hi> or <hi>Turky</hi> Corn, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees beſt with the Hills, their Millet and Rice with the Valleys; they plant their <hi>Mays,</hi> as we do our Peas, but their Millet and Mays is ſown as we do our Corn.</p>
               <p>I did not obſerve many Flowers upon the Coaſts, only one whoſe leaves and ſtalk were as large as our Muſtard-tree: the flower is of an admirable flame colour, but no ſcent at all, they are moſt common about the Iſle of <hi>Saint Thomas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Their Salt is whiter and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than ours, they make it in
<pb n="264" facs="tcp:53662:137"/> great quantity in <hi>January, Febru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary,</hi> and <hi>March,</hi> which they car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry up afterwards higher into the Country, and make good advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage by it, but it has this defect, it will not endure their violent heats, but becomes bitter and acide.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Of their Gold, where it is found, and how, with the variety of works they make of it.</head>
               <p>THe Gold which is tranſport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in ſo great quantities from theſe Coaſts, that it gives them the Epithet of <hi>Golden,</hi> is taken in ſeveral places.</p>
               <p>The Gold of <hi>Axime</hi> is reckon'd the beſt, and is oftentimes found in pieces of two and twenty, or three and twenty Carrets.</p>
               <p>The Gold of <hi>Acara</hi> or <hi>Taſore,</hi> is ſomething leſs: that of <hi>Acanis</hi>
                  <pb n="265" facs="tcp:53662:137"/> and <hi>Achema</hi> is next, and the worſt of all is the Gold of <hi>Fetu.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The manner of taking it, is known only by the report of the <hi>Negroes,</hi> and (if they ſpeak truth) is ſeveral wayes.</p>
               <p>Thoſe of <hi>Axime</hi> and <hi>Achema</hi> find it in the ſands of their Rivers, in powder: &amp; 'tis to be ſuppoſed would they dig at the feet of the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains where theſe Rivers ariſe, 'tis probable they would meet with greater proportions, ſeeing by their own confeſſions, after a luſty ſhower their plenty is increaſt, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which ſcore they have this ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition amongſt them, that when they want Gold, they pray to their <hi>Fetiches</hi> to ſend them good ſtore of rain, and they are ſure to be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd, as I hinted before.</p>
               <p>The Gold of <hi>Acara</hi> comes from the Mountain of <hi>Taffou,</hi> ſome thirty leagues diſtance, from the Town,
<pb n="266" facs="tcp:53662:138"/> which is three dayes journey up in the Countrey: One of the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of the Blacks had a great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to have carried me to the place, &amp; would have leſt the Kings Brother and Son in hoſtage: but the water ſailing as we were ready to go, we could not proceed in our deſign. He told us that the Mine belonged to the King, that there was no more to be done but to dig about the Mountain, and they would have gold enough; that thoſe who found it were to have one Moyety, and the King the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that he had an ingot of gold before his gate, which by the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal confeſſion of all the <hi>Negroes,</hi> was bigger than the <hi>Fetiche</hi> of the whole Countrey, and taken out of this Mountain.</p>
               <p>An Officer at <hi>Frederisbourg,</hi> who has been ſeveral times at <hi>Fetu</hi> and <hi>Acanis,</hi> aſſured me, that thoſe
<pb n="267" facs="tcp:53662:138"/> two Kings had each of them before the gates of their Palaces, a golden <hi>Fetiche</hi> of a vaſt bigneſs, not ſo big indeed as that of the King of <hi>Fetu,</hi> but yet full as big as a Peck.</p>
               <p>The gold of <hi>Acanis</hi> and <hi>Fetu,</hi> is found in the earth by digging, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times more, and ſometimes leſs; he which diſcovers a Mine has one half, &amp; the King the other: it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver above twenty or one &amp; twenty Carrets; it is melted down at nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place, but brought to us aboard as it is taken out of the ground.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Daniſh</hi> General has an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got of gold, taken out of the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of <hi>Tafou,</hi> which weighs ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Marks, and about the ſeventh part of an Ounce. It was a preſent ſent him by the King of <hi>Acara,</hi> when his Army was beaten by the Seigneur of <hi>Acara,</hi> and he protect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him in his Fort.</p>
               <p>When the <hi>French</hi> and the <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugais</hi>
                  <pb n="268" facs="tcp:53662:139"/> frequented theſe Coaſts, the Natives knew not the value of their gold, but ſince other Nations have been admitted, (and the <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers</hi> eſpecially) they have learn'd, by their earneſt deſire to have it, that 'tis of more price, and do now hold it ſo dear, and ſtand ſo high in their demands, 'tis al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt inſupportable.</p>
               <p>Beſides that, they have found out new ways of increaſing their quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tities by adulterating it, and ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling it with little pieces of Copper, which they call <hi>Quaquara,</hi> or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe with Braſs: the chief place for this Artifice is <hi>Commendo,</hi> where I may ſay boldly, there are the beſt cheats in the world.</p>
               <p>Yet theſe practices are only a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the leſſer ſort of Merchants of whom great care is to be taken, for they are ſo ingenious in this kind, there is not a cheat or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery
<pb n="269" facs="tcp:53662:139"/> that can fall under the inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of mankind, which they do not uſe for the circumvention of ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.</p>
               <p>They pretend very much to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the <hi>Europeans</hi> in their working of their Gold, &amp; to ſpeak truth they are ſo happy as to ſurpaſs all the workmen I ever ſaw; their files are much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iner than ours, and will make their work as fine as our <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligranne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The King of <hi>Fetu</hi> has a Caſque, and a ſuit of Arms of beaten Gold, admirably well done. Amongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things, they make great quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tities of Bracelets of poliſh'd Gold, and of thoſe <hi>Fetiches</hi> which they wear upon their heads, as thin as paper: But above all things they tranſcend in their hatbands, which they make of threads as fine as any hair. Their Kings have their Veſſels in Gold ſtill, their
<pb n="270" facs="tcp:53662:140"/> working Goldſmiths making eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing they fancy, and every thing that comes into their heads.</p>
               <p>The Wives and Daughters of their Kings, Merchants, and Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of that Country, are ſo well la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with Rings, Bracelets, &amp; <hi>Feti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches</hi> of Gold, eſpecially when they go to their <hi>Balls,</hi> that they have ſometimes in ſuch trifles, to the weight of 20, or 25 Marks of Gold, and the men to thirty or forty.</p>
               <p>It is ſo incredibly plentiful in thoſe parts, that a King upon an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Feſtival will diſtribute two hundred Marks of Gold amongſt his Courtiers, and ſometimes more; for which reaſon, the <hi>Negroes</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to have liberal Kings, that their largeſſes may be more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, and the Gold (not being lockt up in their private Coffers) may expend and circulate through the whole Kingdome.</p>
               <pb n="271" facs="tcp:53662:140"/>
               <p>Nor is the dearneſs of their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions, a ſmall argument of the plenty aforeſaid; a Fricaſſee of Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets bought of the <hi>Mores</hi> will coſt two Crowns at leaſt, a Pot of their Palm-wine, as it comes intirely from the tree, a Crown, and is no more than three of our <hi>Chopines</hi> at <hi>Paris.</hi> 'Tis true amongſt themſelves things are not altogether ſo dear, but having taken up an opinion that the Whites make treble advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of whatever they buy of them, they ſell every thing they can poſſibly at that rate to them: their fiſh is ſomewhat cheaper indeed, &amp; for ten pence one may have as much as will ſuffice ten men.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding all the pains I did take, I could never inform my ſelf further concerning their Gold, or their manner of taking it out of the Mines: talk to a thouſand perſons of it, and they will all
<pb n="272" facs="tcp:53662:141"/> tell you ſeveral ſtories, not that they are ignorant themſelves, but their diffidence of the Whites is ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincibly great, they will never be perſwaded to impart it to them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Of the return of our Veſſel for <hi>Europe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe immenſe profits that are made upon theſe Coaſts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing obvious to all people, it would be ſuperfluous to ſpeak any more of them: by the univerſal conſent of the whole world, it is agreed, that theſe Voyages are more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and advantageous than any other, which appears by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary attempts have been made by all Nations of <hi>Europe,</hi> to make themſelves abſolute Maſters there, and evinceth the truth of what I have ſaid, to any one that
<pb n="273" facs="tcp:53662:141"/> imagines the contrary, ſo that it remains now, that I ſpeak only one word of our return.</p>
               <p>Having finiſh'd our trading de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, we weigh'd Anchor from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Frederisbourg,</hi> the twentieth of <hi>April,</hi> &amp; ſail'd directly for the Port of <hi>Saint Thomas,</hi> (which is an Iſland belonging to the <hi>Portugais,</hi> ſcituated directly under the Line) to ſupply our ſelves with victuals for ſo long a Voyage. The firſt two dayes we ſteer'd our courſe Eaſt and by South, the two next Eaſt South-Eaſt, and the two next full Eaſt; after which, we diſcover'd the Iſland of <hi>Saint Thomas,</hi> and came to an Anchor before the Caſtle on the ſixth of <hi>May,</hi> ſeven dayes after our departure from <hi>Frederisbourg,</hi> having made in all twenty ſix leagues and upwards.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="274" facs="tcp:53662:142"/>
               <head>The Deſcription of the Iſle of <hi>St. Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> which lies under the Line.</head>
               <p>ON the 8th. of <hi>May</hi> we made a viſit to the Governour of the Caſtle, who received us with great civility, but would not be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to permit us to go into the Town; he gave Orders to his Lieutenant to treat us with all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, which he was not able to perform himſelf, by reaſon of an indiſpoſition that was upon him at that time.</p>
               <p>He is a little man, well propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd, about 40 or 50 years of age, his name is <hi>Acoſta,</hi> a fierce quick man, but very civil. That night a Captain of the Fort came aboard us, to whom we gave an account of what proviſions we wanted, and the Governour order'd us to be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed the laſt day in Rogation week.</p>
               <pb n="275" facs="tcp:53662:142"/>
               <p>Every day whilſt we lay there at Anchor, our men went to a little River which runs hard by into the Sea, to provide our ſelves with freſh water, which is indeed the beſt in all <hi>Africk,</hi> for we kept it a year afterwards, and it was as good and as ſweet as at the firſt day. Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all the time we were there, not one perſon of our Crew was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to go on ſhore, but my ſelf, who had that priviledge by being a Frenchman.</p>
               <p>I lay on ſhore three nights, but deſiring the Governours leave that our Notary might do the ſame for the benefit of his health, he told me for my ſelf all places were free, I might go whether, and buy what I pleaſed, but for the Notary he could not permit it, he being a <hi>Flemming;</hi> that if our whole Equipage had been <hi>French,</hi> they ſhould all have had
<pb n="276" facs="tcp:53662:143"/> the ſame liberty, but that the <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugais</hi> had too rational a jealouſie of the <hi>Dutch</hi> to allow them a free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome that had not been practis'd ſince the Iſland came into their hands; that the Town was then a rebuilding, and that there ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained the foot-ſteps of the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs and deſolations the <hi>Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> had made there, eſpecially amongſt their Churches, which were very beautiful.</p>
               <p>The Iſland of <hi>Saint Thomas</hi> is about ſixty leagues in circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, it has a Biſhoprick in it, and a Cathedral (which they were then in repairing) not inferiour in bigneſs to <hi>Saint Meredick</hi> in <hi>Paris,</hi> but much more beautifull, and neat, the Muſick and Chapter were maintained at the King of <hi>Portugals</hi> charge: Beſides that they had <hi>Negroes</hi> to their Prieſts, I was much pleas'd to hear the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
<pb n="277" facs="tcp:53662:143"/> 
                  <hi>Moriſh</hi> Boys, which ſerve there in the Quire, and ſing without Notes or Books, as exactly as our Choriſters in <hi>France,</hi> which I obſerved in their Proceſſion, the firſt day of their <hi>Rogations:</hi> all the <hi>Mores</hi> in that Iſland are Chriſtians: the Town conſiſts of about five hundred houſes, the moſt part of Wood, ſince the <hi>Hollanders</hi> took it, and burn'd it.</p>
               <p>The general opinion is, that this Iſland is not healthful, but they have all things neceſſary for the life of man, in that plenty and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance, that 'tis a Miracle to me conſidering the heat of the Climat, and the unwholeſomneſs of the air. The Sugar which comes from hence, is cryed up above all the Sugar in the world.</p>
               <p>They have a fair <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tadel</hi> built upon the Sea-ſide, on the Eaſt-ſide of the Town (with its
<pb n="278" facs="tcp:53662:144"/> gate towards the North) about the diſtance of Muſquet ſhot; the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure is ſquare, fortified with four good Baſtions, lined with Free-ſtone, planted with ſixty pieces of braſs Canon, carrying from eight to eight and forty pound bullet. But ſo many Authors having writ of it at large, it would but importune the Reader to enlarge any farther.</p>
               <p>Upon Aſcenſion day we weigh'd Anchor, and ſet ſail for <hi>Europe,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſaluted the Caſtle with 5 Guns, and received their complement in three, ſteering South-weſt, though the wind ſtood South-Eaſt, and is ſo conſtantly upon thoſe Coaſts, the next day we diſcovered <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bou,</hi> another Iſland in the poſſeſſion of the <hi>Portugais;</hi> at which place we began to alter our courſe Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, as we did many times after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, according to the diſcretion of our Pilots.</p>
               <pb n="279" facs="tcp:53662:144"/>
               <p>We paſt on the back-ſide of <hi>Scotland,</hi> coaſting upon the Iſles <hi>de Terro,</hi> which are under the Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> and upon the Coaſts of <hi>Norway,</hi> where meeting with ſome <hi>Dutch</hi> Ships, we received the firſt news of the Treaty at <hi>Breda,</hi> which was the moſt remarkable thing in our paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage; for our Pilots having been miſtaken, and run to the wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, more than two hundred leagues too much, I can ſay but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of our return.</p>
               <p>In ſhort, on the 29th of <hi>August</hi> we found our ſelves at the mouth of the <hi>Texel,</hi> where for want of a fair wind our Ship was forc'd to ride at Anchor till the firſt of <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember,</hi> at which time we entred, and on the fourth following came to an Anchor before <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> where all the Officers, (except the Captain and the Secretary) were
<pb n="280" facs="tcp:53662:145"/> arrived the laſt of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> by the convenience of a Shallop with Oares, which do uſually come out to all ſuch Ships as are to go into the <hi>Texel,</hi> for that purpoſe.</p>
               <p>And thus was our Voyage con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, having ſpent in our jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, our ſtay, and return, about nine Months and a half, without any diſaſter, or the loſs of any more than one man, who dyed as we were paſſing the Line, of a Diſſentery he had got at the Iſland of <hi>Saint Thomas,</hi> by eating too great a quantity of their Sugar, and ſweet meats; all the reſt both Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers and Soulders were continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in health, lively, brisk, and well diſpoſed, without the leaſt malady or ſickneſs in the world. For which, God be praiſed.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:53662:145"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
